Next we turn our attention to encoding data
as sequences of 0's and 1's, a string of bits.
An encoding is an unambiguous mapping between
bit strings and the members of the set of
data to be encoded.
For example, suppose we have a set of four
symbols -- A, B, C, and D – and we want
to use bit strings to encode messages constructed
of these symbols, for example "ABBA".
If we choose to encode the message one character
at a time, our encoding would assign a unique
bit string to each symbol.
Since we have four symbols, we might choose
a unique two-bit string for each: "A" could
be "00", B = "01", C = "10", and D = "11".
This would be called a "fixed-length encoding"
since the bit strings used to represent the
symbols all have the same length.
The encoding for the message "ABBA" would
be "00-01-01-00".
And we can run the process backwards: given
a bit string and the encoding key, we can
look up the next bits in the bit string, using
the key to determine the symbol they represent.
"00" would be decoded as "A", "01" as B and
so on.
We can also use bit strings of different lengths
to encode symbols -- this is called a variable-length
encoding.
So A could be "01", B = "1", C = "000" and
D = "001".
"ABBA" would be encoded as "01-1-1-01".
We'll see that carefully constructed variable-length
encodings are useful for the efficient encoding
of messages where the symbols occur with different
probabilities.
We have to be careful that the encoding is
unambiguous!
Suppose we had decided to encode A as "0",
B as "1", C as "10" and D as "11".
The encoding for "ABBA" would be "0-1-1-0".
Looking good since that encoding is shorter
than either of the previous two encodings.
Now let's try to decode this bit string -- oops.
Using the encoding key, we can unfortunately
arrive at several decodings: "ABBA" of course,
but also "ADA" or "ABC" depending on how we
group the bits.
This attempt at specifying an encoding has
failed since the message cannot be interpreted
unambiguously.
Graphically we can represent an unambiguous
encoding as a binary tree, labeling the branches
from each tree node with "0" and "1", placing
the symbols to be encoded as the leaves of
the tree.
If you build a binary tree for a proposed
encoding and find that there are no symbols
labeling interior nodes and exactly one symbol
at each leaf, then your encoding is good to
go!
For example, consider the encoding shown on
the left.
It takes just a second to draw the corresponding
binary tree.
The symbol B is distance 1 from the root of
the tree, along an arc labeled "0".
A is distance two, and C and D are distance
3.
If we receive an encoded message, for example
"01111", we can decode it using successive
bits of the encoding to identify a path from
the root of tree, descending step-by-step
until we come to leaf, then repeating the
process starting at the root again, until
all the bits in the encoded message have been
consumed.
So the message from the sheep is: "0" takes
us from the root to the leaf B, which is our
first decoded symbol.
Then "1-1" takes us to A and the next "1-1"
results in a second A.
The final decoded message -- "BAA" -- is not
totally unexpected, at least from an American
sheep.