In this problem, we are given a 4 state transition
diagram.
We know that it represents a Moore machine
because the output is a function of only the
current state.
We are also given a partially filled out truth
table and our first job is to fill in the
missing entries in the truth table.
In order to do this, we need to find the correlation
between states A -- D and their S1S0 encoding.
We begin by looking at the output column.
We know that only state A has an output of
1, so state A's encoding must be 00 and OUT=1
regardless of the input because it is a Moore
machine.
We also know that from state A on a 1 input,
the FSM moves to state B.
According to the truth table from state 00
(which is A), on a 1 input, we move to state
01.
That means that state B's encoding is 01.
We continue in this manner, now following
the transitions from state B.
According to the diagram, when IN = 0, we
move to state D.
So looking up that transition in our truth
table, tells us that state D's encoding is
10.
We also see in our state diagram that starting
at state B when IN=1, we move back to state
A which we now know to be 00.
So we can fill in the next missing entry in
our truth table.
Now that we have determined the encoding for
states A, B, and D.
We know that the remaining encoding is for
state C and that is 11.
At this point, we have all the information
we need to complete filling out the missing
entries in the truth table.
Looking at the row where the current state
is 10 (state D) and IN = 1 and the corresponding
transition in the state diagram, shows us
that in this case we go back to state D.
Since the encoding of state D is 10, the S0'
entry is 0.
Because this is a Moore machine, we also know
that the output associated with current state
D, regardless of the input, is 0, so the missing
output entry is 0.
Finally, from state 11 (which is state C),
when IN = 1, we see from the state diagram
that we transition to state A which is state
00, so the remaining missing S0' value is
0.
We now want to determine whether or not there
are any equivalent states in this FSM.
In a Moore machine, equivalent states have
the same output, and the same input transitions.
This rules out state A because it is the only
one that has a 1 output.
Taking a closer look at states B, C, and D,
we can see that both states B and C transition
to state D on a 0 input, and to state A on
a 1 input.
In addition, the output value is 0 for both
of them.
This means that states B and C are equivalent
and can be merged into 1 to turn this into
a 3 state FSM.