Two's complement representation is a way of
representing both positive and negative numbers
in binary.
Let's take a look at an example of a positive
number represented in two's complement in
order to begin understanding how this representation
works.
If we look at the number, 001000, the way
that we determine the value of this two's
complement number is as follows.
Each bit represents a power of 2, with the
right most bit representing 20,
the next bit is 21, then 22,
23, 24, and finally
-25.
Having the most significant bit represent
a negative power of 2 rather than a positive
power allows us to express both positive and
negative numbers with our notation.
If your number has a 0 in a certain position,
then the power of 2 associated with that position
is not present in your number.
If the number has a 1, then that tells us
that the corresponding power of 2 makes up
part of the number's value.
To figure out the value of the number 001000,
we see that there is a single 1 which is in
the 23 position.
So this number is equal to 23 which
equals 8.
Note that if I wanted to represent the same
number 8 using a larger number of binary bits,
I would simply add some leading zeroes to
my positive number.
For example, the number 8 represented in 8-bits
two's complement is the same as the 6-bit
representation but with 2 additional leading
zeroes.
Now let's try a negative number.
Negative numbers in 2's complement representation
always have a 1 in their most significant
bit (MSB).
What is the value of 101100?
We apply the same logic as before, now we
have a 1 in bit positions 2, 3, and 5.
That means that this number is equal to -25
+ 23 + 22 which equals
-32 + 8 + 4 = -20.
In the case of negative numbers, if we wanted
to represent the same value, -20 using more
bits, one would simply need to append leading
1's to the number to end up with the same
value.
For example, -20, using 8 bits is 11101100.
Let's check that this is correct.
This number is equal to -27 + 26
+ 25 + 23 + 22
which is equal to -128 + 64 + 32 + 8 + 4 which
is -128 + 108 and that is equal to -20.
Let's take a look at the range of numbers
that can be represented using N-bit 2's complement.
Let's begin with our example of 6-bits.
The largest positive number in that case is
0 followed by five 1's (011111) which is equal
to 20 + 21 + 22
+ 23 + 24 which is equal
to 1 + 2 + 4 + 8 + 16 which equals 31 which
is also equal to 25-1.
The most negative number using 6 bits is 1
followed by five 0's (100000) which equals
-25 with no positive component
added to the number and that is equal to -32.
So in general for N-bits, the 2's complement
number can range from -2N-1 through
2N-1-1.
An easy way of converting between positive
and negative 2's complement numbers is by
flipping all the bits and adding 1.
For example, earlier we calculated that 101100
= -20.
If I take this number and flip all of the
bits, I get 010011.
I then add 1 to that, which results in 010100.
This number is = 22 + 24
= 4 + 16 = 20.
This tells us that our original number 101100
was equal to -20.
The same methodology can be applied in reverse.
If you start with a positive number 20 = 010100,
and you flip all the bits and add 1, you get
101011 + 1 = 101100.
This brings us back to our original number
which is -20.
So to easily determine the value of a negative
2's complement number, one flips all the bits
and adds 1 to find the corresponding positive
number, say X, which in turn means that your
original negative number had a value of -X.