The page map provides the context for interpreting
virtual addresses, i.e., it provides the information
needed to correctly determine where to find
a virtual address in main memory or secondary
storage.
Several programs may be simultaneously loaded
into main memory, each with its own context.
Note that the separate contexts ensure that
the programs don't interfere which each other.
For example, the physical location for virtual
address 0 in one program will be different
than the physical location for virtual address
0 in another program.
Each program operates independently in its
own virtual address space.
It's the context provided by the page map
that allows them to coexist and share a common
physical memory.
So we need to switch contexts when switching
programs.
This is accomplished by reloading the page
map.
In a timesharing system, the CPU will periodically
switch from running one program to another,
giving the illusion that multiple programs
are each running on their own virtual machine.
This is accomplished by switching contexts
when switching the CPU state to the next program.
There's a privileged set of code called the
operating system (OS) that manages the sharing
of one physical processor and main memory
amongst many programs, each with its own CPU
state and virtual address space.
The OS is effectively creating many virtual
machines and choreographing their execution
using a single set of shared physical resources.
The OS runs in a special OS context, which
we call the kernel.
The OS contains the necessary exception handlers
and timesharing support.
Since it has to manage physical memory, it's
allowed to access any physical location as
it deals with page faults, etc.
Exceptions in running programs cause the hardware
to switch to the kernel context, which we
call entering "kernel mode".
After the exception handling is complete,
execution of the program resumes in what we
call "user mode".
Since the OS runs in kernel mode it has privileged
access to many hardware registers that are
inaccessible in user mode.
These include the MMU state, I/O devices,
and so on.
User-mode programs that need to access, say,
the disk, need to make a request to the OS
kernel to perform the operation, giving the
OS the chance to vet the request for appropriate
permissions, etc.
We'll see how all of this works in an upcoming
lecture.
User-mode programs (aka applications) are
written as if they have access to the entire
virtual address space.
They often obey the same conventions such
as the address of the first instruction in
the program, the initial value for the stack
pointer, etc.
Since all these virtual addresses are interpreted
using the current context, by controlling
the contexts the OS can ensure that the programs
can coexist without conflict.
The diagram on the right shows a standard
plan for organizing the virtual address space
of an application.
Typically the first virtual page is made inaccessible,
which helps catch errors involving references
to uninitialized (i.e., zero-valued) pointers.
Then come some number of read-only pages that
hold the application's code and perhaps the
code from any shared libraries it uses.
Marking code pages as read-only avoids hard-to-find
bugs where errant data accesses inadvertently
change the program!
Then there are read-write pages holding the
application's statically allocated data structures.
The rest of the virtual address space is divided
between two data regions that can grow over
time.
The first is the application's stack, used
to hold procedure activation records.
Here we show it located at the lower end of
the virtual address space since our convention
is that the stack grows towards higher addresses.
The other growable region is the heap, used
when dynamically allocating storage for long-lived
data structures.
"Dynamically" means that the allocation and
deallocation of objects is done by explicit
procedure calls while the application is running.
In other words, we don't know which objects
will be created until the program actually
executes.
As shown here, as the heap expands it grows
towards lower addresses.
The page fault handler knows to allocate new
pages when these regions grow.
Of course, if they ever meet somewhere in
the middle and more space is needed, the application
is out of luck - it's run out of virtual memory!