In this problem, we will examine how compilers
translate high level language descriptions
into assembly language.
We will be given several code fragments and
asked to help the compiler in figuring out
the dependencies of the program so that it
produces valid code.
Let's begin with the code fragment: a = b
+ 3*c.
We can assume that our variables: a, b, and
c are stored in memory.
We can also assume that registers may be used
to store intermediate results.
Given the following partially completed assembly
code, let's determine the missing values that
the compiler would have had to determine.
We begin with XXX which is the first instruction.
The first instruction is trying to put the
value of c into register R1.
Since c comes from memory, that means that
instruction XXX must be a LD operation where
c is the address of the variable to be loaded.
Note that LD(c, R1) is actually a macro instruction
that is equal to LD(R31, c, R1).
The load operation would add the constant
c to the value of register R31, which is always
0, thus ending up with the address c as the
source address of the load operation.
R1 is a temporary register that will hold
the value of variable c.
Next, we need to multiply c by 3.
Multiply operations are generally very expensive,
so it is the compilers job to figure out that
this operation could potentially be achieved
by 2 simpler and faster operations.
The comment tells us that it first tries to
compute 2 * c and store that result into R0.
Since R1 = c, and the constant in this operation
is a 1, we need to realize that the inexpensive
operation that the compiler would use for
this is a logical shift to the left by one
position.
In binary, this produces the same result as
multiplying a number by 2.
So YYY = SHLC.
Note that we use the constant version of the
SHL operation since the amount to shift is
given by a constant in our instruction rather
than being read from another register.
The next instruction is provided for us and
it adds R0 which equals 2*c to R1 which equals
c in order to produce 3*c.
This intermediate result is then stored back
into R0.
Next we want to once again get the value of
a variable from memory.
As we saw before, XXX = LD in order to load
the contents of address b into register R1.
We are almost done, we now just need to add
R1 = b to R0 = 3*c and then store the result
back into memory variable a.
Since the store instruction is using R0 as
its source, that means that ZZZ must also
be R0 so that the correct value ends up in
variable a.
Next, we will take a look at how a conditional
statement would be compiled into assembly
language.
The statement says that if a is greater than
b then c should be assigned the value 17.
Once again we are given the semi-complete
translation of the high level language code
into beta assembly.
For this example, we first load the values
of our variables a and b into temporary registers
R0 and R1.
Now we want to check if a is greater than
b and if so set c = 17.
We know that XXX must be some kind of beta
comparison operation.
However, the beta does not provide a compare
greater than operation, so instead we need
to make use of the compare less than (CMPLT)
or compare less than or equal (CMPLE) operations.
Since we see that the store into label c is
skipped when the code branches to label _L2,
we want to make sure that the branch is not
taken when a is greater than b.
This is equivalent to the branch being taken
when a is less than or equal to b.
So if we make XXX = CMPLE of R0, which equals
a, and R1, which equals b, then the result
stored into R0 will be 1 if a <= b.
We then set YYY to R0 to ensure that we take
the branch when a  b.
Finally, if we set ZZZ = 17, then when the
branch is not taken, we will move 17 into
R0 and then store that value into the location
pointed to by address c.
So the complete translation of this conditional
statement to beta assembly is shown here.
For this next code segment, we are going to
take a look at how a compiler would convert
array accesses into beta code.
Once again we are given partially completed
assembly code to help us understand how the
compiler translates this high level code into
beta assembly.
We begin with a load of the value stored at
location i into register R0.
I is the index into our array.
However, since the beta is byte addressed,
but it deals with 32 bit values, that means
that each array element requires 4 bytes of
storage.
So in order to point to the correct location
in memory, we need to multiply i by 4.
As we saw earlier, shifting to the left by
1 bit is equivalent to multiplying by 2, so
here we shift to the left by 2 bits in order
to multiply by 4.
So XXX = 2.
Now that R0 = 4 * i, in order to load a[i],
we would load the location a + 4*i.
In order to load a[i-1], we need to load the
location that is 4 bytes before that, so location
a + 4*i – 4.
This means that in this load operation which
actually wants to load a[i-1], we need to
set YYY = a-4.
So this load operation places array element
a[i-1] into R1.
Now we want to store the contents of R1 into
array element a[i] which is located at address
a + 4*i.
Since R0 already equals 4*i, then adding a
to R0 will give us the desired destination
address of our store.
This means that we just need to set ZZZ to
R1 since that is the value that we want to
store into a[i].
Let's take a look at one last example.
Here we have a variable sum that is initialized
to 0, followed by a loop that increments the
value of sum by i for every value of i between
0 and 9.
Our partial mostly completed compiled code
is shown here.
The first thing that the compiler does, is
it initializes the two variables sum and i
to 0.
This is done by storing the value of register
R31, which is always 0 in the beta, into the
locations pointed to by sum and by i.
_L7 is a label that indicates the beginning
of our loop.
The first thing that needs to happen in the
loop is to load the current values of sum
and i from memory.
Next, sum should be incremented by i.
Since R0 is stored back into sum, we want
XXX = R0 to be the destination register of
the ADD.
Now the loop index needs to be incremented.
Since R1 = i, that means that we want to increment
R1 by 1,so YYY = R1.
Finally, we need to determine whether the
loop needs to be repeated or we are done.
This is done by checking whether i is less
than 10.
The beta provides the CMPLTC operation to
do just that.
Since R1 holds the latest value of i, comparing
R1 to the constant 10 will produce the result
we want in R0.
So ZZZ = 10.
If the comparison was true, then we need to
repeat the loop so we branch back to _L7.
If not, we proceed to the instruction after
the branch.