In order for multiple processes to be able
to run on the same computer, using a shared
address space, we need to have an operating
system that controls which process gets to
run at any given point in time and ensures
that the state that is currently loaded into
the system is the state of the current process.
Through the following example we will take
a closer look at how the operating system
for the beta works.
We begin by examining the code responsible
for maintaining the current processor state
as well as scheduling which process should
run at any given point in time.
The operating system uses a structure called
MState to keep track of the value of the 32
registers for each of the running processes.
The UserMState variable holds the state of
the currently running process.
The ProcTbl or process table, holds all the
necessary state for each of the processes
that runs on the machine.
For each process, it stores the value of all
of its registers in the State variable.
Additional state may be stored per process.
Examples of some additional state that would
go in a process table are a page map per process
if we want to use virtual memory.
Another example, is a keyboard identifier,
that associates hardware with a particular
process.
The Cur, or current variable, holds the index
of the currently running process.
When we want to switch control from one process
to another, we call the Scheduler.
The Scheduler first stores the state of the
currently running process into the process
table.
Next, it increments the current process by
1.
If the current process was process N – 1,
then it goes back to process 0.
Finally, it reloads the user variable with
the state for the new current process.
In order to be able to run a diagnostic program
on one process that samples the values in
the PC of another process, a supervisor call
named SamplePC is provided for you.
The C portion of the SVC handler is provided
for you here.
It is incomplete, so our first goal is to
determine what should replace the ???.
We are told that the way SamplePC SVC works
is that it takes a process number p in R0,
and returns in R1 the value currently in the
program counter of process p.
The handler shown here reads register 0 from
the UserMState data structure and stores the
value into variable p.
This is the number of the process that is
to be monitored.
In order to determine the value of the PC
of process p, one can look up the value of
the XP register that was saved for process
p the last time process p was run.
The XP register holds the value of the next
PC address.
So reading the XP register from ProcTbl[p]
tells us the next value of the pc for process
p.
The pc value is to be returned in register
R1 of the current program.
This means that the missing code is UserMState.Regs[1]
and that should be assigned the value of pc.
Suppose you have a compute-bound process consisting
of a single 10,000 instruction loop.
You use the SamplePC supervisor call to sample
the PC while running this loop.
You notice many repeated values in the results
of the SamplePC code.
You realize that the reason this is happening
is because every time your profiling process
gets scheduled to run, it makes many SamplePC
calls but the other processes aren't running
so you are getting the same sampled PC multiple
times.
How can the repeated samples be avoided?
To avoid repeated samples, we add a call to
Scheduler() in our SamplePC handler.
This ensures that every time that the profiler
process is scheduled, it only samples a single
PC value and then let's another process run.
Suppose that you continue using the original
version of your SamplePC handler, which does
not call Scheduler, and you use it to test
this code which repeatedly calls the GetKey()
supervisor call to read a character from the
keyboard, and then calls the WrCh() supervisor
call to write the character that was just
read.
We want to answer the question of which PC
value will be the one reported the most often.
Address 0x100 which is the address of the
GetKey() call is reported the most often because
most of the time when GetKey() is called,
there is no key stroke waiting to be processed.
This means that the GetKey() call will get
processed over and over again until there
is finally a key to process.
The result of this is that the PC value that
shows up the most often is 0x100.
The last question we want to consider is what
behavior is observed when the profiler which
is running in process 0 profiles process 0
itself.
Assume that the profiler code consists primarily
of one big loop which has a single call to
the SamplePC supervisor call at instruction
0x1000.
The rest of the loop processes the data that
was collected by the SamplePC call.
The question we want to answer is what is
observed in the SamplePC results.
We are given 4 choices to select from.
The first choice to consider is whether or
not all the sampled PC values point to the
kernel OS code.
This choice is false because if it were true
it would mean that you somehow managed to
interrupt kernel code which is not allowed
by the beta.
The next choice to consider is whether the
sampled PC is always 0x1004.
This seems like it might be a correct choice
because the SamplePC supervisor call is at
address 0x1000, so storing PC + 4 would result
in 0x1004 being stored into the UserMState.Regs[XP].
However, if you look closely at the SamplePC
handler you see that the XP register is read
from the ProcTbl.
But the UserMState regs are only written to
ProcTbl when Scheduler() is called, so reading
the value from ProcTbl would provide the last
value of the PC when process 0 was last interrupted.
To get the correct value, you would need to
read UserMState.Regs[XP] instead.
The third choice is that the SamplePC call
never returns.
There is no reason for this to be true.
Finally, the last choice is "None of the above".
Since none of the other choices were correct,
this is the correct answer.