In the next section we're going to start our
discussion on how to actually engineer the
bit encodings we'll use in our circuitry,
but first we'll need a way to evaluate the
efficacy of an encoding.
The entropy of a random variable is average
amount of information received when learning
the value of the random variable.
The mathematician's name for "average" is
"expected value"; that's what the capital
E means.
We compute the average in the obvious way:
we take the weighted sum, where the amount
of information received when learning of particular
choice i -- that's the log-base-2 of 1/p_i
-- is weighted by the probability of that
choice actually happening.
Here's an example.
We have a random variable that can take on
one of four values: A, B, C or D.
The probabilities of each choice are shown
in the table, along with the associated information
content.
Now we'll compute the entropy using the probabilities
and information content.
So we have the probability of A (1/3) times
its associated information content (1.58 bits),
plus the probability of B times its associated
information content, and so on.
The result is 1.626 bits.
This is telling us that a clever encoding
scheme should be able to do better than simply
encoding each symbol using 2 bits to represent
which of the four possible values is next.
Food for thought!
We'll discuss this further in the third section
of this chapter.
So, what is the entropy telling us?
Suppose we have a sequence of data describing
a sequence of values of the random variable
X.
If, on the average, we use less than H(X)
bits to transmit each piece of information
in the sequence, we will not be sending enough
information to resolve the uncertainty about
the values.
In other words, the entropy is a lower bound
on the number of bits we need to transmit.
Getting less than this number of bits wouldn't
be good if the goal was to unambiguously describe
the sequence of values -- we'd have failed
at our job!
On the other hand, if we send, on the average,
more than H(X) bits to describe the sequence
of values, we will not be making the most
effective use of our resources, since the
same information might have been able to be
represented with fewer bits.
This is okay, but perhaps with some insights
we could do better.
Finally, if we send, on the average, exactly
H(X) bits, then we'd have the perfect encoding.
Alas, perfection is, as always, a tough goal,
so most of the time we'll have to settle for
getting close.
In the final set of exercises for this section,
try computing the entropy for various scenarios.