Given a set of symbols
and their probabilities,
Huffman’s Algorithm tells us
how to construct an optimal
variable-length encoding.
By “optimal” we mean that,
assuming we’re encoding each
symbol one-at-a-time, no other
variable-length code will have
a shorter expected length.
The algorithm builds the
binary tree for the encoding
from the bottom up.
Start by choosing the two
symbols with the smallest
probability (which
means they have
highest information content
and should have the longest
encoding).
If anywhere along
the way, two symbols
have the same probability,
simply choose one arbitrarily.
In our running example, the
two symbols with the lowest
probability are C and D.
Combine the symbols
as a binary subtree,
with one branch labeled
“0” and the other “1”.
It doesn’t matter which
labels go with which branch.
Remove C and D from
our list of symbols,
and replace them with the newly
constructed subtree, whose root
has the associated
probability 1/6,
the sum of the probabilities
of its two branches.
Now continue, at each step
choosing the two symbols
and/or subtrees with the
lowest probabilities,
combining the choices
into a new subtree.
At this point in our
example, the symbol A
has the probability 1/3, the
symbol B the probability 1/2
and the C/D subtree
probability 1/6.
So we’ll combine A
with the C/D subtree.
On the final step we only
have two choices left:
B and the A/C/D
subtree, which we
combine in a new subtree,
whose root then becomes
the root of the
tree representing
the optimal
variable-length code.
Happily, this is the code
we’ve been using all along!
As mentioned above, we can
produce a number of different
variable-length codes by
swapping the “0” and “1” labels
on any of the subtree branches.
But all those encodings would
have the same expected length,
which is determined by the
distance of each symbol
from the root of the tree,
not the labels along the path
from root to leaf.
So all these different
encodings are
equivalent in terms
of their efficiency.
Now try your hand at
using Huffman’s Algorithm
to construct optimal
variable-length encodings.