The previous sections
showed us how
to build a circuit
that computes a given
sum-of-products expression.
An interesting
question to ask is
if we can implement the
same functionality using
fewer gates or smaller gates?
In other words is there an
equivalent Boolean expression
that involves fewer operations?
Boolean algebra
has many identities
that can be used to transform an
expression into an equivalent,
and hopefully
smaller, expression.
The reduction
identity in particular
offers a transformation
that simplifies
an expression involving two
variables and four operations
into a single variable
and no operations.
Let’s see how we might use
that identity to simplify
a sum-of-products expression.
Here’s the equation from
the start of this chapter,
involving 4 product terms.
We’ll use a variant of the
reduction identity involving
a Boolean expression alpha
and a single variable A.
Looking at the product
terms, the middle two
offer an opportunity to
apply the reduction identity
if we let alpha be the
expression (C AND B).
So we simplify the
middle two product terms
to just alpha, i.e., (C AND
B), eliminating the variable A
from this part of
the expression.
Considering the now
three product terms,
we see that the first
and last terms can also
be reduced, this
time letting alpha be
the expression (NOT C and A).
Wow, this equivalent
equation is much smaller!
Counting inversions and
pair-wise operations,
the original equation
has 14 operations,
while the simplified
equation has 4 operations.
The simplified circuit
would be much cheaper
to build and have a
smaller tPD in the bargain!
Doing this sort of Boolean
simplification by hand
is tedious and error-prone.
Just the sort of task a computer
program could help with.
Such programs are in common
use, but the computation
needed to discover the smallest
possible form for an expression
grows faster than
exponentially as the number
of inputs increases.
So for larger
equations, the programs
use various heuristics to choose
which simplifications to apply.
The results are quite good,
but not necessarily optimal.
But it sure beats doing
the simplification by hand!
Another way to think about
simplification is by searching
the truth table for
“don’t-care” situations.
For example, look at
the first and third rows
of the original truth
table on the left.
In both cases A is 0, C is
0, and the output Y is 0.
The only difference is the value
of B, which we can then tell
is irrelevant when
both A and C are 0.
This gives us the first row of
the truth table on the right,
where we use X to indicate that
the value of B doesn’t matter
when A and C are both 0.
By comparing rows with
the same value for Y,
we can find other
don’t-care situations.
The truth table with don’t-cares
has only three rows where
the output is 1.
And, in fact, the last row is
redundant in the sense that
the input combinations it
matches (011 and 111) are
covered by the second
and fourth rows.
The product terms derived
from rows two and four
are exactly the product terms we
found by applying the reduction
identity.
Do we always want to use the
simplest possible equation
as the template
for our circuits?
Seems like that would
minimize the circuit cost
and maximize performance,
a good thing.
The simplified
circuit is shown here.
Let’s look at how it
performs when A is 1, B is 1,
and C makes a
transition from 1 to 0.
Before the transition, C
is 1 and we can see from
the annotated node values that
it’s the bottom AND gate that’s
causing the Y output to be 1.
When C transitions to 0, the
bottom AND gate turns off
and the top AND gate turns on,
and, eventually the Y output
becomes 1 again.
But the turning on of the
top AND is delayed by the tPD
of the inverter, so there’s
a brief period of time where
neither AND gate is on, and the
output momentarily becomes 0.
This short blip in Y’s value
is called a glitch and it may
result in short-lived changes
on many node values as it
propagates through other
parts of the circuit.
All those changes
consume power, so it
would be good to avoid these
sorts of glitches if we can.
If we include the third product
term BA in our implementation,
the circuit still computes
the same long-term answer
as before.
But now when A and
B are both high,
the output Y will
be 1 independently
of the value of the C input.
So the 1-to-0 transition on the
C input doesn’t cause a glitch
on the Y output.
If you recall the last section
of the previous chapter,
the phrase we used to describe
such circuits is “lenient”.