Now we get to the fun part!
To build other logic gates, we'll design complementary
pullup and pulldown circuits, hooked up as
shown in the diagram on the right, to control
the voltage of the output node.
"Complementary" refers to property that when
one of the circuits is conducting, the other
is not.
When the pullup circuit is conducting and
the pulldown circuit is not, the output node
has a connection to V_DD and its output voltage
will quickly rise to become a valid digital
1 output.
Similarly, when the pulldown circuit is conducting
and the pullup is not, the output node has
a connection to GROUND and its output voltage
will quickly fall to become a valid digital
0 output.
If the circuits are incorrectly designed so
that they are not complementary and could
both be conducting for an extended period
of time, there's a path between V_DD and GROUND
and large amounts of short circuit current
will flow, a very bad idea.
Since our simple switch model won't let us
determine the output voltage in this case,
we'll call this output value "X" or unknown.
Another possibility with a non-complementary
pullup and pulldown is that neither is conducting
and the output node has no connection to either
power supply voltage.
At this point, the output node is electrically
floating and whatever charge is stored by
the nodal capacitance will stay there, at
least for a while.
This is a form of memory and we'll come back
to this in a couple of lectures.
For now, we'll concentrate on the behavior
of devices with complementary pullups and
pulldowns.
Since the pullup and pulldown circuits are
complementary, we'll see there's a nice symmetry
in their design.
We've already seen the simplest complementary
circuit: a single NFET pulldown and a single
PFET pullup.
If the same signal controls both switches,
it's easy to see that when one switch is on,
the other switch is off.
Now consider a pulldown circuit consisting
of two NFET switches in series.
There's a connection through both switches
when A is 1 and B is 1.
For any other combination of A and B values,
one or the other of the switches (or both!)
will be off.
The complementary circuit to NFET switches
in series is PFET switches in parallel.
There's a connection between the top and bottom
circuit nodes when either of the PFET switches
is on, i.e., when A is 0 or B is 0.
As a thought experiment consider all possible
pairs of values for A and B: 00, 01, 10, and
11.
When one or both of the inputs is 0, the series
NFET circuit is not conducting and parallel
PFET circuit is.
And when both inputs are 1, the series NFET
circuit is conducting but the parallel PFET
circuit is not.
Finally consider the case where we have parallel
NFETs and series PFETs.
Conduct the same thought experiment as above
to convince yourself that when one of the
circuits is conducting the other isn't.
Let's put these observations to work when
building our next CMOS combinational device.
In this device, we're using series NFETs in
the pulldown and parallel PFETs in the pullup,
circuits that we convinced ourselves were
complementary in the previous slide.
We can build a tabular representation, called
a truth table, that describes the value of
Z for all possible combinations of the input
values for A and B.
When A and B are 0, the PFETs are on and the
NFETs are off, so Z is connected to V_DD and
the output of the device is a digital 1.
In fact, if either A or B is 0 [CLICK, CLICK]
that continues to be the case, and the value
of Z is still 1.
Only when both A and B are 1 [CLICK], will
both NFETs be on and the value of Z become
0.
This particular device is called a NAND gate,
short for "NOT-AND", a function that is the
inverse of the AND function.
Returning to a physical view for a moment,
the figure on the left is a bird's eye view,
looking down on the surface of the integrated
circuit, showing how the MOSFETs are laid
out in two dimensions.
The blue material represents metal wires with
large top and bottom metal runs connecting
to V_DD and GROUND.
The red material forms the polysilicon gate
nodes, the green material the n-type source/drain
diffusions for the NFETs and the tan material
the p-type source/drain diffusions for the
PFETs.
Can you see that the NFETs are connected in
series and the PFETs in parallel?
Just to give you a sense of the costs of making
a single NAND gate, the yellow box is a back-of-the-envelope
calculation showing that we can manufacture
approximately 26 billion NAND gates on a single
300mm (that's 12 inches for us non-metric
folks) silicon wafer.
For the older IC manufacturing process shown
here, it costs about $3500 to buy the materials
and perform the manufacturing steps needed
to form the circuitry for all those NAND gates.
So the final cost is a bit more than 100 nano-dollars
per NAND gate.
I think this qualifies as both cheap and small!