Mathematicians like
to model uncertainty
about a particular circumstance
by introducing the concept
of a random variable.
For our application,
we'll always
be dealing with circumstances
where there are a finite number
N of distinct
choices, so we'll be
using a discrete
random variable that
can take on one of
N possible values:
x_1, x_2, and so on up to x_N.
The probability that X
will take on the value x_1
is given by the
probability p_1, the value
x_2 by probability
p_2, and so on.
The smaller the probability,
the more uncertain
it is that X will take
on that particular value.
Claude Shannon, in his
seminal work on the theory
of information, defined the
information received when
learning that X had taken on
the value x_i as the log-base-2
of 1/p_i.
Note that uncertainty
of a choice
is inversely proportional
to its probability,
so the term inside of the log
is basically the uncertainty
of that particular choice.
We use the log-base-2
to measure the magnitude
of the uncertainty in bits --
where a bit is a quantity that
can take on the value 0 or 1
-- think of the information
content as the number of bits
we would require to encode this
choice.
Suppose the data
we receive doesn't
resolve all the uncertainty.
For example, when earlier
we received the data
that the card was a
heart: some of uncertainty
has been resolved since we
know more about the card
than we did before the
receiving the data,
but we don't yet
know the exact card,
so some uncertainty
still remains.
We can still use the formula
for information content
from the previous slide,
using the probability
we received to compute
the information content.
In our example the
probability of learning
that a card chosen randomly
from a 52-card deck is a heart
is 13/52, the number of
hearts over the total number
of choices.
So p_data is 13/52, or 1/4
and the information content is
computed as
log-base-2 of 1/(1/4),
which figures out to be 2 bits.
This example is one
we encounter often --
we receive partial information
about N equally-probable
choices (each choice has
probability 1/N) that narrows
the number of choices down to M.
The probability of receiving
such information is M*(1/N),
so information received
is log-base-2 of N/M bits.
Let's look at some examples.
If we learn the result
(HEADS or TAILS)
of a flip of a fair coin,
we go from 2 choices
to a single choice.
So the information received
is log-base-2 of 2/1,
or a single bit.
This makes sense:
it would take us
one bit to encode which
of the two possibilities
actually happened, say, "1"
for heads and "0" for tails.
Reviewing the example
from the previous slide:
learning that a card drawn
from a fresh deck is a heart
gives us log-base-2 of 52/13,
or 2 bits of information.
Again this makes
sense: it would take us
two bits to encode which
of four possible card suits
had turned up.
Finally consider
what information
we get from rolling two
dice, one red and one green.
Each die has six faces, so there
are 36 possible combinations.
Once we learn the exact
outcome of the roll,
we've received log-base-2
of 36/1 or 5.17 bits
of information.
Hmm.
What do those
fractional bits mean?
Our circuitry will only
deal with whole bits!
So to encode a single outcome,
we'd need to use six bits.
But suppose we wanted to
record the outcome of 10
successive rolls.
At 6 bits per roll, we would
need a total of 60 bits.
What this formula
is telling us is
that we would need
not 60 bits, but only
52 bits to unambiguously
encode the results.
Whether we can come
with an encoding that
achieves this lower bound
is an interesting question,
which we will take up
later in the chapter.
To wrap up, let's return
to our initial example.
Here's table showing the
different choices for the data
received, along
with the probability
of that event and the
computed information content.
We've already talked
about learning
that the card was a heart.
The probability of this event
is 13/52 with an information
content of 2 bits.
Learning that a card is
not the Ace of spades
is quite likely, since
there's only one chance in 52
that it is the Ace of spades.
So we only get a small amount of
information from this event --
.028 bits.
There twelve face
cards in a card deck,
so the probability of
this event is 12/52
and we would receive 2.115 bits.
A bit more information than
learning about the card's suit
since there's slightly
less residual uncertainty.
Finally, we get the most
information when all
uncertainty is eliminated
-- a bit more than 5.7 bits.
The results line up nicely with
our and Mr. Blue's intuition:
the more uncertainty is
resolved, the more information
we have received.
Now try your hand at computing
the information for a few
more examples in the
following exercises.