Well, we’ll need at least one
MOSFET to serve as the access
FET so we can select which
bits will be affected by read
and write operations.
We can use a simple
capacitor for storage,
where the value
of a stored bit is
represented by voltage across
the plates of the capacitor.
The resulting circuit is termed
a dynamic random-access memory
(DRAM) cell.
If the capacitor voltage
exceeds a certain threshold,
we’re storing a “1” bit,
otherwise we’re storing a “0”.
The amount of charge
on the capacitor,
which determines the
speed and reliability
of reading the stored
value, is proportional
to the capacitance.
We can increase the
capacitance by increasing
the dielectric constant
of the insulating layer
between the two plates of
the capacitor, increasing
the area of the plates, or by
decreasing the the distance
between the plates.
All of these are
constantly being improved.
A cross section of a modern
DRAM cell is shown here.
The capacitor is formed
in a large trench
dug into the substrate material
of the integrated circuit.
Increasing the depth of the
trench will increase the area
of the capacitor plates without
increasing the cell’s area.
The wordline forms the gate
of the N-FET access transistor
connecting the outer plate of
the capacitor to the bitline.
A very thin insulating layer
separates the outer plate
from the inner plate,
which is connected
to some reference voltage
(shown as GND in this diagram).
You can Google “trench
capacitor” to get the latest
information on the
dimensions and materials used
in the construction
of the capacitor.
The resulting circuit is quite
compact: about 20-times less
area/bit than an SRAM bit cell.
There are some
challenges however.
There’s no circuitry to main the
static charge on the capacitor,
so stored charge will
leak from the outer plate
of the capacitor, hence
the name “dynamic memory”.
The leakage is caused by small
picoamp currents through the PN
junction with the
surrounding substrate,
or subthreshold conduction of
the access FET even when it’s
turned “off”.
This limits the amount of time
we can leave the capacitor
unattended and still expect
to read the stored value.
This means we’ll have to arrange
to read then re-write each bit
cell (called a “refresh”
cycle) every 10ms or so, adding
to the complexity of the
DRAM interface circuitry.
DRAM write operations
are straightforward:
simply turn on the access FET
with the wordline and charge
or discharge the storage
capacitor through the bitline.
Reads are bit more complicated.
First the bitline is precharged
to some intermediate voltage,
e.g., VDD/2, and then
the precharge circuitry
is disconnected.
The wordline is activated,
connecting the storage
capacitor of the selected
cell to the bitline causing
the charge on the
capacitor to be
shared with the charge stored by
the capacitance of the bitline.
If the value stored by the
cell capacitor is a “1”,
the bitline voltage will
increase very slightly (e.g.,
a few tens of millivolts).
If the stored value is a
“0”, the bitline voltage will
decrease slightly.
Sense amplifiers are used
to detect this small voltage
change to produce a
digital output value.
This means that read operations
wipe out the information stored
in the bit cell, which
must then be rewritten
with the detected value at
the end of the read operation.
DRAM circuitry is usually
organized to have “wide” rows,
i.e., multiple consecutive
locations are read in a single
access.
This particular
block of locations
is selected by the
DRAM row address.
Then the DRAM column
address is used
to select a particular location
from the block to be returned.
If we want to read multiple
locations in a single row,
then we only need to
send a new column address
and the DRAM will respond
with that location
without having to access
the bit cells again.
The first access to a
row has a long latency,
but subsequent accesses to the
same row have very low latency.
As we’ll see, we’ll be able
to use fast column accesses
to our advantage.
In summary, DRAM bit cells
consist of a single access FET
connected to a storage capacitor
that’s cleverly constructed
to take up as little
area as possible.
DRAMs must rewrite the contents
of bit cells after they are
read and every cell must be
read and written periodically
to ensure that the stored
charge is refreshed before it’s
corrupted by leakage currents.
DRAMs have much
higher capacities
than SRAMs because of the small
size of the DRAM bit cells,
but the complexity of the
DRAM interface circuitry
means that the initial
access to a row of locations
is quite a bit slower
than an SRAM access.
However subsequent
accesses to the same row
happen at speeds close
to that of SRAM accesses.
Both SRAMs and DRAMs
will store values as long
as their circuitry has power.
But if the circuitry
is powered down,
the stored bits will be lost.
For long-term
storage we will need
to use non-volatile memory
technologies, the topic
of the next lecture segment.