Now let’s turn our attention
to control hazards,
illustrated by the code
fragment shown here.
Which instruction should
be executed after the BNE?
If the value in R3 is non-zero,
ADDC should be executed.
If the value in R3 is zero, the
next instruction should be SUB.
If the current instruction is
an explicit transfer of control
(i.e., JMPs or branches), the
choice of the next instruction
depends on the execution
of the current instruction.
What are the implications
of this dependency
on our execution pipeline?
How does the unpipelined
implementation
determine the next instruction?
For branches (BEQ
or BNE), the value
to be loaded into the
program counter depends on
(1) the opcode, i.e.,
whether the instruction
is a BEQ or a BNE,
(2) the current value of the
program counter since that’s
used in the offset
calculation, and
(3) the value stored in the
register specified by the RA
field of the instruction
since that’s the value tested
by the branch.
For JMP instructions, the next
value of the program counter
depends once again on the opcode
field and the value of the RA
register.
For all other instructions,
the next PC value depends only
the opcode of the instruction
and the value PC+4.
Exceptions also change
the program counter.
We’ll deal with them
later in the lecture.
The control hazard is
triggered by JMP and branches
since their execution depends
on the value in the RA register,
i.e., they need to read from
the register file, which happens
in the RF pipeline stage.
Our bypass mechanisms ensure
that we’ll use the correct
value for the RA register
even if it’s not yet written
into the register file.
What we’re concerned about
here is that the address
of the instruction following
the JMP or branch will be loaded
into program counter at the
end of the cycle when the JMP
or branch is in the RF stage.
But what should the IF stage
be doing while all this is
going on in RF stage?
The answer is that in the case
of JMPs and taken branches,
we don’t know what the IF stage
should be doing until those
instructions are able to access
the value of the RA register
in the RF stage.
One solution is to stall the
IF stage until the RF stage can
compute the necessary result.
This was the first of
our general strategies
for dealing with hazards.
How would this work?
If the opcode in the RF
stage is JMP, BEQ, or BNE,
stall the IF stage
for one cycle.
In the example code shown here,
assume that the value in R3
is non-zero when the
BNE is executed, i.e.,
that the instruction
following BNE
should be the ADDC at
the top of the loop.
The pipeline diagram shows the
effect we’re trying to achieve:
a NOP is inserted into the
pipeline in cycles 4 and 8.
Then execution resumes
in the next cycle
after the RF stage determines
what instruction comes next.
Note, by the way, that we’re
relying on our bypass logic
to deliver the correct value
for R3 from the MEM stage since
the ADDC instruction that
wrote into R3 is still
in the pipeline, i.e., we have
a data hazard to deal with too!
Looking at, say, the WB stage
in the pipeline diagram,
we see it takes 4 cycles
to execute one iteration
of our 3-instruction loop.
So the effective CPI is
4/3, an increase of 33%.
Using stall to deal
with control hazards
has had an impact on the
instruction throughput
of our execution pipeline.
We’ve already seen the logic
needed to introduce NOPs
into the pipeline.
In this case, we add a mux
to the instruction path
in the IF stage, controlled
by the IRSrc_IF signal.
We use the superscript
on the control
signals to indicate which
pipeline stage holds
the logic they control.
If the opcode in the RF
stage is JMP, BEQ, or BNE
we set IRSrc_IF
to 1, which causes
a NOP to replace the
instruction that was
being read from main memory.
And, of course, we’ll be setting
the PCSEL control signals
to select the correct
next PC value,
so the IF stage will fetch the
desired follow-on instruction
in the next cycle.
If we replace an
instruction with NOP,
we say we “annulled”
the instruction.
The branch instructions
in the Beta ISA
make their branch
decision in the RF stage
since they only need the
value in register RA.
But suppose the ISA had a branch
where the branch decision was
made in ALU stage.
When the branch decision
is made in the ALU stage,
we need to introduce two
NOPs into the pipeline,
replacing the now unwanted
instructions in the RF and IF
stages.
This would increase the
effective CPI even further.
But the tradeoff is that
the more complex branches
may reduce the number of
instructions in the program.
If we annul instructions in all
the earlier pipeline stages,
this is called
“flushing the pipeline”.
Since flushing the pipeline has
a big impact on the effective
CPI, we do it when it’s the
only way to ensure the correct
behavior of the
execution pipeline.
We can be smarter
about when we choose
to flush the pipeline
when executing branches.
If the branch is not
taken, it turns out
that the pipeline has
been doing the right thing
by fetching the instruction
following the branch.
Starting execution of an
instruction even when we’re
unsure whether we really
want it executed is called
“speculation”.
Speculative execution is
okay if we’re able to annul
the instruction before it has an
effect on the CPU state, e.g.,
by writing into the register
file or main memory.
Since these state changes
(called “side effects”) happen
in the later pipeline stages,
an instruction can progress
through the IF, RF, and ALU
stages before we have to make
a final decision about
whether it should be annulled.
How does speculation help
with control hazards?
Guessing that the next value of
the program counter is PC+4 is
correct for all but
JMPs and taken branches.
Here’s our example again, but
this time let’s assume that
the BNE is not taken, i.e.,
that the value in R3 is zero.
The SUB instruction
enters the pipeline
at the start of cycle 4.
At the end of cycle 4,
we know whether or not
to annul the SUB.
If the branch is
not taken, we want
to execute the SUB
instruction, so we just
let it continue
down the pipeline.
In other words, instead
of always annulling
the instruction
following branch,
we only annul it if
the branch was taken.
If the branch is not
taken, the pipeline
has speculated correctly
and no instructions
need to be annulled.
However if the BNE
is taken, the SUB
is annulled at
the end of cycle 4
and a NOP is
executed in cycle 5.
So we only introduce a bubble
in the pipeline when there’s
a taken branch.
Fewer bubbles will decrease
the impact of annulment
on the effective CPI.
We’ll be using the same data
path circuitry as before,
we’ll just be a bit more
clever about when the value
of the IRSrc_IF control
signal is set to 1.
Instead of setting it
to 1 for all branches,
we only set it to 1 when
the branch is taken.
Our naive strategy of always
speculating that the next
instruction comes from PC+4
is wrong for JMPs and taken
branches.
Looking at simulated
execution traces,
we’ll see that this error in
speculation leads to about 10%
higher effective CPI.
Can we do better?
This is an important question
for CPUs with deep pipelines.
For example, Intel’s Nehalem
processor from 2009 resolves
the more complex x86 branch
instructions quite late
in the pipeline.
Since Nehalem is capable of
executing multiple instructions
each cycle, flushing
the pipeline in Nehalem
actually annuls the execution
of many instructions,
resulting in a considerable
hit on the CPI.
Like many modern
processor implementations,
Nehalem has a much more
sophisticated speculation
mechanism.
Rather than always guessing the
next instruction is at PC+4,
it only does that for
non-branch instructions.
For branches, it
predicts the behavior
of each individual branch
based on what the branch did
last time it was executed
and some knowledge of how
the branch is being used.
For example, backward
branches at the end of loops,
which are taken for all but the
final iteration of the loop,
can be identified by their
negative branch offset values.
Nehalem can even determine if
there’s correlation between
branch instructions, using
the results of an another,
earlier branch to speculate
on the branch decision
of the current branch.
With these sophisticated
strategies,
Nehalem’s speculation is
correct 95% to 99% of the time,
greatly reducing the impact of
branches on the effective CPI.
There’s also the lazy option of
changing the ISA to deal with
control hazards.
For example, we
could change the ISA
to specify that the instruction
following a jump or branch
is always executed.
In other words the transfer
of control happens *after*
the next instruction.
This change ensures that the
guess of PC+4 as the address
of the next instruction
is always correct!
In the example shown here,
assuming we changed the ISA,
we can reorganize the execution
order of the loop to place
the MUL instruction after
the BNE instruction,
in the so-called
“branch delay slot”.
Since the instruction
in the branch delay slot
is always executed,
the MUL instruction
will be executed during
each iteration of the loop.
The resulting execution is
shown in this pipeline diagram.
Assuming we can find an
appropriate instruction
to place in the delay
slot, the branch
will have zero impact
on the effective CPI.
Are branch delay
slots a good idea?
Seems like they reduce
the negative impact
that branches might have
on instruction throughput.
The downside is that
only half the time can
we find instructions to move
to the branch delay slot.
The other half of
the time we have
to fill it with an
explicit NOP instruction,
increasing the size of the code.
And if we make the branch
decision later in the pipeline,
there are more branch
delay slots, which
would be even harder to fill.
In practice, it turns out
that branch prediction
works better than
delay slots in reducing
the impact of branches.
So, once again we see that it’s
problematic to alter the ISA
to improve the throughput
of pipelined execution.
ISAs outlive implementations,
so it’s best not to change
the execution semantics to deal
with performance issues created
by a particular implementation.