Using more complicated series/parallel networks
of switches, we can build devices that implement
more complex logic functions.
To design a more complex logic gate, first
figure the series and parallel connections
of PFET switches that will connect the gate's
output to V_DD for the right combination of
inputs.
In this example, the output F will be 1 when
A is 0 OR when both B is 0 AND C is 0.
The "OR" translates into a parallel connection,
and the "AND" translates into a series connection,
giving the pullup circuit you see to the right.
To build the complementary pulldown circuit,
systematically walk the hierarchy of pullup
connections, replacing PFETs with NFETs, series
subcircuits with parallel subcircuits, and
parallel subcircuits with series subcircuits.
In the example shown, the pullup circuit had
a switch controlled by A in parallel with
a series subcircuit consisting of switches
controlled by B and C.
The complementary pulldown circuit uses NFETs,
with the switch controlled by A in series
with a parallel subcircuit consisting of switches
controlled by B and C.
Finally combine the pullup and pulldown circuits
to form a fully-complementary CMOS implementation.
This probably went by a quickly, but with
practice you'll get comfortable with the CMOS
design process.
Mr. Blue is asking a good question: will this
recipe work for any and all logic functions?
The answer is "no", let's see why.
Using CMOS, a single gate (a circuit with
one pullup network and one pulldown network)
can only implement the so-called inverting
functions where rising inputs lead to falling
outputs and vice versa.
To see why, consider what happens with one
of the gate's inputs goes from 0 to 1.
Any NFET switches controlled by the rising
input will go from off to on.
This may enable one or more paths between
the gate's output and GROUND.
And PFET switches controlled by the rising
input will from on to off.
This may disable one or more paths between
the gate's output and V_DD.
So if the gate's output changes as the result
of the rising input, it must be because some
pulldown path was enabled and some pullup
path was disabled.
In other words, any change in the output voltage
due to a rising input must be a falling transition
from 1 to 0.
Similar reasoning tells us that falling inputs
must lead to rising outputs.
In fact, for any non-constant CMOS gate, we
know that its output must be 1 when all inputs
are 0 (since all the NFETs are off and all
the PFETs are on).
And vice-versa: if all the inputs are 1, the
gate's output must be 0.
This means that so-called positive logic can't
be implemented with a single CMOS gate.
Look at this truth table for the AND function.
It's value when both inputs are 0 or both
inputs are 1 is inconsistent with our deductions
about the output of a CMOS gate for these
combinations of inputs.
Furthermore, we can see that when A is 1 and
B rises from 0 to 1, the output rises instead
of falls.
Moral of the story: when you're a CMOS designer,
you'll get very good at implementing functionality
with inverting logic!