Finally, let's discuss the third
class of instructions that let
us change the program counter.
Up until now, the
program counter
has simply been incremented by 4
at the end of each instruction,
so that the next instruction
comes from the memory
location that immediately
follows the location that
held the current instruction,
i.e., the Beta has been
executing instructions
sequentially from memory.
But in many programs,
such as in factorial,
we need to disrupt
sequential execution,
either to loop back to repeat
some earlier instruction,
or to skip over instructions
because of some data
dependency.
We need a way to change
the program counter
based on data values generated
by the program's execution.
In the factorial example, as
long as b is not equal to 0,
we need to keep executing the
instructions that calculate a*b
and decrement b.
So we need instructions
to test the value of b
after it's been decremented
and if it's non-zero,
change the PC to repeat
the loop one more time.
Changing the PC depending
on some condition
is implemented by a
branch instruction,
and the operation is referred
to as a "conditional branch".
When the branch is
taken, the PC is changed
and execution is restarted
at the new location, which
is called the branch target.
If the branch is not taken,
the PC is incremented by 4
and execution continues with
the instruction following
the branch.
As the name implies,
a branch instruction
represents a potential fork
in the execution sequence.
We'll use branches to
implement many different types
of control structures: loops,
conditionals, procedure
calls, etc.
Branches instructions also
use the instruction format
with the 16-bit signed constant.
The operation of the
branch instructions
are a bit complicated, so let's
walk through their operation
step-by-step.
Let's start by looking at
the operation of the BEQ
instruction.
First the usual PC
4 calculation is
performed, giving us the address
of the instruction following
the BEQ.
This value is written
to the "rc" register
whether or not the
branch is taken.
This feature of
branches is pretty handy
and we'll use it to
implement procedure calls
a couple of lectures from now.
Note that if we don't need
to remember the PC 4 value,
we can specify R31
as the "rc" register.
Next, BEQ tests the
value of the "ra"
register to see if
it's equal to 0.
If it is equal to 0,
the branch is taken
and the PC is incremented
by the amount specified
in the constant field
of the instruction.
Actually the constant,
called an offset
since we're using
it to offset the PC,
is treated as a word offset
and is multiplied by 4
to convert it a byte
offset since the PC uses
byte addressing.
If the contents of the "ra"
register is not equal to 0,
the PC is incremented
by 4 and execution
continues with the
instruction following the BEQ.
Let me say a few more
words about the offset.
The branches are using what's
referred to as "pc-relative
addressing".
That means the address
of the branch target
is specified relative to
the address of the branch,
or, actually, relative to the
address of the instruction
following the branch.
So an offset of 0 would refer
to the instruction following
the branch and an
offset of -1 would
refer to the branch itself.
Negative offsets are
called "backwards branches"
and are usually seen at branches
used at the end of loops, where
the looping condition
is tested and we
branch backwards to the
beginning of the loop
if another iteration
is called for.
Positive offsets are
called "forward branches"
and are usually seen in
code for "if statements",
where we might skip over
some part of the program
if a condition is not true.
We can use BEQ to implement a
so-called unconditional branch,
i.e., a branch that
is always taken.
If we test R31 to see if
it's 0, that's always true,
so BEQ(R31,...) would always
branch to the specified target.
There's also a BNE
instruction, identical to BEQ
in its operation except
the sense of the condition
is reversed: the branch is taken
if the value of register "ra"
is non-zero.
It might seem that only testing
for zero/non-zero doesn't let
us do everything we
might want to do.
For example, how would
we branch if "a b"?
That's where the compare
instructions come in -
they do more
complicated comparisons,
producing a non-zero value
if the comparison is true
and a zero value if the
comparison is false.
Then we can use
BEQ and BNE to test
the result of the comparison
and branch appropriately.
At long last we're
finally in a position
to write Beta code
to compute factorial
using the iterative algorithm
shown in C code on the left.
In the Beta code,
the loop starts
at the second instruction and
is marked with the "L:" label.
The body of the loop consists
of the required multiplication
and the decrement of b.
Then, in the fourth
instruction, b is tested
and, if it's non-zero,
the BNE will branch back
to the instruction
with the label L.
Note that in symbolic notation
for BEQ and BNE instructions
we don't write the offset
directly since directly that
would be a pain to
calculate and would
change if we added or removed
instructions from the loop.
Instead we reference
the instruction
to which we want to
branch, and the program
that translates
the symbolic code
into the binary
instruction fields
will do the offset
calculation for us.
There's a satisfying similarity
between the Beta code
and the operations specified
by the high-level FSM
we created for
computing factorial in the
simple programmable datapath
discussed earlier
in this lecture.
In this example, each
state in the high-level
FSM matches up nicely
with a particular
Beta instruction.
We wouldn't expect that high
degree of correspondence
in general, but since our
Beta datapath and the example
datapath were very similar,
the states and instructions
match up pretty well.