We are going to compare the behavior of 3
different cache configurations on a benchmark
program to better understand the impact of
the cache configuration on the performance
of the benchmark.
The first cache we will consider is a 64-line
direct mapped cache.
The second is a 2-way set associative cache
that uses the LRU, or least recently used,
replacement strategy, and has a total of 64
lines.
The third is a 4-way set associative cache
that uses the LRU replacement strategy, and
also has a total of 64 lines.
Note that all three caches have the same capacity
in that they can store a total of 64 words
of data.
In a direct mapped cache any particular memory
address maps to exactly one line in the cache.
Let's assume that our data is 32 bits, or
4 bytes wide.
This means that consecutive addresses are
4 bytes apart, so we treat the bottom two
address bits as always being 00 so that our
address is on a data word boundary.
Next, we want to determine which cache line
this particular address maps to.
Since there are 64 lines in this cache, we
need 6 bits to select one of the 64 lines.
These 6 bits are called the index.
In this example, the index is 000011, so this
particular address maps to line 3 of the cache.
The data that gets stored in the cache is
the tag portion of the address of the line
plus the 32 bits of data.
The tag is used for comparison when checking
if a particular address is in the cache or
not.
It uniquely identifies the particular memory
address.
In addition, each cache line has a valid bit
that lets you know whether the data in the
cache is currently valid or not.
This is important upon startup because without
this bit there is no way to know whether the
data in the cache is garbage or real data.
In a 2-way set associative cache, the cache
is divided into 2 sets each with half the
number of lines.
So we have two sets with 32 lines each.
Since there are only 32 lines, we now only
need a 5 bit index to select the line.
However, any given index can map to two distinct
locations, one in each set.
This also means that when the tag comparisons
are done, two comparisons are required, one
per set.
In a 4-way set associative cache, the cache
is divided into 4 sets each with 16 lines.
The width of the index is now 4 bits to select
the cache line.
Here, selecting a line identifies one of 4
words as possible locations for reading or
writing the associated data.
This also implies that 4 tags need to be compared
when trying to read from the cache to determine
if the desired address is stored in the cache
or not.
The test program begins by defining a few
constants, J, A, B, and N.
J specifies the address where the program
lives.
A is the starting address of data region 1,
and B is the starting address of data region
2.
Finally, N specifies the size of the data
regions.
Since one word consists of 4 bytes, 16 bytes
of data mean that there are 4 data elements
per region.
Next the assembler is told that the beginning
of the program is at address 0x1000.
The green rectangle identifies the outer loop,
and the yellow rectangle identifies the inner
loop of the code.
Before entering the outer loop, a loop counter,
which is stored in register R6 is initialized
to 1,000.
Then each time through the outer loop, R6
is decremented by 1 and the loop is repeated
as long as R6 is not equal to 0.
The outer loop also resets R0 to N each time
through the loop.
R0 is used to hold the desired array offset.
Since the last element of the array is stored
at location N – 4, the first step of the
inner loop, is to decrement R0 by 4.
R1 is then loaded with the value at address
A + N – 4 which is the address of A[3] because
array indeces begin at 0.
R2 is loaded with B[3].
As long as R0 is not equal to 0, the loop
repeats itself, each time accessing the previous
element of each array until the first element
(index 0) is loaded.
Then the outer loop decrements R6 and repeats
the entire thing 1000 times.
Now that we understand the configuration of
our three caches and the behavior of our test
benchmark, we can begin comparing the behavior
of this benchmark on the three caches.
The first thing we want to ask ourselves is
which of the three cache configurations gets
the highest hit ratio.
Here we are not asked to calculate an actual
hit ratio, instead we just need to realize
that there are 3 distinct regions of data
in this benchmark.
The first holds the instructions, the second
holds array A, and the third holds array B.
If we think about the addresses of each of
these regions in memory, we see that the first
instruction is at address 0x1000.
This will result in an index of 0 regardless
of which cache you consider, so for all three
caches the first instruction would map to
the first line of the cache.
Similarly the first element of arrays A and
B are at address 0x2000 and 0x3000.
These addresses will also result in an index
of 0 regardless of which of the three caches
you consider.
So we see that the 1st CMOVE, A[0], and B[0]
would all map to line 0 of the cache.
Similarly, the 2nd CMOVE whose address is
0x1004 would map to line 1 of the cache as
would array elements A[1] and B[1].
This tells us that if we use the direct mapped
cache, or a 2-way set associative cache, then
we will have cache collisions between the
instructions, and the array elements.
Collisions in the cache imply cache misses
as we replace one piece of data with another
in the cache.
However, if we use a 4-way set associative
cache then each region of memory can go in
a distinct set in the cache thus avoiding
collisions and resulting in 100% hit rate
after the first time through the loop.
Note that the first time through the loop
each instruction and data access will result
in a cache miss because the data needs to
initially be brought into the cache.
But when the loop is repeated, the data is
already there and results in cache hits.
Now suppose that we make a minor modification
to our test program by changing B from 0x3000
to 0x2000.
This means that array A and array B now refer
to same locations in memory.
We want to determine, which of the cache's
hit rate will show a noticeable improvement
as a result of this change.
The difference between our original benchmark
and this modified one is that we now have
two distinct regions of memory to access,
one for the instructions, and one for the
data.
This means that the 2-way set associative
cache will no longer experience collisions
in its cache, so its hit rate will be significantly
better than with the original benchmark.
Now suppose that we change our benchmark once
again, this time making J, A and B all equal
to 0, and changing N to be 64.
This means that we now have 16 elements in
our arrays instead of 4.
It also means that the array values that we
are loading for arrays A and B are actually
the same as the instructions of the program.
Another way of thinking about this is that
we now only have one distinct region of memory
being accessed.
What we want to determine now, is the total
number of cache misses that will occur for
each of the cache configurations.
Let's begin by considering the direct mapped
cache.
In the direct mapped cache, we would want
to first access the first CMOVE instruction.
Since this instruction is not yet in the cache,
our first access is a cache miss.
We now bring the binary equivalent of this
instruction into line 0 of our cache.
Next, we want to access the second CMOVE instruction.
Once again the instruction is not in our cache
so we get another cache miss.
This results in our loading the 2nd CMOVE
instruction to line 1 of our cache.
We continue in the same manner with the SUBC
instruction and the first LD instruction.
Again we get cache misses for each of those
instructions and that in turn causes us to
load those instructions into our cache.
Now, we are ready to execute our first load
operation.
This operation wants to load A[15] into R1.
Because the beginning of array A is at address
0, then A[15] maps to line 15 of our cache.
Since we have not yet loaded anything into
line 15 of our cache, this means that our
first data access is a miss.
We continue with the second load instruction.
This instruction is not yet in the cache,
so we get a cache miss and then load it into
line 4 of our cache.
We then try to access B[15].
B[15] corresponds to the same piece of data
as A[15], so this data access is already in
the cache thus resulting in a data hit for
B[15].
So far we have gotten 5 instruction misses,
1 data miss and 1 data hit.
Next we need to access the BNE instruction.
Once again we get a cache miss which results
in loading the BNE instruction into line 5
of our cache.
The inner loop is now repeated with R0 = 60
which corresponds to element 14 of the arrays.
This time through the loop, all the instructions
are already in the cache and result in instruction
hits.
A[14] which maps to line 14 of our cache results
in a data miss because it is not yet present
in our cache.
So we bring A[14] into the cache.
Then as before, when we try to access B[14],
we get a data hit because it corresponds to
the same piece of data as A[14].
So in total, we have now seen 6 instruction
misses and 2 data misses.
The rest of the accesses have all been hits.
This process repeats itself with a data miss
for array element A[i], and a data hit for
array element B[i] until we get to A[5] which
actually results in a hit because it corresponds
to the location in memory that holds the BNE(R0,
R) instruction which is already in the cache
at line 5.
From then on the remaining data accesses all
result in hits.
At this point we have completed the inner
loop and proceed to the remaining instructions
in the outer loop.
These instructions are the second SUBC and
the second BNE instructions.
These correspond to the data that is in lines
6 and 7 of the cache thus resulting in hits.
The loop then repeats itself 1000 times but
each time through all the instructions and
all the data is in the cache so they all result
in hits.
So the total number of misses that we get
when executing this benchmark on a direct
mapped cache is 16.
These are known as compulsory misses which
are misses that occur when you are first loading
the data into your cache.
Recall that the direct mapped cache has one
set of 64 lines in the cache.
The 2-way set associative has 2 sets of 32
lines each, and the 4-way set associative
has 4 sets of 16 lines each.
Since only 16 lines are required to fit all
the instructions and data associated with
this benchmark, this means that effectively,
only one set will be used in the set associative
caches, and because even in the 4-way set
associative cache there are 16 lines, that
means that once the data is loaded into the
cache it does not need to be replaced with
other data so after the first miss per line,
the remaining accesses in the entire benchmark
will be hits.
So the total number of misses in the 2-way
and 4-way set associative caches is also 16.