Let’s try using the latch
as the memory component
in our sequential logic system.
To load the encoding of the
new state into the latch,
we open the latch by setting
the latch’s gate input HIGH,
letting the new value propagate
to the latch’s Q output,
which represents
the current state.
This updated value
propagates through
the combinational logic,
updating the new state
information.
Oops, if the gate
stays HIGH too long,
we’ve created a loop in our
system and our plan to load
the latch with new state goes
awry as the new state value
starts to change rapidly as
information propagates around
and around the loop.
So to make this work, we need
to carefully time the interval
when G is HIGH.
It has to be long enough
to satisfy the constraints
of the dynamic discipline,
but it has to be short enough
that the latch closes again
before the new state information
has a chance to propagate
all the way around the loop.
Hmm.
I think Mr. Blue is right: this
sort of tricky system timing
would likely be error-prone
since the exact timing
of signals is almost
impossible to guarantee.
We have upper and lower
bounds on the timing of signal
transitions but no guarantees
of exact intervals.
To make this work, we
want to a load signal
that marks an instant in
time, not an interval.
Here’s an analogy that will help
us understand what’s happening
and what we can do about it.
Imagine a line cars waiting
at a toll booth gate.
The sequence of cars
represents the sequence
of states in our
sequential logic
and the gated toll both
represents the latch.
Initially the gate is closed and
the cars are waiting patiently
to go through the toll booth.
When the gate
opens, the first car
proceeds out of the toll both.
But you can see that the timing
of when to close the gate
is going to be tricky.
It has to be open long
enough for the first car
to make it through, but not too
long lest the other cars also
make it through.
This is exactly
the issue we faced
with using the latch
as our memory component
in our sequential logic.
So how do we ensure only one car
makes it through the open gate?
One solution is
to use TWO gates!
Here’s the plan: Initially Gate
1 is open allowing exactly one
car to enter the toll
booth and Gate 2 is closed.
Then at a particular
point in time,
we close Gate 1
while opening Gate 2.
This lets the car in the
toll booth proceed on,
but prevents any other
car from passing through.
We can repeat this
two-step process
to deal with each
car one-at-time.
The key is that at
no time is there
a path through both gates.
This is the same arrangement
as the escapement mechanism
in a mechanical clock.
The escapement ensures that the
gear attached to the clock’s
spring only advances
one tooth at a time,
preventing the spring from
spinning the gear wildly
causing a whole day
to pass at once!
If we observed the
toll booth’s output,
we would see a car emerge
shortly after the instant
in time when Gate 2 opens.
The next car would
emerge shortly
after the next time
Gate 2 opens, and so on.
Cars would proceed
through the toll booth
at a rate set by the interval
between Gate 2 openings.
Let’s apply this solution
to design a memory component
for our sequential logic.
Taking our cue from
the 2-gate toll both,
we’ll design a new component,
called a D register,
using two back-to-back latches.
The load signal for a D
register is typically called
the register’s “clock”, but the
register’s D input and Q output
play the same roles as
they did for the latch.
First we’ll describe the
internal structure of the D
register, then we’ll describe
what it does and look in detail
at how it does it.
The D input is connected to
what we call the master latch
and the Q output is
connected to the slave latch.
Note that the clock signal is
inverted before it’s connected
to the gate input
of the master latch.
So when the master latch is
open, the slave is closed,
and vice versa.
This achieves the escapement
behavior we saw on the previous
slide: at no time is there
active path from the register’s
D input to the
register’s Q output.
The delay introduced by the
inverter on the clock signal
might give us cause for concern.
When there’s a rising 0-to-1
transition on the clock signal,
might there be a brief interval
when the gate signal is HIGH
for both latches since there
will be a small delay before
the inverter’s output
transitions from 1 to 0?
Actually the inverter
isn’t necessary:
Mr Blue is looking at a slightly
different latch schematic
where the latch is
open when G is LOW
and closed when G is high.
Just what we need
for the master latch!
By the way, you’ll sometimes
hear a register called
a flip-flop because of the
bistable nature of the positive
feedback loops in the latches.
That’s the internal
structure of the D register.
In the next section we’ll
take a step-by-step tour
of the register in operation.