Given a probability, p, of an event occurring,
we know that the amount of information that
you get from being told that a particular
event occurred is log2(1/p).
Using that information, let's try to answer
the following questions.
Someone picks a name out of a hat known to
contain the names of 5 women and 3 men, and
tells you a man has been selected.
How much information have they given you about
the selection?
The probability of a man being selected in
this problem is 3/8.
So the amount of information that you have
been given
is log2(1/(3/8)) = log2(8/3).
Another way to think about this is that if
you start off with N choices, and the additional
information that you are given reduces your
choices to M, then the amount of information
that you have been given is log2(N/M).
In this example N = 8 because that is the
original number of choices.
The reduced number of choices once you are
told that a man has been selected is 3, so
M = 3.
This means that the amount of information
you received is log2(8/3).
For the second question, you are asked to
guess a random 4-bit 2's complement number.
I then tell you that the number is greater
than 0.
How much information have you been given?
For this problem the original number of choices
is the number of permutations of 4 binary
bits which is 16, so N = 16.
Once you are told that the number is greater
than 0, this reduces your choice to 7, so
M = 7.
That means that the amount of information
that you have been given is log2(16/7).