This discussion of design tradeoffs completes
Part 1 of the course.
We've covered a lot of ground in the last
eight lectures.
We started by looking at the mathematics underlying
information theory and used it to help evaluate
various alternative ways of effectively using
sequences of bits to encode information content.
Then we turned our attention to adding carefully-chosen
redundancies to our encoding to ensure that
we could detect and even correct errors that
corrupted our bit-level encodings.
Next we learned how analog signaling accumulates
errors as we added processing elements to
our system.
We solved the problem by using voltages "digitally"
choosing two ranges of voltages to encode
the bit values 0 and 1.
We had different signaling specifications
for our outputs and inputs, adding noise margins
to make our signaling more robust.
Then we developed the static discipline for
combinational devices and were led to the
conclusion that our devices had to be non-linear
and exhibit gains > 1.
In our study of combinational logic, we fist
learned about the MOSFET, a voltage-controlled
switch.
We developed a technique for using MOSFETS
to build CMOS combinational logic gates, which
met all the criteria of the static discipline.
Then we discussed systematic ways of synthesizing
larger combinational circuits that could implement
any functionality we could express in the
form a truth table.
To be able to perform sequences of operations,
we first developed a reliable bistable storage
element based on a positive feedback loop.
To ensure the storage elements worked correctly
we imposed the dynamic discipline which required
inputs to the storage elements to be stable
just before and after the time the storage
element was transitioned to "memory mode".
We introduced finite-state machines as a useful
abstraction for designing sequential logic.
And then we figured out how to deal with asynchronous
inputs in way that minimized the chance of
incorrect operation due to metastability.
In the last two lectures we developed latency
and throughput as performance measures for
digital systems and discussed ways of achieving
maximum throughput under various constraints.
We discussed how it's possible to make tradeoffs
to achieve goals of minimizing power dissipation
and increasing performance through decreased
latency or increased throughput.
Whew!
That's a lot of information in a short amount
of time.
Mr. Blue and the rest of the 6.004x staff
hope you've found the course useful in increasing
your skills in designing digital systems and
analyzing their operation.
You've completed several actual designs and
you're well on your way to designing a complete
computer using our standard cell library.
That's quite an accomplishment.
If you'd like to continue the journey, please
join us for Part 2 of the course where we'll
discuss programmable architectures and work
out the design of a modern 32-bit processor.
See you then!