The LD and ST instructions access main memory.
Note that its the same main memory that holds
the instructions, even though for drafting
convenience we show it has two separate boxes
in our datapath diagram.
In the form we show it here, main memory has
three ports:
two read ports for fetching instructions and
reading load data, and one write port used
by the ST instruction to write data into main
memory.
The address calculation is exactly the same
computation as performed by the ADDC instruction:
the contents of the RA register are added
to the sign-extended 16-bit literal from the
low-order 16 bits of the instruction.
So we'll simply reuse the existing datapath
hardware to compute the address.
For the LD instruction the output of the ALU
is routed to main memory as the address of
the location we wish to access.
After the memory's propagation delay, the
contents of the addressed location is returned
by the memory and we need to route that back
to the register file to be written into the
RC register.
The memory has two control signals: MOE (memory
output enable), which we set to 1 when we
want to read a value from the memory.
And MWE (memory write enable) which is set
to 1 when we want main memory to store the
value on its write data (WD) port into the
addressed memory location.
We need to add another MUX to select which
value to write back to the register file:
the output of the ALU or the data returning
from main memory.
We've used a 3-to-1 MUX and we'll see the
use for the other MUX input when we get to
the implementation of branches and jumps.
The two-bit WDSEL signal is used to select
the source of the write-back value.
Let's follow the flow of data when executing
the LD instruction.
The ALU operands are chosen just as they are
for the ADDC instruction and the ALU is requested
to perform an ADD operation.
The ALU result is connected to the address
port of main memory, who's control signals
are set for a read operation.
The WDSEL control signals are set to 2 to
route the returning data to the register file.
Execution of the ST instruction is very similar
to the execution of the LD instruction, with
one extra complication.
The value to be written to memory comes from
the RC register, but the RC instruction field
is not connected a register file read address.
Happily, the RB register address isn't being
used by the ST instruction since the second
ALU operand comes from the literal field.
So we'll use a MUX to enable the RC field
to be selected as the address for the register
file's second read port.
When the RA2SEL control signal is 0, the RB
field is selected as the address.
When RA2SEL is 1, the RC field is selected.
The output from the second read data port
is connected to the write data port of main
memory.
The ST instruction is the only instruction
that does not write a result into the register
file.
So the WERF control signal will be 0 when
executing ST.
Here's the flow of data when executing ST.
The operands are selected as for LD and the
ALU performs the address computation with
the result sent to main memory as the address.
Meanwhile the RC field is selected as the
address for the second register file read
port and the value from the RC register becomes
the write data for main memory.
By setting the MWR control signal to 1, the
main memory will write the WD data into the
selected memory location at the end of the
cycle.
The WERF control signal is set to zero since
we won't be writing a value into the register
file.
And, since we're not writing to the register
file, we don't care about the value for the
WDSEL signal.
Of course, the logic will need to supply some
value for WDSEL.
The "don't care" annotation is telling the
logic designer that she's welcome to supply
whatever value is most convenient.
This is particularly useful when using Karnaugh
maps to optimize the control logic, where
the value can be chosen as either 0 or 1,
whichever results in the best minimization
of the logic equations.