We are given a CBit module shown here.
This module takes corresponding bits of two
unsigned binary numbers, A and B, along with
two Cin bits from higher-order
CBit modules.
Its output bit R, is the appropriate bit of
the larger among A and B.
It also has two additional output bits Cout
which indicate respectively if A>B or B>A
in the bits considered so far.
The propagation delay of each Cbit module
is 4ns.
The CBit module is used to create a product
MAXC which is a combinational device that
determines the maximum of its two 4-bit unsigned
binary inputs.
It is constructed using 4 CBit modules as
shown here.
The first question we want to consider is
what are the propagation delay and throughput
of this combinational circuit?
The propagation delay of a combinational circuit
is the propagation delay along its longest
path from input to output.
In this case, the longest path is through
4 CBit modules.
Since each CBit module has a propagation delay
of 4 ns, the propagation delay of this combinational
circuit is 4 * 4 ns = 16 ns.
The throughput of a combinational circuit
is 1 / Latency, so the throughput of this
circuit is 1 / (16 ns).
The next question we want to consider is what
two bits would we expect to see coming out
of the (unused) Cout outputs from
the low-order CBit module if A3:0
and B3:0 are identical numbers.
The Cout[1] bit indicates whether
A>B and the Cout[0] bit indicates
whether B>A.
Since the numbers are identical neither of
these inequalities is true, so both Cout
bits are 0.
Next, we want to pipeline this circuit for
maximum throughput.
We are given ideal pipeline registers for
this step.
Recall that ideal registers have a 0 propagation
delay and 0 setup time.
In order to pipeline this circuit for maximum
throughput, we want to add pipeline registers
that isolate each individual CBit to be in
its own pipeline stage.
Recall, that when pipelining a circuit, we
want to add pipeline registers to all the
outputs, so we begin by adding a contour that
goes across all 4 outputs.
We now want to isolate the low order CBit
module.
To do this we draw an additional contour that
crosses the outputs R3-R1, then passes between
the two low order CBit modules and finally
crosses the A0 and B0 inputs.
Remember that every time a contour crosses
a wire, it means that we are adding a pipeline
register.
So this first step added 6 pipeline registers,
one for each of R3, R2, and R1, another between
the two CBit modules and the last 2 on the
A0 and B0 inputs.
Notice that regardless of which input to output
path we look at the number of pipeline registers
along the path so far is 2.
We continue in this manner isolating each
Cbit module into its own pipeline stage.
Now that each CBit module has been placed
into its own pipeline stage, we can clock
this circuit for maximum througput.
Our clock period must allow for enough time
for the propagation delay of the pipeline
register, plus the propagation delay of the
Cbit module, plus the setup time of the next
pipeline register.
Since our pipeline registers are ideal, the
propagation delay and the setup time of the
pipeline registers is 0, so the clock period
is equal to the propagation delay of 1 CBit
module which is 4 ns.
The latency of this pipelined circuit is equal
to the number of pipeline stages (4 in this
example) times the clock period time, so the
latency is 4 * 4 ns = 16 ns.
The throughput of a pipelined circuit is 1
divided by the clock period, so throughput
is 1 / (4 ns).
Our Cbit module can be used to create the
MAX4X4 product which is a combinational circuit
capable of determining the maximum of four
4-bit binary inputs.
Our first task here is to determine the combinational
latency and throughput of this new circuit.
Looking carefully at this circuit, we see
that the longest path through the circuit
begins at the upper left CBit module and ends
at the bottom right CBit module.
Counting the number of CBit modules along
this path, we see that we need to cross 6
CBit modules.
This means that the latency of this circuit
is L = 6 * propagation delay of a single CBit
module = 6 * 4 ns = 24 ns.
The throughput of a combinational circuit
is equal to 1 / Latency = 1 / (24 ns).
Out final task is to pipeline this new circuit
for maximum througput.
We begin as we did before by adding a contour
that goes across all of our outputs.
Next we want to figure out how to add the
remaining contours so that the clock period
of our pipelined circuit can be minimized.
The clock period must allow enough time for
the propagation delay of the pipeline register,
plus the propagation delay of any combinational
logic, plus the setup time of the next pipeline
register.
Since our pipeline registers are ideal, both
the propagation delay and the setup time of
the pipeline registers is 0, so our clock
period is equal to the propagation delay of
the combinational logic between each pair
of pipeline registers.
In order to minimize this, we would like the
number of CBit modules between each pair of
pipeline registers to be at most 1.
This would make our period, T = 4 ns.
To achieve this, we can draw diagonal contours
through our circuit.
Notice that these contours result in at most
1 CBit module appearing between any pair of
pipeline registers while at the same time
including as many CBit modules that can be
executed in parallel in a single pipeline
stage.
The latter constraint will minimize our latency
in addition to maximizing our throughput.
Notice that regardless of which input to output
path you follow, at this stage you are crossing
3 pipeline registers.
We continue pipelining our circuit in this
manner until we have added enough pipeline
stages so that each stage passes through a
single CBit module.
We now see that any path from input to output
passes through 6 pipeline registers because
we have split our circuit into 6 pipeline
stages in order to break up the longest path.
We can now clock this circuit with period
T = 4 ns.
So the latency is the number of pipeline stages
times the clock period which equals 6 * 4
ns = 24 ns.
The throughput of this circuit is 1 / clock
period (T) = 1 /(4 ns).