Let's take a closer look at how macros work
in UASM.
Here we see the definition of the macro "consec"
which has a single parameter "n".
The body of the macro is a sequence of four
expressions.
When there's an invocation of the "consec"
macro, in this example with the argument 37,
the body of the macro is expanded replacing
all occurrences of "n" with the argument 37.
The resulting text is then processed as if
it had appeared in place of the macro invocation.
In this example, the four expressions are
evaluated to give a sequence of four values
that will be placed in the next four bytes
of the output array.
Macro expansions may contain other macro invocations,
which themselves will be expanded, continuing
until all that's left are expressions to be
evaluated.
Here we see the macro definition for WORD,
which assembles its argument into two consecutive
bytes.
And for the macro LONG, which assembles its
argument into four consecutive bytes, using
the WORD macro to process the low 16 bits
of the value, then the high 16 bits of the
value.
These two UASM statements cause the constant
0xDEADBEEF to converted to 4 bytes, which
are then deposited in the output array starting
at index 0x100.
Note that the Beta expects the least-significant
byte of a multi-byte value to be stored at
the lowest byte address.
So the least-significant byte 0xEF is placed
at address 0x100 and the most-significant
byte 0xDE is placed at address 0x103.
This is the "little-endian" convention for
multi-byte values: the least-significant byte
comes first.
Intel's x86 architecture is also little-endian.
There is a symmetrical "big-endian" convention
where the most-significant byte comes first.
Both conventions are in active use and, in
fact, some ISAs can be configured to use either
convention!
There is no right answer for which convention
to use, but the fact that there two conventions
means that we have to be alert for the need
to convert the representation of multi-byte
values when moving values between one ISA
and another, e.g., when we send a data file
to another user.
As you can imagine there are strong advocates
for both schemes who are happy to defend their
point of view at great length.
Given the heat of the discussion, it's appropriate
that the names for the conventions were drawn
from Jonathan Swift's "Gulliver's Travels"
in which a civil war is fought over whether
to open a soft-boiled egg at its big end or
its little end.
Let's look at the macros used to assemble
Beta instructions.
The BETAOP helper macro supports the 3-register
instruction format, taking as arguments the
values to be placed in the OPCODE, Ra, Rb,
and Rc fields.
The ".align 4" directive is a bit of administrative
bookkeeping to ensure that instructions will
have a byte address that's a multiple of 4,
i.e., that they span exactly one 32-bit word
in memory.
That's followed by an invocation of the LONG
macro to generate the 4 bytes of binary data
representing the value of the expression shown
here.
The expression is where the actual assembly
of the fields takes place.
Each field is limited to requisite number
of bits using the modulo operator (%), then
shifted left (<<) to the correct position
in the 32-bit word.
And here are the helper macros for the instructions
that use a 16-bit constant as the second operand.
Let's follow the assembly of an ADDC instruction
to see how this works.
The ADDC macro expands into an invocation
of the BETAOPC helper macro, passing along
the correct value for the ADDC opcode, along
with the three operands.
The BETAOPC macro does the following arithmetic:
the OP argument, in this case the value 0x30,
is shifted left to occupy the high-order 6
bits of the instruction.
Then the RA argument, in this case 15, is
placed in its proper location.
The 16-bit constant -32768 is positioned in
the low 16 bits of the instruction.
And, finally, the Rc argument, in this case
0, is positioned in the Rc field of the instruction.
You can see why we call this processing "assembling
an instruction".
The binary representation of an instruction
is assembled from the binary values for each
of the instruction fields.
It's not a complicated process, but it requires
a lot of shifting and masking, tasks that
we're happy to let a computer handle.
Here's the entire sequence of macro expansions
that assemble this ADDC instruction into an
appropriate 32-bit binary value in main memory.
You can see that the knowledge of Beta instruction
formats and opcode values is built into the
bodies of the macro definitions.
The UASM processing is actually quite general.
With a different set of macro definitions
it could process assembly language programs
for almost any ISA!
All the macro definitions for the Beta ISA
are provided in the beta.uasm file, which
is included in each of the assembly language
lab assignments.
Note that we include some convenience macros
to define shorthand representations that provide
common default values for certain operands.
For example, except for procedure calls, we
don't care about the PC+4 value saved in the
destination register by branch instructions,
so almost always would specify R31 as the
Rc register, effectively discarding the PC+4
value saved by branches.
So we define two-argument branch macros that
automatically provide R31 as the destination
register.
Saves some typing, and, more importantly,
it makes it easier to understand the assembly
language program.
Here are a whole set of convenience macros
intended to make programs more readable.
For example, unconditional branches can be
written using the BR() macro rather than the
more cumbersome BEQ(R31,...).
And it's more readable to use branch-false
(BF) and branch-true (BT) macros when testing
the results of a compare instruction.
And note the PUSH and POP macros at the bottom
of page.
These expand into multi-instruction sequences,
in this case to add and remove values from
a stack data structure pointed to by the SP
register.
We call these macros "pseudo instructions"
since they let us provide the programmer with
what appears a larger instruction set,
although underneath the covers we've just
using the same small instruction repertoire
developed in Lecture 9.
In this example we've rewritten the original
code we had for the factorial computation
using pseudo instructions.
For example, CMOVE is a pseudo instruction
for moving small constants into a register.
It's easier for us to read and understand
the intent of a "constant move" operation
than an "add a value to 0" operation provided
by the ADDC expansion of CMOVE.
Anything we can do to remove the cognitive
clutter will be very beneficial in the long
run.