On our to-do list from
the previous section
is figuring out how to build AND
and OR gates with many inputs.
These will be needed
when creating circuit
implementations using a
sum-of-products equation
as our template.
Let’s assume our gate library
only has 2-input gates
and figure how to build wider
gates using the 2-input gates
as building blocks.
We’ll work on creating
3- and 4-input gates,
but the approach we use can
be generalized to create AND
and OR gates of
any desired width.
The approach shown here relies
on the associative property
of the AND operator.
This means we can
perform an N-way
AND by doing pair-wise ANDs
in any convenient order.
The OR and XOR operations
are also associative,
so the same approach will work
for designing wide OR and XOR
circuits from the
corresponding 2-input gate.
Simply substitute 2-input OR
gates or 2-input XOR gates
for the 2-input AND gates shown
below and you’re good to go!
Let’s start by designing a
circuit that computes the AND
of three inputs A, B, and C.
In the circuit shown here,
we first compute (A AND B),
then AND that result with C.
Using the same strategy, we
can build a 4-input AND gate
from three 2-input AND gates.
Essentially we’re building
a chain of AND gates,
which implement an N-way AND
using N-1 2-input AND gates.
We can also associate the
four inputs a different way:
computing (A AND B) in
parallel with (C AND D),
then combining those two
results using a third AND gate.
Using this approach, we’re
building a tree of AND gates.
Which approach is
best: chains or trees?
First we have to decide
what we mean by “best”.
When designing circuits
we’re interested in cost,
which depends on the number of
components, and performance,
which we characterize
by the propagation delay
of the circuit.
Both strategies require the
same number of components
since the total number
of pair-wise ANDs
is the same in both cases.
So it’s a tie when
considering costs.
Now consider propagation delay.
The chain circuit in the middle
has a tPD of 3 gate delays,
and we can see that the
tPD for an N-input chain
will be N-1 gate delays.
The propagation delay
of chains grows linearly
with the number of inputs.
The tree circuit
on the bottom has
a tPD of 2 gates,
smaller than the chain.
The propagation delay of
trees grows logarithmically
with the number of inputs.
Specifically, the
propagation delay
of tree circuits built using
2-input gates grows as log2(N).
When N is large,
tree circuits can
have dramatically
better propagation delay
than chain circuits.
The propagation
delay is an upper
bound on the worst-case
delay from inputs to outputs
and is a good measure
of performance
assuming that all inputs
arrive at the same time.
But in large circuits,
A, B, C and D
might arrive at
different times depending
on the tPD of the circuit
generating each one.
Suppose input D
arrives considerably
after the other inputs.
If we used the tree circuit
to compute the AND of all four
inputs, the additional
delay in computing Z
is two gate delays
after the arrival of D.
However, if we use
the chain circuit,
the additional
delay in computing Z
might be as little
as one gate delay.
The moral of this story:
it’s hard to know which
implementation of a subcircuit,
like the 4-input AND shown
here, will yield the smallest
overall tPD unless we know
the tPD of the circuits
that compute the values
for the input signals.
In designing CMOS circuits,
the individual gates
are naturally inverting, so
instead of using AND and OR
gates, for the best
performance we want to the use
the NAND and NOR
gates shown here.
NAND and NOR gates can be
implemented as a single CMOS
gate involving one pullup
circuit and one pulldown
circuit.
AND and OR gates
require two CMOS gates
in their implementation,
e.g., a NAND gate
followed by an INVERTER.
We’ll talk about how to build
sum-of-products circuitry using
NANDs and NORs in
the next section.
Note that NAND and NOR
operations are not associative:
NAND(A,B,C) is not equal
to NAND(NAND(A,B),C).
So we can’t build a NAND gate
with many inputs by building
a tree of 2-input NANDs.
We’ll talk about this
in the next section too!
We’ve mentioned the
exclusive-or operation,
sometimes called
XOR, several times.
This logic function
is very useful
when building circuitry
for arithmetic or parity
calculations.
As you’ll see in Lab 2,
implementing a 2-input XOR gate
will take many more NFETs
and PFETs than required
for a 2-input NAND or NOR.
We know we can come up with
a sum-of-products expression
for any truth table
and hence build
a circuit implementation
using INVERTERs, AND gates,
and OR gates.
It turns out we
can build circuits
with the same functionality
using only 2-INPUT NAND gates.
We say the the 2-INPUT
NAND is a universal gate.
Here we show how to implement
the sum-of-products building
blocks using just
2-input NAND gates.
In a minute we’ll show a
more direct implementation
for sum-of-products
using only NANDs,
but these little schematics are
a proof-of-concept showing that
NAND-only equivalent
circuits exist.
2-INPUT NOR gates
are also universal,
as shown by these
little schematics.
Inverting logic takes a
little getting used to,
but its the key to designing
low-cost high-performance
circuits in CMOS.