PROFESSOR In this
problem, we are
going to take a look at the
timing constraints associated
with sequential logic circuits.
We are given a generic
state machine diagram,
which has two state bits.
We are also given
the timing parameters
for the combinational logic
and the state register.
Using this data we want
to determine the largest
value for the
register's whole time
that allows the necessary
timing specifications to be met.
In order to satisfy the
whole time of the register,
the input to the register
must remain stable until tHOLD
after the clock edge.
The fastest that a new
change can propagate
to the input of the
register is found
by taking the sum
of the contamination
delays along the shortest
path to that input.
That is [? tCD ?] of the
register plus tCD of the logic.
So tHOLD must be less than or
equal to tCD of the register
plus tCD of the logic.
Plugging in the given
contamination delays,
we find that tHOLD must be less
than or equal to 0.1 plus 0.2,
which equals 0.3 nanoseconds.
What is the smallest
value for the period
of the clock that will meet
the timing specifications?
The clock period must be
long enough for the data
to pass through
the entire circuit
and be ready and
stable for tSETUP
before the next period begins.
The data in this circuit must
propagate through the register
and the combinational logic.
So the constraint
on the clock period
is that tCLOCK has to be
greater than or equal to tPD
of the register plus
tPD of the logic
plus tSETUP of the register.
Plugging in the given
timing parameters,
we find that tCLOCK must be
greater than or equal to 5
plus 3 plus 2, which
equals 10 nanoseconds.
Next, we want to determine
what are the smallest
setup and whole time
specifications on the input
in with respect to the
active edge of the clock
so that we can ensure
that the necessary timing
specifications are met.
The IN input must be stable
and valid long enough
before the rising
clock edge for it
to propagate through
the combinational logic
and arrive at the register
in time for it to setup.
So tSETUP of IN is
greater than or equal
to tPROPAGATION DELAY
of the LOGIC plus
tSETUP of the register.
That equals 3 plus 2,
which equals 5 nanoseconds.
Once the IN input
becomes invalid,
the input to the register
will become invalid
after the contamination
delay of the logic.
IN must stay valid
long enough to ensure
that the input to the register
does not become invalid
before the registers hold time.
So tHOLD of IN plus
tCD of the LOGIC
are greater than or equal
to tHOLD of the register.
This can be rewritten
as tHOLD of IN
must be greater than
or equal to tHOLD
of the register minus
tCD of the LOGIC,
which equals 0.3 minus 0.2.
And that equals 0.1 nanoseconds.