The goal of this problem is
to design a reliable latch.
A latch can be designed using
a multiplexor where the G
input is used to
determine whether or not
a new data value should
be loaded into the latch.
The way the latch works is that
when G = 0, the old value of Q
is fed back through
the multiplexor
so it retains its old value.
When G = 1, the multiplexor
selects D as the input
so Q gets updated to
be the value of D.
The logic function
that describes
the operation of the latch is Q
= (NOT(G) AND Q) OR (G AND D).
We want to build this
latch using only AND, OR,
and inverter gates.
We are given three proposed
designs for the latch.
For each proposed
design, we want
to specify whether the design
is BAD, GOOD, or OBESE.
BAD means that the latch
does not work reliably.
GOOD means that the
latch works reliably.
OBESE means that the latch
works, but uses more gates
than necessary.
Latch proposal A is shown here.
Taking a closer look
at this circuit,
we see that the logic
function that it implements
is Q = (G AND Q) OR D.
This is not the correct
logic equation for a latch,
so this design is BAD.
Next, we take a look
at proposals B and C.
The logic equation for proposal
B is Q = (NOT(G) AND Q)
OR (G AND D)).
This is exactly the
same logic equation
that we specified for our latch.
However, this implementation
is not lenient
because it does not
guarantee that you will not
see glitches on your output
signal when G changes value.
Proposal C, however, includes
the same logic function
Q = (NOT(G) AND Q) OR (G
AND D)) plus one more term
which is OR (Q AND D).
If you create a karnaugh map for
both of these logic functions,
you see that the QD
term is redundant
because it doesn't
add any additional 1's
to the karnaugh map.
This means that logically the
two functions are equivalent,
but the effect of the
extra term is that it makes
the implementation lenient.
So Proposal C is the GOOD
proposal and B is BAD.