One last bit of housekeeping,
then we’re done!
What should our hardware do if
for some reason an instruction
can’t be executed?
For example, if a programming
error has led to trying
to execute some piece of data
as an instruction and the opcode
field doesn’t correspond to a
Beta instruction (a so-called
“illop” or illegal operation).
Or maybe the memory address is
larger than the actual amount
main memory.
Or maybe one of
the operand values
is not acceptable,
e.g., if the B operand
for a DIV instruction is 0.
In modern computers,
the accepted strategy
is cease execution of
the running program
and transfer control to
some error handler code.
The error handler might
store the program state
onto disk for later debugging.
Or, for an unimplemented
but legal opcode,
it might emulate the missing
instruction in software
and resume execution as
if the instruction had
been implemented in hardware!
There’s also the need to
deal with external events,
like those associated
with input and output.
Here we’d like to interrupt
the execution of the current
program, run some code to
deal with the external event,
then resume execution as if the
interrupt had never happened.
To deal with these cases,
we’ll add hardware to treat
exceptions like forced procedure
calls to special code to handle
the situation,
arranging to save the PC+4
value of the interrupted program
so that the handler can
resume execution if it wishes.
This is a very powerful
feature since it
allows us to transfer
control to software to handle
most any circumstance
beyond the capability
of our modest hardware.
As we’ll see in Part
3 of the course,
the exception hardware will be
our key to interfacing running
programs to the operating
system (OS) and to allow the OS
to deal with external
events without any awareness
on the part of the
running program.
So our plan is to interrupt
the running program,
acting like the current
instruction was actually
a procedure call to
the handler code.
When it finishes execution, the
handler can, if appropriate,
use the normal procedure
return sequence
to resume execution
of the user program.
We’ll use the term “exception”
to refer to exceptions caused
by executing the
current program.
Such exceptions are
“synchronous” in the sense that
they are triggered by executing
a particular instruction.
In other words, if the program
was re-run with the same data,
the same exception would occur.
We’ll use the term “interrupt”
to refer to asynchronous
exceptions resulting from
external events whose timing is
unrelated to the
currently running program.
The implementation for
both types of exceptions
is the same.
When an exception is
detected, the Beta hardware
will behave as if the current
instruction was a taken BR
to either location 0x4 (for
synchronous exceptions)
or location 0x8 (for
asynchronous interrupts).
Presumably the instructions
in those locations
will jump to the entry points
of the appropriate handler
routines.
We’ll save the PC+4 value of the
interrupted program into R30,
a register dedicated
to that purpose.
We’ll call that register XP
(“exception pointer”) to remind
ourselves of how we’re using it.
Since interrupts in particular
can happen at any point during
a program’s execution, thus
overwriting the contents of XP
at any time, user programs can’t
use the XP register to hold
values since those values
might disappear at any moment!
Here’s how this scheme works:
suppose we don’t include
hardware to implement the DIV
instruction, so it’s treated
as an illegal opcode.
The exception hardware
forces a procedure call
to location 0x4, which then
branches to the Illop handler
shown here.
The PC+4 value of the DIV
instruction has been saved
in the XP register, so the
handler can fetch the illegal
instruction and, if it
can, emulate its operation
in software.
When handler is complete,
it can resume execution
of the original program at
the instruction following
DIV by performing a JMP(XP).
Pretty neat!
To handle exceptions, we only
need a few simple changes
to the datapath.
We’ve added a MUX controlled
by the WASEL signal to choose
the write-back address
for the register file.
When WASEL is 1, write-back
will occur to the XP register,
i.e., register 30.
When WASEL is 0, write-back
will occur normally, i.e.,
to the register
specified by the RC field
of the current instruction.
The remaining two
inputs of the PCSEL MUX
are set to the constant
addresses for the exception
handlers.
In our case, 0x4 for illegal
operations, and 0x8 for
interrupts.
Here’s the flow of control
during an exception.
The PC+4 value for the
interrupted instruction is
routed through the WDSEL MUX
to be written into the XP
register.
Meanwhile the
control logic chooses
either 3 or 4 as
the value of PCSEL
to select the appropriate next
instruction that will initiate
the handling the exception.
The remaining control signals
are forced to their “don’t
care” values, since we no longer
care about completing execution
of the instruction we had
fetched from main memory
at the beginning of the cycle.
Note that the interrupted
instruction has not
been executed.
So if the exception
handler wishes
to execute the
interrupted instruction,
it will have to subtract 4 from
the value in the XP register
before performing a
JMP(XP) to resume execution
of the interrupted program.