Fixed-length encodings work well when all
the possible choices have the same information
content, i.e., all the choices have an equal
probability of occurring.
If those choices don't have the same information
content, we can do better.
To see how, consider the expected length of
an encoding, computed by considering each
x_i to be encoded, and weighting the length
of its encoding by p_i, the probability of
its occurrence.
By "doing better" we mean that we can find
encodings that have a shorter expected length
than a fixed-length encoding.
Ideally we'd like the expected length of the
encoding for the x_i to match the entropy
H(X), which is the expected information content.
We know that if x_i has a higher probability
(i.e., a larger p_i), that is has a smaller
information content, so we'd like to use shorter
encodings.
If x_i has a lower probability, then we'd
use a longer encoding.
So we'll be constructing encodings where the
x_i may have different length codes - we'll
call these variable-length encodings.
Here's an example we've seen before.
There are four possible choices to encode
(A, B, C, and D), each with the specified
probability.
The table shows a suggested encoding where
we've followed the advice from the previous
slide: high-probability choices that convey
little information (e.g., B) are given shorter
encodings,
while low-probability choices that convey
more information (e.g., C or D) are given
longer encodings.
Let's diagram this encoding as a binary tree.
Since the symbols all appear as the leaves
of the tree, we can see that the encoding
is unambiguous.
Let's try decoding the following encoded data.
We'll use the tree as follows: start at the
root of the tree and use bits from the encoded
data to traverse the tree as directed, stopping
when we reach a leaf.
Starting at the root, the first encoded bit
is 0, which takes us down the left branch
to the leaf B.
So B is the first symbol of the decoded data.
Starting at the root again, 1 takes us down
the right branch, 0 the left branch from there,
and 0 the left branch below that, arriving
at the leaf C, the second symbol of the decoded
data.
Continuing on: 11 gives us A, 0 decodes as
B, 11 gives us A again, and, finally, 101
gives us D.
The entire decoded message is "BCABAD".
The expected length of this encoding is easy
to compute: the length of A's encoding (2
bits) times its probability, plus the length
of B's encoding (1 bit) times 1/2, plus the
contributions for C and D, each 3 times 1/12.
This adds up to 1 and 2/3 bits.
How did we do?
If we had used a fixed-length encoding for
our four possible symbols, we'd have needed
2 bits each, so we'd need 2000 bits to encode
1000 symbols.
Using our variable-length encoding, the expected
length for 1000 symbols would be 1667.
The lower bound on the number of bits needed
to encode 1000 symbols is 1000 times the entropy
H(X), which is 1626 bits, so the variable-length
code got us closer to our goal, but not quite
all the way there.
Could another variable-length encoding have
done better?
In general, it would be nice to have a systematic
way to generate the best-possible variable-length
code, and that's the subject of the next video.