Now let's think a bit about what happens if
there's an error and one or more of the bits
in our encoded data gets corrupted.
We'll focus on single-bit errors, but much
of what we discuss can be generalized to multi-bit
errors.
For example, consider encoding the results
of some unpredictable event, e.g., flipping
a fair coin.
There are two outcomes: "heads", encoded as,
say, 0, and "tails" encoded as 1.
Now suppose some error occurs during processing
- for example, the data is corrupted while
being transmitted from Bob to Alice:
Bob intended to send the message "heads",
but the 0 was corrupted and become a 1 during
transmission, so Alice receives 1, which she
interprets as "tails".
So this simple encoding doesn't work very
well if there's the possibility of single-bit
errors.
To help with our discussion, we'll introduce
the notion of "Hamming distance", defined
as the number of positions in which the corresponding
digits differ in two encodings of the same
length.
For example, here are two 7-bit encodings,
which differ in their third and fifth positions,
so the Hamming distance between the encodings
is 2.
If someone tells us the Hamming distance of
two encodings is 0, then the two encodings
are identical.
Hamming distance is a handy tool for measuring
how encodings differ.
How does this help us think about single-bit
errors?
A single-bit error changes exactly one of
the bits of an encoding, so the Hamming distance
between a valid binary code word and the same
code word with a single-bit error is 1.
The difficulty with our simple encoding is
that the two valid code words ("0" and "1")
also have a Hamming distance of 1.
So a single-bit error changes one valid code
word into another valid code word.
We'll show this graphically, using an arrow
to indicate that two encodings differ by a
single bit, i.e., that the Hamming distance
between the encodings is 1.
The real issue here is that when Alice receives
a 1, she can't distinguish between an uncorrupted
encoding of tails and a corrupted encoding
of heads - she can't detect that an error
occurred.
Let's figure how to solve her problem!
The insight is to come up with a set of valid
code words such that a single-bit error does
NOT produce another valid code word.
What we need are code words that differ by
at least two bits, i.e., we want the minimum
Hamming distance between any two code words
to be at least 2.
If we have a set of code words where the minimum
Hamming distance is 1, we can generate the
set we want by adding a parity bit to each
of the original code words.
There's "even parity" and "odd parity."
Using even parity, the additional parity bit
is chosen so that the total number of 1 bits
in the new code word are even.
For example, our original encoding for "heads"
was 0, adding an even parity bit gives us
00.
Adding an even parity bit to our original
encoding for "tails" gives us 11.
The minimum Hamming distance between code
words has increased from 1 to 2.
How does this help?
Consider what happens when there's a single-bit
error: 00 would be corrupted to 01 or 10,
neither of which is a valid code word.
Aha!
We can detect that a single-bit error has
occurred.
Similarly, single-bit errors for 11 would
also be detected.
Note that the valid code words 00 and 11 both
have an even number of 1-bits, but that the
corrupted code words 01 or 10 have an odd
number of 1-bits.
We say that corrupted code words have a "parity
error".
It's easy to perform a parity check: simply
count the number of 1s in the code word.
If it's even, a single-bit error has NOT occurred;
if it's odd, a single-bit error HAS occurred.
We'll see in a couple of chapters that the
Boolean function exclusive-or can be used
to perform parity checks.
Note that parity won't help us if there's
an even number of bit errors, where a corrupted
code word would have an even number of 1-bits
and hence appear to be okay.
Parity is useful for detecting single-bit
errors; we'll need a more sophisticated encoding
to detect more errors.
In general, to detect some number E of errors,
we need a minimum Hamming distance of E+1
between code words.
We can see this graphically below which shows
how errors can corrupt the valid code words
000 and 111, which have a Hamming distance
of 3.
In theory this means we should be able to
detect up to 2-bit errors.
Each arrow represents a single-bit error and
we can see from the diagram that following
any path of length 2 from either 000 or 111
doesn't get us to the other valid code word.
In other words, assuming we start with either
000 or 111, we can detect the occurrence of
up to 2 errors.
Basically our error detection scheme relies
on choosing code words far enough apart, as
measured by Hamming distance, so that E errors
can't corrupt one valid code word so that
it looks like another valid code word.