In discussing out-of-order superscalar pipelined
CPUs we commented that the costs grow very
quickly relative to the performance gains,
leading to the cost-performance curve shown
here.
If we move down the curve, we can arrive at
more efficient architectures that give, say,
1/2 the performance at a 1/4 of the cost.
When our applications involve independent
computations that can be performed in a parallel,
it may be that we would be able to use two
cores to provide the same performance as the
original expensive core, but a fraction of
the cost.
If the available parallelism allows us to
use additional cores, we'll see a linear relationship
between increased performance vs. increased
cost.
The key, of course, is that desired computations
can be divided into multiple tasks that can
run independently, with little or no need
for communication or coordination between
the tasks.
What is the optimal tradeoff between core
cost and the number of cores?
If our computation is arbitrarily divisible
without incurring additional overhead,
then we would continue to move down the curve
until we found the cost-performance point
that gave us the desired performance at the
least cost.
In reality, dividing the computation across
many cores does involve some overhead, e.g.,
distributing the data and code, then collecting
and aggregating the results, so the optimal
tradeoff is harder to find.
Still, the idea of using a larger number of
smaller, more efficient cores seems attractive.
Many applications have some computations that
can be performed in parallel, but also have
computations that won't benefit from parallelism.
To understand the speedup we might expect
from exploiting parallelism, it's useful to
perform the calculation proposed by computer
scientist Gene Amdahl in 1967, now known as
Amdahl's Law.
Suppose we're considering an enhancement that
speeds up some fraction F of the task at hand
by a factor of S.
As shown in the figure, the gray portion of
the task now takes F/S of the time that it
used to require.
Some simple arithmetic lets us calculate the
overall speedup we get from using the enhancement.
One conclusion we can draw is that we'll benefit
the most from enhancements that affect a large
portion of the required computations, i.e.,
we want to make F as large a possible.
What's the best speedup we can hope for if
we have many cores that can be used to speed
up the parallel part of the task?
Here's the speedup formula based on F and
S, where in this case F is the parallel fraction
of the task.
If we assume that the parallel fraction of
the task can be speed up arbitrarily by using
more and more cores, we see that the best
possible overall speed up is 1/(1-F).
For example, you write a program that can
do 90% of its work in parallel, but the other
10% must be done sequentially.
The best overall speedup that can be achieved
is a factor of 10, no matter how many cores
you have at your disposal.
Turning the question around, suppose you have
a 1000-core machine which you hope to be able
to use to achieve a speedup of 500 on your
target application.
You would need to be able parallelize 99.8%
of the computation in order to reach your
goal!
Clearly multicore machines are most useful
when the target task has lots of natural parallelism.
Using multiple independent cores to execute
a parallel task is called thread-level parallelism
(TLP), where each core executes a separate
computation "thread".
The threads are independent programs, so the
execution model is potentially more flexible
than the lock-step execution provided by vector
machines.
When there are a small number of threads,
you often see the cores sharing a common main
memory, allowing the threads to communicate
and synchronize by sharing a common address
space.
We'll discuss this further in the next section.
This is the approach used in current multicore
processors, which have between 2 and 12 cores.
Shared memory becomes a real bottleneck when
there 10's or 100's of cores, since collectively
they quickly overwhelm the available memory
bandwidth.
In these architectures, threads communicate
using a communication network to pass messages
back and forth.
We discussed possible network topologies in
an earlier lecture.
A cost-effective on-chip approach is to use
a nearest-neighbor mesh network, which supports
many parallel point-to-point communications,
while still allowing multi-hop communication
between any two cores.
Message passing is also used in computing
clusters, where many ordinary CPUs collaborate
on large tasks.
There's a standardized message passing interface
(MPI) and
specialized, very high throughput, low latency
message-passing communication networks (e.g.,
Infiniband) that make it easy to build high-performance
computing clusters.
In the next couple of sections we'll look
more closely at some of the issues involved
in building shared-memory multicore processors.