We'll use the stack to hold a procedure's
activation record.
That includes the values of the arguments
to the procedure call.
We'll allocate words on the stack to hold
the values of the procedure's local variables,
assuming we don't keep them in registers.
And we'll use the stack to save the return
address (passed in LP) so the procedure can
make nested procedure calls without overwriting
its return address.
The responsibility for allocating and deallocating
the activation record will be shared between
the calling procedure (the "caller") and the
called procedure (the "callee").
The caller is responsible for evaluating the
argument expressions and saving their values
in the activation record being built on the
stack.
We'll adopt the convention that the arguments
are pushed in reverse order, i.e., the first
argument will be the last to be pushed on
the stack.
We'll explain why we made this choice in a
couple of slides…
The code compiled for a procedure involves
a sequence of expression evaluations, each
followed by a PUSH to save the calculated
value on the stack.
So when the callee starts execution, the top
of the stack contains the value of the first
argument, the next word down the value of
the second argument, and so on.
After the argument values, if any, have been
pushed on the stack, there's a BR to transfer
control to the procedure's entry point,
saving the address of the instruction following
the BR in the linkage pointer, R28, a register
that we'll dedicate to that purpose.
When the callee returns and execution resumes
in the caller, a DEALLOCATE is used to remove
all the argument values from the stack, preserving
stack discipline.
So that's the code the compiler generates
for the procedure.
The rest of the work happens in the called
procedure.
The code at the start of the called procedure
completes the allocation of the activation
record.
Since when we're done the activation record
will occupy a bunch of consecutive words on
the stack, we'll sometimes refer to the activation
record as a "stack frame" to remind us of
where it lives.
The first action is to save the return address
found in the LP register.
This frees up LP to be used by any nested
procedure calls in the body of the callee.
In order to make it easy to access values
stored in the activation record, we'll dedicate
another register called the "base pointer"
(BP = R27) which will point to the stack frame
we're building.
So as we enter the procedure, the code saves
the pointer to the caller's stack frame, and
then uses the current value of the stack pointer
to make BP point to the current stack frame.
We'll see how we use BP in just a moment.
Now the code will allocate words in the stack
frame to hold the values for the callee's
local variables, if any.
Finally, the callee needs to save the values
of any registers it will use when executing
the rest of its code.
These saved values can be used to restore
the register values just before returning
to the caller.
This is called the "callee saves" convention
where the callee guarantees that all register
values will be preserved across the procedure
call.
With this convention, the code in the caller
can assume any values it placed in registers
before a nested procedure call will still
be there when the nested call returns.
Note that dedicating a register as the base
pointer isn't strictly necessary.
All accesses to the values on the stack can
be made relative to the stack pointer, but
the offsets from SP will change as values
are PUSHed and POPed from the stack, e.g.,
during procedure calls.
It will be easier to understand the generated
code if we use BP for all stack frame references.
Let's return to the question about the order
of argument values in the stack frame.
We adopted the convention of PUSHing the values
in reverse order, i.e., where the value of
the first argument is the last one to be PUSHED.
So, why PUSH argument values in reverse order?
With the arguments PUSHed in reverse order,
the first argument (labeled "arg 0") will
be at a fixed offset from the base pointer
regardless of the number of argument values
pushed on the stack.
The compiler can use a simple formula to the
determine the correct BP offset value for
any particular argument.
So the first argument is at offset -12, the
second at -16, and so on.
Why is this important?
Some languages, such as C, support procedure
calls with a variable number of arguments.
Usually the procedure can determine from,
say, the first argument, how many additional
arguments to expect.
The canonical example is the C printf function
where the first argument is a format string
that specifies how a sequence of values should
be printed.
So a call to printf includes the format string
argument plus a varying number of additional
arguments.
With our calling convention the format string
will always be in the same location relative
to BP, so the printf code can find it without
knowing the number of additional arguments
in the current call.
The local variables are also at fixed offsets
from BP.
The first local variable is at offset 0, the
second at offset 4, and so on.
So, we see that having a base pointer makes
it easy to access the values of the arguments
and local variables using fixed offsets that
can be determined at compile time.
The stack above the local variables is available
for other uses, e.g., building the activation
record for a nested procedure call!