We are given this circuit which consists of
nine combinational modules connected as shown.
The number in each block corresponds to the
propagation delay (in microseconds) of that
block.
The first question we want to ask ourselves
is what are the latency and throughput of
this combinational circuit?
The longest path through this circuit passes
through two 3 microsecond modules, one 2 microsecond
module, and two 1 microsecond modules.
Therefore the latency = 2(3) + 1(2) + 2(1)
= 10 microseconds.
The throughput is 1/Latency = 1/(10 microseconds).
Now we want to pipeline this circuit for maximum
throughput.
Recall that the clock period must allow enough
time for the propagation delay of the pipeline
register, plus the propagation delay of any
combinational logic between the pipeline registers,
plus the setup time of the pipeline register.
Since our pipeline registers are ideal, the
propagation delay and setup time of the pipeline
registers is 0, so our clock period will be
equal to the longest combinational logic delay
between any pair of pipeline registers.
To minimize the clock period, we want to add
pipeline contours so that each pipeline stage
can be clocked at the rate of our slowest
component which is 3 microseconds.
This means that within a single pipeline stage
all combinational paths must have at most
a propagation delay of 3 microseconds.
Recall, that when pipelining a circuit, all
outputs must have a pipeline register on them,
so our first contour is drawn so as to cross
the single output C(X).
Each pipeline stage should have at most a
latency of 3 microseconds.
This means that the bottom right 1 microsecond
module and the 3 microsecond module above
it must be in separate pipeline stages so
our next contour crosses between them.
We then complete that contour by joining each
end of the contour to one of the two ends
of our original output contour.
Every time a wire is crossed, that indicates
that we are adding a pipeline register.
There is more than one way of doing this because
for example, the bottom three 1 units could
all be in the same pipeline stage, or just
the two rightmost bottom 1 unit components,
or just the single bottom right 1 unit component.
Let's try to pipeline this circuit in two
different ways to make sure that we end up
with the same latency and throughput results.
For our first implementation, let's put the
bottom right 1 unit in its own pipeline stage.
Next we have a pipeline stage that includes
our second row 3 unit.
We can include the middle bottom 1 unit in
this same pipeline stage because those two
units are independent of each other and can
be executed in parallel.
Now we see that we have a bunch of 2 and 1
unit components.
We want to isolate these from the top left
3 unit component, so we draw our final contour
to isolate that 3 unit.
Note that at this point all the remaining
2 and 1 unit modules add up to at most 3 microseconds
along any path in the second pipeline stage.
This means that we are done and we do not
need to add any further pipeline stages.
So our pipelined circuit ended up with 4 pipeline
stages and our clock period = 3 microseconds.
This means that our pipelined latency is 4
* T = 4 * 3 = 12 microseconds.
Our throughput for the pipelined circuit is
1/T = 1/(3 microseconds).
Note that the latency of the pipelined circuit
is actually slower than the combinational
latency.
This occurs because our pipelined implementation
has some unused cycles in the last pipeline
stage.
However, our throughput is significantly better
as a result of being able to now have our
clock period equal to the length of the slowest
component.
Recall that we said that this was not the
only way that we could draw our contours.
Let's try an alternate solution.
For our second solution, let's try to merge
the bottom three 1 units into one pipeline
stage.
Next we need to isolate our middle 3.
The remaining 2 and 1 unit components can
all be merged into another pipeline stage.
Finally, the top left 3 ends up in its own
pipeline stage.
As before we end up with 4 pipeline stages
that can be clocked with a period of T = 3
microseconds.
This demonstrates that both component divisions
end up with a latency of 12 microseconds and
a throughput of 1/(3 microseconds).
Now suppose you found pipelined replacements
for the components marked 3 and 2 that had
3 and 2 stages, respectively, and could be
clocked at a 1 microsecond period.
Using these replacements and pipelining for
maximum throughput, what is the best achievable
performance?
With these new components that can each be
clocked with a period of 1 microsecond, our
clock period T goes down to 1 microsecond.
The number of stages in our pipeline, however,
now rises to 10 stages because these new components
each have multiple pipeline stages in them.
So our new latency is L = 10 * T = 10(1) = 10
microseconds.
The throughput is 1/T = 1/(1 microsecond).