Okay, one more cache design decision to make,
then we're done!
How should we handle memory writes in the
cache?
Ultimately we'll need update main memory with
the new data, but when should that happen?
The most obvious choice is to perform the
write immediately.
In other words, whenever the CPU sends a write
request to the cache, the cache then performs
the same write to main memory.
This is called "write-through".
That way main memory always has the most up-to-date
value for all locations.
But this can be slow if the CPU has to wait
for a DRAM write access - writes could become
a real bottleneck!
And what if the program is constantly writing
a particular memory location, e.g., updating
the value of a local variable in the current
stack frame?
In the end we only need to write the last
value to main memory.
Writing all the earlier values is waste of
memory bandwidth.
Suppose we let the CPU continue execution
while the cache waits for the write to main
memory to complete - this is called "write-behind".
This will overlap execution of the program
with the slow writes to main memory.
Of course, if there's another cache miss while
the write is still pending, everything will
have to wait at that point until both the
write and subsequent refill read finish, since
the CPU can't proceed until the cache miss
is resolved.
The best strategy is called "write-back" where
the contents of the cache are updated and
the CPU continues execution immediately.
The updated cache value is only written to
main memory when the cache line is chosen
as the replacement line for a cache miss.
This strategy minimizes the number of accesses
to main memory, preserving the memory bandwidth
for other operations.
This is the strategy used by most modern processors.
Write-back is easy to implement.
Returning to our original cache recipe, we
simply eliminate the start of the write to
main memory when there's a write request to
the cache.
We just update the cache contents and leave
it at that.
However, replacing a cache line becomes a
more complex operation, since we can't reuse
the cache line without first writing its contents
back to main memory in case they had been
modified by an earlier write access.
Hmm.
Seems like this does a write-back of all replaced
cache lines whether or not they've been written
to.
We can avoid unnecessary write-backs by adding
another state bit to each cache line: the
"dirty" bit.
The dirty bit is set to 0 when a cache line
is filled during a cache miss.
If a subsequent write operation changes the
data in a cache line, the dirty bit is set
to 1, indicating that value in the cache now
differs from the value in main memory.
When a cache line is selected for replacement,
we only need to write its data back to main
memory if its dirty bit is 1.
So a write-back strategy with a dirty bit
gives an elegant solution that minimizes the
number of writes to main memory and only delays
the CPU on a cache miss if a dirty cache line
needs to be written back to memory.
That concludes our discussion of caches, which
was motivated by our desire to minimize the
average memory access time by building a hierarchical
memory system that had both low latency and
high capacity.
There were a number of strategies we employed
to achieve our goal.
Increasing the number of cache lines decreases
AMAT by decreasing the miss ratio.
Increasing the block size of the cache let
us take advantage of the fast column accesses
in a DRAM to efficiently load a whole block
of data on a cache miss.
The expectation was that this would improve
AMAT by increasing the number of hits in the
future as accesses were made to nearby locations.
Increasing the number of ways in the cache
reduced the possibility of cache line conflicts,
lowering the miss ratio.
Choosing the least-recently used cache line
for replacement minimized the impact of replacement
on the hit ratio.
And, finally, we chose to handle writes using
a write-back strategy with dirty bits.
How do we make the tradeoffs among all these
architectural choices?
As usual, we'll simulate different cache organizations
and chose the architectural mix that provides
the best performance on our benchmark programs.