Okay, it's finally time to investigate issues
caused by asynchronous inputs to a sequential
logic circuit.
By "asynchronous" we mean that the timing
of transitions on the input is completely
independent of the timing of the sequential
logic clock.
This situation arises when the inputs arrive
from the outside world where the timing of
events is not under our control.
As we saw at the end of Chapter 5, to ensure
reliable operation of the state registers
inputs to a sequential logic system have to
obey setup and hold time constraints relative
to the rising edge of the system clock.
Clearly if the input can change at anytime,
it can change at time that would violate the
setup and hold times.
Maybe we can come up with a synchronizer circuit
that takes an unsynchronized input signal
and produces a synchronized signal that only
changes shortly after the rising edge of the
clock.
We'd use a synchronizer on each asynchronous
input and solve our timing problems that way.
Here's a detailed specification for our synchronizer.
The synchronizer has two inputs, IN and CLK,
which have transitions at time t_IN and t_C
respectively.
If IN's transition happens sufficiently before
C's transition, we want the synchronizer to
output a 1 within some bounded time t_D after
CLK's transition.
And if CLK's transition happens sufficient
before IN's transition, we want the synchronizer
to output a 0 within time t_D after CLK's
transition.
Finally, if the two transitions are closer
together than some specified interval t_E,
the synchronizer can output either a 0 or
a 1 within time t_D of CLK's transition.
Either answer is fine so long as it's a stable
digital 0 or digital 1 by the specified deadline.
This turns out to be an unsolvable problem!
For no finite values of t_E and t_D can we
build a synchronizer that's guaranteed to
meet this specification even when using components
that are 100% reliable.
But can't we just use a D register to solve
the problem?
We'll connect IN to the register's data input
and connect CLK to the register's clock input.
We'll set the decision time t_D to the propagation
delay of the register and the allowable error
interval to the larger of the register's setup
and hold times.
Our theory is that if the rising edge of IN
occurs at least t_SETUP before the rising
edge of CLK, the register is guaranteed to
output a 1.
And if IN transitions more than t_HOLD after
the rising edge of CLK, the register is guaranteed
to output a 0.
So far, so good.
If IN transitions during the setup and hold
times with respect to the rising edge on CLK,
we know we've violated the dynamic discipline
and we can't tell whether the register will
store a 0 or a 1.
But in this case, our specification lets us
produce either answer, so we're good to go,
right?
Sadly, we're not good to go.
We're lured by the digital abstraction into
assuming that even if we violate the dynamic
discipline that Q must be either 1 or 0 after
the propagation delay.
But that isn't a valid assumption as we'll
see when we look more carefully at the operation
of the register's master latch when B and
C change at about the same time.
Recall that the master latch is really just
a lenient MUX that can be configured as a
bi-stable storage element using a positive
feedback loop.
When the latch is in memory mode, it's essentially
a two-gate cyclic circuit whose behavior has
two constraints:
the voltage transfer characteristic of the
two-gate circuit, shown in green on the graph,
and that V_IN = V_OUT, a constraint that's
shown in red on the graph.
These two curves intersect at three points.
Our concern is the middle point of intersection.
If IN and CLK change at the same time, the
voltage on Q may be in transition at the time
the MUX closes and enables the positive feedback
loop.
So the initial voltage in the feedback loop
may happen to be at or very near the voltage
of the middle intersection point.
When Q is at the metastable voltage, the storage
loop is in an unstable equilibrium called
the metastable state.
In theory the system could balance at this
point forever, but a small change in the voltages
in the loop will move the system away from
the metastable equilibrium point and set it
irrevocably in motion towards the stable equilibrium
points.
Here's the issue we face: we can't bound the
amount of time the system will spend in the
metastable state.
Here's what we know about the metastable state.
It's in the forbidden zone of the digital
signaling specifications and so corresponds
to an invalid logic level.
Violating the dynamic discipline means that
our register is no longer guaranteed to produce
a digital output in bounded time.
A persistent invalid logic level can wreak
both logical and electrical havoc in our sequential
logic circuit.
Since combinational logic gates with invalid
inputs have unpredictable outputs, an invalid
signal may corrupt the state and output values
in our sequential system.
At the electrical level, if an input to a
CMOS gate is at the metastable voltage, both
PFET and NFET switches controlled by that
input would be conducting, so we'd have a
path between V_DD and GROUND, causing a spike
in the system's power dissipation.
It's an unstable equilibrium and will eventually
be resolved by a transition to one of the
two stable equilibrium points.
You can see from the graph that the metastable
voltage is in the high-gain region of the
VTC, so a small change in V_IN results in
a large change in V_OUT, and once away from
the metastable point the loop voltage will
move towards 0 or V_DD.
The time it takes for the system to evolve
to a stable equilibrium is related to how
close Q's voltage was to the metastable point
when the positive feedback loop was enabled.
The closer Q's initial voltage is to the metastable
voltage, the longer it will take for the system
to resolve the metastability.
But since there's no lower bound on how close
Q is to the metastable voltage, there's no
upper bound on the time it will take for resolution.
In other words, if you specify a bound, e.g.,
t_D, on the time available for resolution,
there's a range of initial Q voltages that
won't be resolved within that time.
If the system goes metastable at some point
in time, then there's a non-zero probability
that the system will still be metastable after
some interval T, for any finite choice of
T.
The good news is that the probability of being
metastable at the end of the interval decreases
exponentially with increasing T.
Note that every bistable system has at least
one metastable state.
So metastability is the price we pay for building
storage elements from positive feedback loops.
If you'd like to read a more thorough discussion
of synchronizers and related problems and
learn about the mathematics behind the exponential
probabilities, please see Chapter 10 of the
Course Notes.
Our approach to dealing with asynchronous
inputs is to put the potentially metastable
value coming out of our D-register synchronizer
into "quarantine" by adding a second register
hooked to the output of the first register.
If a transition on the input violates the
dynamic discipline and causes the first register
to go metastable, it's not immediately an
issue since the metastable value is stopped
from entering the system by the second register.
In fact, during the first half of the clock
cycle, the master latch in the second register
is closed, so the metastable value is being
completely ignored.
It's only at the next clock edge, an entire
clock period later, that the second D register
will need a valid and stable input.
There's still some probability that the first
register will be metastable after an entire
clock period, but we can make that probability
as low as we wish by choosing a sufficiently
long clock period.
In other words, the output of the second register,
which provides the signal used by the internal
combinational logic, will be stable and valid
with a probability of our choosing.
Validity is not 100% guaranteed, but the failure
times are measured in years or decades, so
it's not an issue in practice.
Without the second register, the system might
see a metastability failure every handful
of hours - the exact failure rate depends
on the transition frequencies and gains in
the circuit.
What happens if our clock period is short
but we want a long quarantine time?
We can use multiple quarantine registers in
series.
It's the total delay between when the first
register goes metastable and when the synchronized
input is used by the internal logic that determines
the failure probability.
The bottom line?
We can use synchronizing registers to quarantine
potentially metastable signals for some period
of time.
Since the probability of still being metastable
decreases exponentially with the quarantine
time, we can reduce the failure probability
to any desired level.
Not a 100% guaranteed, but close enough that
metastability is not a practical issue if
we use our quarantine strategy.