ISA designers receive many requests for what
are affectionately known as "features" - additional
instructions that, in theory, will make the
ISA better in some way.
Dealing with such requests is the moment to
apply our quantitive approach in order to
be able to judge the tradeoffs between cost
and benefits.
Our first "feature request" is to allow small
constants as the second operand in ALU instructions.
So if we replaced the 5-bit "rb" field, we
would have room in the instruction to include
a 16-bit constant as bits [15:0] of the instruction.
The argument in favor of this request is that
small constants appear frequently in many
programs and it would make programs shorter
if we didn't have use load operations to read
constant values from main memory.
The argument against the request is that we
would need additional control and datapath
logic to implement the feature, increasing
the hardware cost and probably decreasing
the performance.
So our strategy is to modify our benchmark
programs to use the ISA augmented with this
feature and measure the impact on a simulated
execution.
Looking at the results, we find that there
is compelling evidence that small constants
are indeed very common as the second operands
to many operations.
Note that we're not so much interested in
simply looking at the code.
Instead we want to look at what instructions
actually get executed while running the benchmark
programs.
This will take into account that instructions
executed during each iteration of a loop might
get executed 1000's of times even though they
only appear in the program once.
Looking at the results, we see that over half
of the arithmetic instructions have a small
constant as their second operand.
Comparisons involve small constants 80% of
the time.
This probably reflects the fact that during
execution comparisons are used in determining
whether we've reached the end of a loop.
And small constants are often found in address
calculations done by load and store operations.
Operations involving constant operands are
clearly a common case, one well worth optimizing.
Adding support for small constant operands
to the ISA resulted in programs that were
measurably smaller and faster.
So: feature request approved!
Here we see the second of the two Beta instruction
formats.
It's a modification of the first format where
we've replaced the 5-bit "rb" field with a
16-bit field holding a constant in two's complement
format.
This will allow us to represent constant operands
in the range of 0x8000 (decimal -32768) to
0x7FFF (decimal 32767).
Here's an example of the add-constant (ADDC)
instruction which adds the contents of R1
and the constant -3, writing the result into
R3.
We can see that the second operand in the
symbolic representation is now a constant
(or, more generally, an expression that can
evaluated to get a constant value).
One technical detail needs discussion: the
instruction contains a 16-bit constant, but
the datapath requires a 32-bit operand.
How does the datapath hardware go about converting
from, say, the 16-bit representation of -3
to the 32-bit representation of -3?
Comparing the 16-bit and 32-bit representations
for various constants, we see that if the
16-bit two's-complement constant is negative
(i.e., its high-order bit is 1), the high
sixteen bits of the equivalent 32-bit constant
are all 1's.
And if the 16-bit constant is non-negative
(i.e., its high-order bit is 0), the high
sixteen bits of the 32-bit constant are all
0's.
Thus the operation the hardware needs to perform
is "sign extension" where the sign-bit of
the 16-bit constant is replicated sixteen
times to form the high half of the 32-bit
constant.
The low half of the 32-bit constant is simply
the 16-bit constant from the instruction.
No additional logic gates will be needed to
implement sign extension - we can do it all
with wiring.
Here are the fourteen ALU instructions in
their "with constant" form, showing the same
instruction mnemonics but with a "C" suffix
indicate the second operand is a constant.
Since these are additional instructions, these
have different opcodes than the original ALU
instructions.
Finally, note that if we need a constant operand
whose representation does NOT fit into 16
bits, then we have to store the constant as
a 32-bit value in a main memory location and
load it into a register for use just like
we would any variable value.
To give some sense for the additional datapath
hardware that will be needed, let's update
our implementation sketch to add support for
constants as the second ALU operand.
We don't have to add much hardware:
just a multiplexer which selects either the
"rb" register value or the sign-extended constant
from the 16-bit field in the instruction.
The BSEL control signal that controls the
multiplexer is 1 for the ALU-with-constant
instructions and 0 for the regular ALU instructions.
We'll put the hardware implementation details
aside for now and revisit them in a few lectures.