Earlier we talked about about finding equivalent
FSMs with fewer states.
Now we'll develop an approach for finding
such FSMs by looking for two states that that
can be merged into a single state without
changing the behavior of the FSM in any externally
distinguishable manner.
Two states are equivalent if they meet the
following two criteria.
First, the states must have identical outputs.
This makes sense: the outputs are visible
to the outside, so if their values differed
between the two states, that difference would
clearly be externally distinguishable!
Second, for each combination of input values,
the two states transition to equivalent states.
Our strategy for deriving an equivalent machine
with fewer states will be to start with our
original FSM, find pairs of equivalent states
and merge those states.
We'll keep repeating the process until we
can't find any more equivalent states.
Let's try this on our ant FSM.
First we need to find a pair of states that
have the same outputs.
As it turns out, there's only one such pair:
WALL1 and CORNER, both of which assert the
turn-right and forward outputs.
Okay, so let's assume that WALL1 and CORNER
are equivalent and ask if they transition
to equivalent states for each applicable combination
of input values.
For these two states, all the transitions
depend only on the value of the R input, so
we just have to check two cases.
If R is 0, both states transition to CORNER.
If R is 1, both states transition to WALL2.
So both equivalence criteria are satisfied
and we can conclude that the WALL1 and CORNER
states are equivalent and can be merged.
This gives us the four-state FSM shown here,
where we've called the single merged state
WALL1.
This smaller, equivalent FSM behaves exactly
as the previous 5-state FSM.
The implementation of the 5-state machine
requires 3 state bits; the implementation
of the 4-state machine only requires 2 state
bits.
Reducing the number of state bits by 1 is
huge since it reduces the size of the required
ROM by half!
Just as we were able to achieve considerable
hardware savings by minimizing Boolean equations,
we can do the same in sequential logic by
merging equivalent states.
Roboant customers are looking forward to the
price cut!
Let's look at what we'd need to do if we wanted
to implement the FSM using logic gates instead
a ROM for the combinational logic.
First we have to build the truth table, entering
all the transitions in the state transition
diagram.
We'll start with the LOST state.
So if the FSM is in this state, the F output
should be 1.
If both antenna inputs are 0, the next state
is also LOST.
Assigning the LOST state the encoding 00,
we've captured this information in the first
row of the table.
If either antenna is touching, the FSM should
transition from LOST to the rotate-counterclockwise
state.
We've given this an encoding of 01.
There are three combinations of L and R values
that match this transition, so we've added
three rows to the truth table.
This takes care of all the transitions from
the LOST state.
Now we can tackle the transitions from the
rotate-counterclockwise state.
If either antenna is touching, the next state
is again rotate-counterclockwise.
So we've identified the matching values for
the inputs and added the appropriate three
rows to the transition table.
We can continue in a similar manner to encode
the transitions one-by-one.
Here's the final table, where we've used don't
cares to reduce the number of rows for presentation.
Next we want to come up with Boolean equations
for each of the outputs of the combinational
logic, i.e., the two next-state bits and the
three motion-control outputs.
Here are the Karnaugh maps for the two next-state
bits.
Using our K-map skills from Chapter 4, we'll
find a cover of the prime implicants for S1-prime
and write down the corresponding product terms
in a minimal sum-of-products equation.
And then do the same for the other next-state
bit.
We can follow a similar process to derive
minimal sum-of-products expressions for the
motion-control outputs.
Implementing each sum-of-products in a straight-forward
fashion with AND and OR gates, we get the
following schematic for the ant brain.
Pretty neat!
Who knew that maze following behavior could
be implemented with a couple of D registers
and a handful of logic gates?
There are many complex behaviors that can
be created with surprisingly simple FSMs.
Early on, the computer graphics folks learned
that group behaviors like swarming, flocking
and schooling can be modeled by equipping
each participant with a simple FSM.
So next time you see the massive battle scene
from the Lord of the Rings movie, think of
many FSMs running in parallel!
Physical behaviors that arise from simple
interactions between component molecules can
sometimes be more easily modeled using cellular
automata -
arrays of communicating FSMS - than by trying
to solve the partial differential equations
that model the constraints on the molecules'
behavior.
And here's an idea: what if we allowed the
FSM to modify its own transition table?
Hmm.
Maybe that's a plausible model for evolution!
FSMs are everywhere!
You'll see FSMs for the rest of your life…