We are given the combinational circuit shown
here consisting of an inverter, an AND gate,
an exclusive OR gate, and a multiplexor.
We are also provided with the contamination
and propagation delays for each of the components
in the circuit.
We are then asked to determine the contamination
delay and propagation delay for the entire
circuit.
The propagation delay of a circuit is defined
as the longest delay that can occur from when
the inputs changed to when the output becomes
stable.
In order to calculate the propagation delay
of a circuit, we need to identify the path
from input to output whose sum of the propagation
delays is the largest.
For this circuit, the longest delay path is
through the exclusive or gate and the multiplexor.
The sum of the propagation delay across these
2 gates is 2.1 + 1.5 = 3.6 ns.
The contamination delay of a circuit is defined
as the shortest delay from when the inputs
change to when the outputs begin to change,
or when the outputs are no longer guaranteed
to be holding their previous stable value.
In order to calculate the contamination delay,
we find the path whose sum of the contamination
delays is the least.
For this circuit, the shortest path is from
input A through the selector of the multiplexor.
So the contamination delay for this circuit
is equal to the contamination delay of the
multiplexor which equals 0.2 ns.