So, how hard can it be to build a communication
channel?
Aren't they just logic circuits with a long
wire that runs from one component to another?
A circuit theorist would tell you that wires
in a schematic diagram are intended to represent
the equipotential nodes of the circuit, which
are used to connect component terminals.
In this simple model, a wire has the same
voltage at all points and any changes in the
voltage or current at one component terminal
is instantly propagated to the other component
terminals connected to the same wire.
The notion of distance is abstracted out of
our circuit models: terminals are either connected
by a wire, or they're not.
If there are resistances, capacitances, and
inductances that need to be accounted for,
the necessary components can be added to the
circuit model.
Wires are timeless.
They are used to show how components connect,
but they aren't themselves components.
In fact, thinking of wires as equipotential
nodes is a very workable model when the rate
of change of the voltage on the wire is slow
compared to the time it takes for an electromagnetic
wave to propagate down the wire.
Only as circuit speeds have increased with
advances in integrated circuit technologies
did this rule-of-thumb start to be violated
in logic circuits where the components were
separated by at most 10's of inches.
In fact, it has been known since the late
1800s that changes in voltage levels take
finite time to propagate down a wire.
Oliver Heaviside was a self-taught English
electrical engineer who, in the 1880's, developed
a set of "telegrapher's equations" that described
how signals propagate down wires.
Using these, he was able to show how to improve
the rate of transmission on then new transatlantic
telegraph cable by a factor of 10.
We now know that for high-speed signaling
we have to treat wires as transmission lines,
which we'll say more about in the next few
slides.
In this domain, the distance between components
and hence the lengths of wires is of critical
concern if we want to correctly predict the
performance of our circuits.
Distance and signal propagation matter - real-world
wires are, in fact, fairly complex components!
Here's an electrical model for an infinitesimally
small segment of a real-world wire.
An actual wire is correctly modeled by imagining
a many copies of the model shown here connected
end-to-end.
The signal, i.e., the voltage on the wire,
is measured with respect to the reference
node which is also shown in the model.
There are 4 parameters that characterize the
behavior of the wire.
R tells us the resistance of the conductor.
It's usually negligible for the wiring on
printed circuit boards, but it can be significant
for long wires in integrated circuits.
L represents the self-inductance of the conductor,
which characterizes how much energy will be
absorbed by the wire's magnetic fields when
the current flowing through the wire changes.
The conductor and reference node are separated
by some sort insulator (which might be just
air!) and hence form a capacitor with capacitance
C.
Finally, the conductance G represents the
current that leaks through the insulator.
Usually this is quite small.
The table shows the parameter values we might
measure for wires inside an integrated circuit
and on printed circuit boards.
If we analyze what happens when sending signals
down the wire, we can describe the behavior
of the wires using a single component called
a transmission line, which has a characteristic
complex-valued impedance Z_0.
At high signaling frequencies and over the
distances found on-chip or on circuit boards,
such as one might find in a modern digital
system, the transmission line is lossless,
and voltage changes ("steps") propagate down
the wire at the rate of 1/sqrt(LC) meters
per second.
Using the values given here for a printed
circuit board, the characteristic impedance
is approximately 50 ohms and the speed of
propagation is about 18 cm (7") per ns.
To send digital information from one component
to another, we change the voltage on the connecting
wire, and that voltage step propagates from
the sender to the receiver.
We have to pay some attention to what happens
to that energy front when it gets to the end
of the wire!
If we do nothing to absorb that energy, conservation
laws tell us that it reflects off the end
of the wire as an "echo" and soon our wire
will be full of echoes from previous voltage
steps!
To prevent these echoes we have to terminate
the wire with a resistance to ground that
matches the characteristic impedance of the
transmission line.
If the signal can propagate in both directions,
we'll need to terminate at both ends.
What this model is telling is the time it
takes to transmit information from one component
to another and that we have to be careful
to absorb the energy associated with the transmission
when the information has reached its destination.
With that little bit of theory as background,
we're in a position to describe the real-world
consequences of poor engineering of our signal
wires.
The key observation is that unless we're careful
there can still be energy left over from previous
transmissions that might corrupt the current
transmission.
The general fix to this problem is time, i.e.,
giving the transmitted value a longer time
to settle to an interference-free value.
But slowing down isn't usually acceptable
in high-performance systems, so we have to
do our best to minimize these energy-storage
effects.
If the termination isn't exactly right, we'll
get some reflections from any voltage step
reaching the end of the wire, and it will
take a while for these echoes to die out.
In fact, as we'll see, energy will reflect
off of any impedance discontinuity, which
means we'll want to minimize the number of
such discontinuities.
We need to be careful to allow sufficient
time for signals to reach valid logic levels.
The shaded region shows a transition of the
wire A from 1 to 0 to 1.
The first inverter is trying to produce a
1-output from the initial input transition
to 0, but doesn't have sufficient time to
complete the transition on wire B before the
input changes again.
This leads to a runt pulse on wire C, the
output of the second inverter, and we see
that the sequence of bits on A has been corrupted
by the time the signal reaches C.
This problem was caused by the energy storage
in the capacitance of the wire between the
inverters, which will limit the speed at which
we can run the logic.
And here see we what happens when a large
voltage step triggers oscillations in a wire,
called ringing, due to the wire's inductance
and capacitance.
The graph shows it takes some time before
the ringing dampens to the point that we have
a reliable digital signal.
The ringing can be diminished by spreading
the voltage step over a longer time.
The key idea here is that by paying close
attention to the design of our wiring and
the drivers that put information onto the
wire, we can minimize the performance implications
of these energy-storage effects.
Okay, enough electrical engineering!
Suppose we have some information in our system.
If we preserve that information over time,
we call that storage.
If we send that information to another component,
we call that communication.
In the real world, we've seen that communication
takes time and we have to budget for that
time in our system timing.
Our engineering has to accommodate the fundamental
bounds on propagating speeds, distances between
components, and how fast we can change wire
voltages without triggering the effects we
saw on the previous slide.
The upshot: our timing models will have to
account for wire delays.
In Part 1 of this course, we had a simple
timing model that assigned a fixed propagation
delay, t_PD, to the time it took for the output
of a logic gate to reflect a change to the
gate's input.
We'll need to change our timing model to account
for delay of transmitting the output of a
logic gate to the next components.
The timing will be load dependent, so signals
that connect to the inputs of many other gates
will be slower than signals that connect to
only one other gate.
The Jade simulator takes the loading of a
gate's output signal into account when calculating
the effective propagation delay of the gate.
We can improve propagation delays by reducing
the number of loads on output signals or by
using specially-design gates called buffers
(the component shown in red) to drive signals
that have very large loads.
A common task when optimizing the performance
of a circuit is to track down heavily-loaded
and hence slow wires and re-engineering the
circuit to make them faster.
Today our concern is wires used to connect
components at the system level.
So next we'll turn our attention to possible
designs for system-level interconnect and
the issues that might arise.