PROFESSOR: This truth
table represents
a five-state finite
state machine, or FSM,
with a one-bit input, IN,
and a two-bit output, OUT.
This FSM is a Mealy machine.
That means that its
outputs are a function
of both the current state
and the current input.
When this FSM is initialized,
its starting state
is state B. We are given
a partially filled state
transition diagram shown here.
Our job is to fill in the
missing state and transition
labels.
In other words, S1
through S4 should
be replaced with the states A
through E. And T1 through T7
should be replaced with a
IN/OUT transition corresponding
to that arrow.
In order to do this, we begin
by looking at the truth table,
beginning with
the starting state
B. The truth table shows
us that when IN equals 0,
our next state is state C.
Since the 0 input transition out
of state B is already
labeled for us,
we know that state S2 equals
C. This also tells us that T2
corresponds to IN equals 1.
So S4 is equal to D.
And T2 is equal to 1/00.
From state D, we have
the one input transition
already labeled.
So T3 corresponds
to IN equals 0.
Looking at the truth
table, that means that S3
equals E and T3 equals 0/01.
The truth table then shows
us that from state E,
a 1 input takes you
back to state B.
So T4 equals 1/01, which in
turn means that T5 equals 0/10.
And state S1 equals A.
From state A, the
0 input transition
is already filled in.
So T1 equals 1/11.
From state C, a 1
input goes to state B.
So T6 equals 1/01, which in
turn means that T7 equals 0/10.
Now that we have a complete
state diagram for our FSM,
the next thing we want to figure
out is what sequence of outputs
is produced if we begin in state
B and receive inputs 1, 0, 0.
Since our state transition
diagram is now filled,
we see that from state B, a
1 input takes us to state D
and produces a 00 output.
From state D, a 0 input moves
us to state E and outputs 01.
Finally, from state E, a 0
input moves us to state A
and produces a 10 output.
OK.
Now let's try to find
a sequence of inputs
that is guaranteed to
leave the FSM in state E,
regardless of the state it
is in before the sequence is
processed.
To answer this question, we take
a look at our filled-in state
diagram and determine
what sequence of inputs
takes us from each
state X to state E.
We begin with state
A. From state A,
the shortest sequence of inputs
required to get to state E
is 1, 1, 0.
This takes you from A
to B to D to E. Next,
we examine state B. We see that
the sequence 1, 0 will take us
from B to D to E.
Since we are looking
for a single sequence that
will work from all states,
we want to see if 1,
1, 0 would also work.
Taking a closer look
at state D shows us
that the sequence
1, 1, 0 will also
get us from B to E because the
extra 1 just keeps you in state
D for one extra iteration.
And then the 0 takes you
to state E. Similarly,
if you begin at state
D, the sequence 1, 1, 0
leaves you at state
D for two iterations.
And then on the third, the
0 takes you to state E.
Beginning at state E
itself, the sequence 1, 1, 0
takes you to state
B, then D, then E.
So we have one
state left to check,
and that is state
C. From state C,
the sequence 1, 1, 0 takes us
to state B, then D, then E.
So once again, the
sequence 1, 1, 0 works.
This means that
regardless of what state
you start in, the sequence 1, 1,
0 will have you end at state E.
The last question we want to
answer about the finite state
machine is whether
or not there exists
an equivalent FSM that has only
four states instead of five.
In other words, are
there two states
that can be merged into one to
reduce the FSM to an equivalent
FSM with one fewer state?
Recall that in a
Mealy FSM, two states
are equivalent if they
have the same input/output
transitions as each other.
If it were a Moore FSM,
then the two states
would be equivalent if they
produced the same output
and have the same transitions.
Taking a closer look at
the states in this FSM,
we see that both states C and
E transition to state B on a 1
input and produce a 01 output.
On a 0 input, they both
transition to state A
and produce a 10 output.
So states C and E are
equivalent and can
be merged into a single state,
thus reducing the total number
of states in our FSM to four.