Let’s think a bit more
about the FSM abstraction.
If we see an FSM that
uses K state bits,
what can we say about the
number of states in its state
transition diagram?
Well, we know the FSM can
have at most 2^K states,
since that’s the number of
unique combinations of K bits.
Suppose we connect
two FSMs in series,
with the outputs of the first
FSM serving as the inputs
to the second.
This larger system is also an
FSM — how many states does it
have?
Well, if we don’t know
the details of either
of the component FSMs, the upper
bound on the number of states
for the larger system is M*N.
This is because it may be
possible for the first FSM
to be in any of its M states
while the second FSM is
any of its N states.
Note that the answer
doesn’t depend on X or Y,
the number of input signals
to each of the component FSMs.
Wider inputs just mean that
there are longer labels
on the transitions in the
state transition diagram,
but doesn’t tell us anything
about the number of internal
states.
Finally, here’s a question
that’s a bit trickier than it
seems.
I give you an FSM with two
inputs labeled 0 and 1,
and one output
implemented as a light.
Then I ask you to discover
its state transition diagram.
Can you do it?
Just to be a bit
more concrete, you
experiment for an hour
pushing the buttons
in a variety of sequences.
Each time you push the 0
button the light turns off
if it was on.
And when you push the 1
button the light turns on
if it was off, otherwise
nothing seems to happen.
What state transition
diagram could we
draw based on our experiments?
Consider the following two
state transition diagrams.
The top diagram
describes the behavior
we observed in our experiments:
pushing 0 turns the light off,
pushing 1 turns the light on.
The second diagram appears
to do the same thing
unless you happened to push
the 1 button 4 times in a row!
If we don’t have an upper
bound on the number of states
in the FSM, we can never be sure
that we’ve explored all of its
possible behaviors.
But if we do have an
upper bound, say, K,
on the number of states
and we reset the FSM
to its initial state, we
can discover its behavior.
This is because in a K-state
FSM every reachable state
can reached in less
than K transitions,
starting from the initial state.
.244 So if we try all the
possible K-step input sequences
one after the other starting
each trial at the initial
state, we’ll be guaranteed
to have visited every state
in the machine.
Our answer is also
complicated by the observation
that FSMs with different number
of states may be equivalent.
Here are two FSMs, one with
2 states, one with 5 states.
Are they different?
Well, not in any
practical sense.
Since the FSMs are
externally indistinguishable,
we can use them interchangeably.
We say that two FSMs
are equivalent if
and only if every input
sequence yields identical output
sequences from both FSMs.
So as engineers,
if we have an FSM
we would like to find the the
simplest (and hence the least
expensive) equivalent FSM.
We’ll talk about how to
find smaller equivalent FSMs
in the context of
our next example.