We can tweak the design of the DM cache a
little to take advantage of locality and save
some of the overhead of tag fields and valid
bits.
We can increase the size of the data field
in a cache from 1 word to 2 words, or 4 words,
etc.
The number of data words in each cache line
is called the "block size" and is always a
power of two.
Using a larger block size makes sense.
If there's a high probability of accessing
nearby words, why not fetch a larger block
of words on a cache miss, trading the increased
cost of the miss against the increased probability
of future hits.
Compare the 16-word DM cache shown here with
a block size of 4 with a different 16-word
DM cache with a block size of 1.
In this cache for every 128 bits of data there
are 27 bits of tags and valid bit, so ~17%
of the SRAM bits are overhead in the sense
that they're not being used to store data.
In the cache with block size 1, for every
32 bits of data there are 27 bits of tag and
valid bit, so ~46% of the SRAM bits are overhead.
So a larger block size means we'll be using
the SRAM more efficiently.
Since there are 16 bytes of data in each cache
line, there are now 4 offset bits.
The cache uses the high-order two bits of
the offset to select which of the 4 words
to return to the CPU on a cache hit.
There are 4 cache lines, so we'll need two
cache line index bits from the incoming address.
And, finally, the remaining 26 address bits
are used as the tag field.
Note that there's only a single valid bit
for each cache line, so either the entire
4-word block is present in the cache or it's
not.
Would it be worth the extra complication to
support caching partial blocks?
Probably not.
Locality tells us that we'll probably want
those other words in the near future, so having
them in the cache will likely improve the
hit ratio.
What's the tradeoff between block size and
performance?
We've argued that increasing the block size
from 1 was a good idea.
Is there a limit to how large blocks should
be?
Let's look at the costs and benefits of an
increased block size.
With a larger block size we have to fetch
more words on a cache miss and the miss penalty
grows linearly with increasing block size.
Note that since the access time for the first
word from DRAM is quite high, the increased
miss penalty isn't as painful as it might
be.
Increasing the block size past 1 reduces the
miss ratio since we're bringing words into
the cache that will then be cache hits on
subsequent accesses.
Assuming we don't increase the overall cache
capacity, increasing the block size means
we'll make a corresponding reduction in the
number of cache lines.
Reducing the number of lines impacts the number
of separate address blocks that can be accommodated
in the cache.
As we saw in the discussion on the size of
the working set of a running program, there
are a certain number of separate regions we
need to accommodate to achieve a high hit
ratio: program, stack, data, etc.
So we need to ensure there are a sufficient
number of blocks to hold the different addresses
in the working set.
The bottom line is that there is an optimum
block size that minimizes the miss ratio and
increasing the block size past that point
will be counterproductive.
Combining the information in these two graphs,
we can use the formula for AMAT to choose
the block size the gives us the best possible
AMAT.
In modern processors, a common block size
is 64 bytes (16 words).
DM caches do have an Achilles heel.
Consider running the 3-instruction LOOPA code
with the instructions located starting at
word address 1024 and the data starting at
word address 37 where the program is making
alternating accesses to instruction and data,
e.g., a loop of LD instructions.
Assuming a 1024-line DM cache with a block
size of 1, the steady state hit ratio will
be 100% once all six locations have been loaded
into the cache since each location is mapped
to a different cache line.
Now consider the execution of the same program,
but this time the data has been relocated
to start at word address 2048.
Now the instructions and data are competing
for use of the same cache lines.
For example, the first instruction (at address
1024) and the first data word (at address
2048) both map to cache line 0, so only one
them can be in the cache at a time.
So fetching the first instruction fills cache
line 0 with the contents of location 1024,
but then the first data access misses and
then refills cache line 0 with the contents
of location 2048.
The data address is said to "conflict" with
the instruction address.
The next time through the loop, the first
instruction will no longer be in the cache
and it's fetch will cause a cache miss, called
a "conflict miss".
So in the steady state, the cache will never
contain the word requested by the CPU.
This is very unfortunate!
We were hoping to design a memory system that
offered the simple abstraction of a flat,
uniform address space.
But in this example we see that simply changing
a few addresses results in the cache hit ratio
dropping from 100% to 0%.
The programmer will certainly notice her program
running 10 times slower!
So while we like the simplicity of DM caches,
we'll need to make some architectural changes
to avoid the performance problems caused by
conflict misses.