There are many
approaches to building
a general-purpose computer that
can be easily re-programmed
for new problems.
Almost all modern computers are
based on the “stored program”
computer architecture developed
by John von Neumann in 1945,
which is now commonly referred
to as the “von Neumann model”.
The von Neumann model
has three components.
There’s a central processing
unit (aka the CPU) that
contains a datapath and control
FSM as described previously.
The CPU is connected
to a read/write memory
that holds some number W
of words, each with N bits.
Nowadays, even small
memories have a billion words
and the width of each
location is at least 32 bits
(usually more).
This memory is often referred to
as “main memory” to distinguish
it from other memories
in the system.
You can think of it as an array:
when the CPU wishes to operate
on values in memory , it sends
the memory an array index,
which we call the address, and,
after a short delay (currently
10’s of nanoseconds) the memory
will return the N-bit value
stored at that address.
Writes to main memory
follow the same protocol
except, of course,
the data flows
in the opposite direction.
We’ll talk about memory
technologies a couple
of lectures from now.
And, finally, there are
input/output devices
that enable the computer
system to communicate
with the outside world or
to access data storage that,
unlike main memory, will
remember values even when
turned off.
The key idea is
to use main memory
to hold the instructions
for the CPU as well as data.
Both instructions and data are,
of course, just binary data
stored in main memory.
Interpreted as an
instruction, a value in memory
can be thought of as a set of
fields containing one or bits
encoding information
about the actions
to be performed by the CPU.
The opcode field indicates
the operation to be performed
(e.g., ADD, XOR, COMPARE).
Subsequent fields specify which
registers supply the source
operands and the
destination register
where the result is stored.
The CPU interprets the
information in the instruction
fields and performs the
requested operation.
It would then move on to the
next instruction in memory,
executing the stored
program step-by-step.
The goal of this
chapter is to discuss
the details of what operations
we want the CPU to perform,
how many registers we
should have, and so on.
Of course, some values in
memory are not instructions!
They might be binary
data representing
numeric values, strings
of characters, and so on.
The CPU will read these values
into its temporary registers
when it needs to operate on them
and write newly computed values
back into memory.
Mr. Blue is asking a
good question: how do we
know which words in
memory are instructions
and which are data?
After all, they’re
both binary values!
The answer is that we can’t tell
by looking at the values — it’s
how they are used by the CPU
that distinguishes instructions
from data.
If a value is loaded
into the datapath,
it’s being used as data.
If a value is loaded
by the control logic,
it’s being used an instruction.
So this is the digital
system we’ll build to perform
computations.
We’ll start with a datapath
that contains some number
of registers to
hold data values.
We’ll be able to select which
registers will supply operands
for the arithmetic and
logic unit that will perform
an operation.
The ALU produces a result
and other status signals.
The ALU result can
be written back
to one of the registers
for later use.
We’ll provide the datapath with
means to move data to and from
main memory.
There will be a
control unit that
provides the necessary control
signals to the datapath.
In the example
datapath shown here,
the control unit would
provide ASEL and BSEL
to select two register
values as operands
and DEST to select
the register where
the ALU result will be written.
If the datapath had, say,
32 internal registers,
ASEL, BSEL and DEST
would be 5-bit values,
each specifying a particular
register number in the range
0 to 31.
The control unit also
provides the FN function code
that controls the operation
performed by the ALU.
The ALU we designed in
Part 1 of the course
requires a 6-bit
function code to select
between a variety of arithmetic,
boolean and shift operations.
The control unit would load
values from main memory
to be interpreted
as instructions.
The control unit
contains a register,
called the “program counter”,
that keeps track of the address
in main memory of the next
instruction to be executed.
The control unit also
contains a (hopefully small)
amount of logic to translate
the instruction fields
into the necessary
control signals.
Note the control unit
receives status signals
from the datapath that will
enable programs to execute
different sequences
of instructions
if, for example, a particular
data value was zero.
The datapath serves as the
brawn of our digital system
and is responsible for storing
and manipulating data values.
The control unit serves as
the brain of our system,
interpreting the program
stored in main memory
and generating the necessary
sequence of control
signals for the datapath.
Instructions are the
fundamental unit of work.
They’re fetched by the control
unit and executed one after
another in the order
they are fetched.
Each instruction
specifies the operation
to be performed along
with the registers
to supply the source operands
and destination register where
the result will be stored.
In a von Neumann machine,
instruction execution
involves the steps shown here:
the instruction is
loaded from the memory
location whose address is
specified by the program
counter.
When the requested data
is returned by the memory,
the instruction
fields are converted
to the appropriate control
signals for the datapath,
selecting the source operands
from the specified registers,
directing the ALU to perform
the specified operation,
and storing the result in the
specified destination register.
The final step in
executing an instruction
is updating the
value of the program
counter to be the address
of the next instruction.
This execution loop is
performed again and again.
Modern machines can execute
up more than a billion
instructions per second!
The discussion so far
has been a bit abstract.
Now it’s time to roll up our
sleeves and figure out what
instructions we want
our system to support.
The specification of instruction
fields and their meaning
along with the details
of the datapath design
are collectively called the
instruction set architecture
(ISA) of the system.
The ISA is a detailed functional
specification of the operations
and storage
mechanisms and serves
as a contract
between the designers
of the digital hardware
and the programmers who
will write the programs.
Since the programs are stored
in main memory and can hence be
changed, we’ll
call them software,
to distinguish them from
the digital logic which,
once implemented,
doesn’t change.
It’s the combination of hardware
and software that determine
the behavior of our system.
The ISA is a new
layer of abstraction:
we can write programs
for the system
without knowing
the implementation
details of the hardware.
As hardware
technology improves we
can build faster systems without
having to change the software.
You can see here that over
a fifteen year timespan,
the hardware for executing
the Intel x86 instruction set
went from executing 300,000
instructions per second
to executing 5 billion
instructions per second.
Same software as before, we’ve
just taken advantage of smaller
and faster MOSFETs to build
more complex circuits and faster
execution engines.
But a word of
caution is in order!
It’s tempting to make choices
in the ISA that reflect
the constraints of current
technologies, e.g.,
the number of
internal registers,
the width of the operands,
or the maximum size of main
memory.
But it will be hard to change
the ISA when technology
improves since there’s a
powerful economic incentive
to ensure that old software
can run on new machines,
which means that a particular
ISA can live for decades
and span many generations
of technology.
If your ISA is successful,
you’ll have to live with any
bad choices you made
for a very long time.
Designing an ISA is hard!
What are the operations
that should be supported?
How many internal registers?
How much main memory?
Should we design the
instruction encoding
to minimize program size or to
keep the logic in the control
unit as simple as possible?
Looking into our
crystal ball, what
can we say about the computation
and storage capabilities
of future technologies?
We’ll answer these questions by
taking a quantitative approach.
First we’ll choose a set
of benchmark programs,
chosen as representative of
the many types of programs we
expect to run on our system.
So some of benchmark
programs will
perform scientific and
engineering computations,
some will manipulate
large data sets
or perform database
operations, some
will require specialized
computations for graphics
or communications, and so on.
Happily, after many
decades of computer use,
several standardized
benchmark suites
are available for us to use.
We’ll then implement the
benchmark programs using
our instruction set and simulate
their execution on our proposed
datapath.
We’ll evaluate the results to
measure how well the system
performs.
But what do we mean by “well”?
That’s where it
gets interesting:
“well” could refer to execution
speed, energy consumption,
circuit size, system cost, etc.
If you’re designing
a smart watch,
you’ll make different choices
than if you’re designing
a high-performance graphics
card or a data-center server.
Whatever metric you choose to
evaluate your proposed system,
there’s an important design
principle we can follow:
identify the common
operations and focus on them
as you optimize your design.
For example, in
general-purpose computing,
almost all programs
spend a lot of their time
on simple arithmetic
operations and accessing values
in main memory.
So those operations
should be made as fast
and energy efficient
as possible.
Now, let’s get to work designing
our own instruction set
and execution engine, a
system we’ll call the Beta.