And now we've reached the end of 6.004.
Looking back, there are two ways of thinking
about the material we've discussed, the skills
we've practiced, and the designs we've completed.
Starting at devices, we've worked our way
up the design hierarchy, each level serving
as building blocks for the next.
Along the way we thought about design tradeoffs,
choosing the alternatives that would make
our systems reliable, efficient and easy to
understand and hence easy to maintain.
In the other view of 6.004, we created and
then used a hierarchy of engineering abstractions
that are reasonably independent of the technologies
they encapsulate.
Even though technologies change at a rapid
pace, these abstractions embody principles
that are timeless.
For example, the symbolic logic described
by George Boole in 1847 is still used to reason
about the operation of digital circuits you
and I design today.
The power of engineering abstractions is that
they allow us to reason about the behavior
of a system based on the behavior of the components
without having to understand the implementation
details of each component.
The advantage of viewing components as "black
boxes" implementing some specified function
is that the implementation can change as long
as the same specification is satisfied.
In my lifetime, the size of a 2-input NAND
gate has shrunk by 10 orders of magnitude,
yet a 50-year-old logic design would still
work as intended if implemented in today's
technologies.
Imagine trying to build a circuit that added
two binary numbers if you had to reason about
the electrical properties of doped silicon
and conducting metals.
Using abstractions lets us limit the design
complexity at each level, shortening design
time and making it easier to verify that the
specifications have been met.
And once we've created a useful repertoire
of building blocks, we can use them again
and again to assemble many different systems.
Our goal in 6.004 is to demystify how computers
work, starting with MOSFETs and working our
way up to operating systems.
We hope you've understood the engineering
abstractions we've introduced and had a chance
to practice using them when completing the
design problems offered in the labs.
We also hope that you'll also understand their
limitations and have the confidence to create
new abstractions when tackling new engineering
tasks.
Good engineers use abstractions, but great
engineers create them.
principles used at each level of the design
hierarchy.
If a particular topic struck you as especially
interesting, we hope you'll seek out a more
advanced course that will let you dig deeper
into that engineering discipline.
Hundreds of thousands of engineers have worked
to create the digital systems that are the
engines of today's information society.
As you can imagine, there's no end of interesting
engineering to explore and master - so roll
up your sleeves and come join in the fun!
What will be the engineering challenges of
tomorrow?
Here are a few thoughts about how the future
of computing may be very different than the
present.
The systems we build today have a well-defined
notion of state:
the exact digital values stored in their memories,
produced by their logic components, and traveling
along their interconnect.
But computation based on the principles of
quantum mechanics may allow us to solve what
are now intractable problems using states
described not as collections of 1's and 0's,
but as interrelated probabilities that describe
the superposition of many states.
We've built our systems using voltages to
encode information and voltage-controlled
switches to perform computation, using silicon-based
electrical devices.
But the chemistry of life has been carrying
out detailed manufacturing operations for
millennia using information encoded as sequences
of amino acids.
Some of the information encoded in our DNA
has been around for millions of years, a truly
long-lived information system!
Today biologists are starting to build computational
components from biological materials.
Maybe in 50 years instead of plugging in your
laptop, you'll have to feed it :)
Instead of using truth tables and logic functions,
some computations are best performed neural
networks that operate by forming appropriately
weighted combinations of analog inputs,
where the weights are learned by the system
as it is trained using example inputs that
should produce known outputs.
Artificial neural nets are thought to model
the operation of the synapses and neurons
in our brains.
As we learn more about how the brain operates,
we may get many new insights into how to implement
systems that are good at recognition and reasoning.
Again using living organisms as useful models,
programming may be replaced by learning, where
stimulus and feedback are used to evolve system
behavior.
In other words, systems will use adaptation
mechanisms to evolve the desired functionality
rather than have it explicitly programmed.
This all seems the stuff of science fiction,
but I suspect our parents feel the same way
about having conversations with Siri about
tomorrow's weather.
Thanks for joining us here in 6.004.
We've enjoyed presenting the material and
challenging you with design tasks to exercise
your new skills and understanding.
There are interesting times ahead in the world
of digital systems and we can certainly use
your help in inventing the future!
We'd welcome any feedback you have about the
course so please feel free leave comments
in the forum.
Good bye for now... and good luck in your
future studies.