Given the CMOS circuit with pull-down shown
here, we can generate the corresponding function
that this CMOS circuit represents which is
NOT(F) = (A+B)C + D.
So F = ((A+B)C + D) the whole thing negated.
This function can be expressed as a truth
table which describes the output that the
function produces for any set of inputs.
All of the possible input combinations are
enumerated, and then the value of F is specified
for each of those combinations.
For this function, F, for example, if A=0
B=0 C=0 and D=0, then (A+B)C = 0 that ORed
with D = 0, and finally the entire thing is
negated, so F = 1.
For A=0 B=0 C=0 and D=1, (A+B)C = 0 + D=1
gives us 1 and the whole thing negated is
F=0.
In the same way, we can complete the rest
of the truth table, and we get.
1 0 1 0 0 0 1 0 0 0 1 0 0 0
Given a truth table, one can be asked if the
function F that this truth table defines,
can be implemented using a single CMOS gate.
To figure that out, we first convert the truth
table to a logical equation for F.
Given this truth table, the function F can
be expressed as a sum of products by listing
all terms that make F=1 and ORing them together.
For this truth table F = NOT(A) NOT(B) NOT(C)
+ NOT(A) B NOT(C) + A NOT(B) NOT(C).
In order to determine if this function can
be implemented as a single CMOS circuit, the
function F needs to be manipulated through
logic simplifications in order to see if NOT(F)
can be written as a function of just the inputs
A, B, and C (without any negations of those
inputs) together with ANDs and ORs.
We start with our function for F.
Factoring out NOT(C), that equals NOT(C) (NOT(A)
NOT(B) + NOT(A) B + A NOT(B)).
Rearranging the terms and repeating the first
one continues to produce the same function.
So F = NOT(C) (NOT(A) NOT(B) + A NOT(B) +
NOT(A) B + NOT(A) NOT(B)).
Noting that A X + NOT(A) X = X, this reduces
to: F = NOT(C) (NOT(B) + NOT(A)).
We are almost there, we now want to convert
F to NOT(F) by negating the entire thing,
so NOT(F) = NOT (NOT(C) (NOT(B) + NOT(A)).
To simplify this we make use of De Morgan's
Law which states that NOT(AB) = NOT(A) + NOT(B).
And that NOT(A+B) = NOT(A) AND NOT(B).
So NOT(F) = C + NOT(NOT(B) + NOT(A)), and
finally NOT(F) = C + (B A).
Now that we have found that NOT(F) = C + BA,
we know that F can be implemented as a single
CMOS gate because we were able to express
NOT(F) as a function that consists purely
of our non-negated inputs, A, B, and C, together
with ANDs and ORs.
The pull-down for this circuit would basically
implement NOT(F) so it would be series(A,B)
in parallel with C.
The pull-up would be the inverse of that which
is parallel(A,B) in series with C.