Let's see if we can improve the throughput
of the original combinational multiplier design.
We'll use our patented pipelining process
to divide the processing into stages with
the expectation of achieving a smaller clock
period and higher throughput.
The number to beat is approximately 1 output
every 2N, where N is the number of bits in
each of the operands.
Our first step is to draw a contour across
all the outputs.
This creates a 1-pipeline, which gets us started
but doesn't improve the throughput.
Let's add another contour, dividing the computations
about in half.
If we're on the right track, we hope to see
some improvement in the throughput.
And indeed we do: the throughput has doubled.
Yet both the before and after throughputs
are order 1/N.
Is there any hope of a dramatically better
throughput?
The necessary insight is that as long as an
entire row is inside a single pipeline stage,
the latency of the stage will be order N since
we have to leave time for the N-bit ripple-carry
add to complete.
There are several ways to tackle this problem.
The technique illustrated here will be useful
in our next task.
In this schematic we've redrawn the carry
chains.
Carry-outs are still connected to a module
one column to the left, but, in this case,
a module that's down a row.
So all the additions that need to happen in
a specific column still happen in that column,
we've just reorganized which row does the
adding.
Let's pipeline this revised diagram, creating
stages with approximately two module's worth
of propagation delay.
The horizontal contours now break the long
carry chains and the latency of each stage
is now constant, independent of N.
Note that we had to add order N extra rows
to take of the propagating the carries all
the way to the end - the extra circuitry is
shown in the grey box.
To achieve a latency that's independent of
N in each stage, we'll need order N contours.
This means the latency is constant, which
in order-of notation we write as "order 1".
But this means the clock period is now independent
of N, as is the throughput - they are both
order 1.
With order N contours, there are order N pipeline
stages, so the system latency is order N.
The hardware cost is still order N^2.
So the pipelined carry-save multiplier has
dramatically better throughput than the original
circuit, another design tradeoff we can remember
for future use.
We'll use the carry-save technique in our
next optimization, which is to implement the
multiplier using only order N hardware.
This sequential multiplier design computes
a single partial product in each step and
adds it to the accumulating sum.
It will take order N steps to perform the
complete multiplication.
In each step, the next bit of the multiplier,
found in the low-order bit of the B register,
is ANDed with the multiplicand to form the
next partial product.
This is sent to the N-bit carry-save adder
to be added to the accumulating sum in the
P register.
The value in the P register and the output
of the adder are in "carry-save format".
This means there are 32 data bits, but, in
addition, 31 saved carries, to be added to
the appropriate column in the next cycle.
The output of the carry-save adder is saved
in the P register, then in preparation for
the next step both P and B are shifted right
by 1 bit.
So each cycle one bit of the accumulated sum
is retired to the B register since it can
no longer be affected by the remaining partial
products.
Think of it this way: instead of shifting
the partial products left to account for the
weight of the current multiplier bit, we're
shifting the accumulated sum right!
The clock period needed for the sequential
logic is quite small, and, more importantly
is independent of N.
Since there's no carry propagation, the latency
of the carry-save adder is very small, i.e.,
only enough time for the operation of a single
full adder module.
After order N steps, we've generated the necessary
partial products, but will need to continue
for another order N steps to finish propagating
the carries through the carry-save adder.
But even at 2N steps, the overall latency
of the multiplier is still order N.
And at the end of the 2N steps, we produce
the answer in the P and B registers combined,
so the throughput is order 1/N.
The big change is in the hardware cost at
order N, a dramatic improvement over the order
N^2 hardware cost of the original combinational
multiplier.
This completes our little foray into multiplier
designs.
We've seen that with a little cleverness we
can create designs with order 1 throughput,
or designs with only order N hardware.
The technique of carry-save addition is useful
in many situations and its use can improve
throughput at constant hardware cost, or save
hardware at a constant throughput.