CMOS gates consist of an output node connected
to a pull-up circuit that contains only PFETs
and a pull-down circuit that contains only
NFETs.
In our example, our gate computes F(A,B,C,D).
It is observed that F(1,0,1,1) = 1.
With that information, what can you say about
the value of F(1,0,0,0)?
All CMOS gates are inverting which means that
if all your inputs are 0, then only the PFETs
in the pull-up are on, and so the output = 1.
If all your inputs are 1, then only the NFETs
in the pull-down circuitry are on, and the
output = 0.
If we are told that F(1,0,1,1) = 1 and we
want to find out what F(1,0,0,0) is, we notice
that the difference between the first set
of inputs and the second is that the third
and fourth inputs have been changed from 1
to 0 while the others remain unchanged.
Changing an input from 1 to 0 will turn more
PFETs on, and more NFETs off, which means
that there are more possibilities of the pull-up
circuitry to pull the output up to high, and
fewer chances of the pull-down circuitry pulling
the output down to 0.
Since, we were already producing a high output
with even fewer PFETs turned on, we are guaranteed
that by turning more PFETs on and turning
some NFETs off, the only thing we can do is
maintain our high output.
So F(1,0,0,0) = 1.