Let's review what happens when the CPU accesses
a non-resident virtual page, i.e., a page
with its resident bit set to 0.
In the example shown here, the CPU is trying
to access virtual page 5.
In this case, the MMU signals a page fault
exception, causing the CPU to suspend execution
of the program and switch to the page fault
handler, which is code that deals with the
page fault.
The handler starts by either finding an unused
physical page or, if necessary, creating an
unused page by selecting an in-use page and
making it available.
In our example, the handler has chosen virtual
page 1 for reuse.
If the selected page is dirty, i.e., its D
bit is 1 indicating that its contents have
changed since being read from secondary storage,
write it back to secondary storage.
Finally, mark the selected virtual page as
no longer resident.
In the "after" figure, we see that the R bit
for virtual page 1 has been set to 0.
Now physical page 4 is available for re-use.
Are there any restrictions on which page we
can select?
Obviously, we can't select the page that holds
the code for the page fault handler.
Pages immune from selection are called "wired"
pages.
And it would very inefficient to choose the
page that holds the code that made the initial
memory access, since we expect to start executing
that code as soon as we finish handling the
page fault.
The optimal strategy would be to choose the
page whose next use will occur farthest in
the future.
But, of course, this involves knowledge of
future execution paths and so isn't a realizable
strategy.
Wikipedia provides a nice description of the
many strategies for choosing a replacement
page, with their various tradeoffs between
ease of implementation and impact on the rate
of page faults -
see the URL given at the bottom of the slide.
The aging algorithm they describe is frequently
used since it offers near optimal performance
at a moderate implementation cost.
Next, the desired virtual page is read from
secondary storage into the selected physical
page.
In our example, virtual page 5 is now loaded
into physical page 4.
Then the R bit and PPN fields in the page
table entry for virtual page 5 are updated
to indicate that the contents of that virtual
page now reside in physical page 4.
Finally the handler is finished and execution
of the original program is resumed, re-executing
the instruction that caused the page fault.
Since the page map has been updated, this
time the access succeeds and execution continues.
To double-check our understanding of page
faults, let's run through an example.
Here's the same setup as in our previous example,
but this time consider a store instruction
that's making an access to virtual address
0x600, which is located on virtual page 6.
Checking the page table entry for VPN 6, we
see that its R bit 0 indicating that it is
NOT resident in main memory, which causes
a page fault exception.
The page fault handler selects VPN 0xE for
replacement since we've been told in the setup
that it's the least-recently-used page.
The page table entry for VPN 0xE has D=1 so
the handler writes the contents of VPN 0xE,
which is found in PPN 0x5, to secondary storage.
Then it updates the page table to indicate
that VPN 0xE is no longer resident.
Next, the contents of VPN 0x6 are read from
secondary storage into the now available PPN
0x5.
Now the handler updates the page table entry
for VPN 0x6 to indicate that it's resident
in PPN 0x5.
The page fault handler has completed its work,
so program execution resumes and the ST instruction
is re-executed.
This time the MMU is able to translate virtual
address 0x600 to physical address 0x500.
And since the ST instruction modifies the
contents of VPN 0x6, its D bit is set to 1.
Whew!
We're done :)
We can think of the work of the MMU as being
divided into two tasks, which as computer
scientists, we would think of as two procedures.
In this formulation the information in the
page map is held in several arrays: the R
array holds the resident bits,
the D array holds the dirty bits, the PPN
array holds the physical page numbers,
and the DiskAdr array holds the location in
secondary storage for each virtual page.
The VtoP procedure is invoked on each memory
access to translate the virtual address into
a physical address.
If the requested virtual page is not resident,
the PageFault procedure is invoked to make
the page resident.
Once the requested page is resident, the VPN
is used as an index to lookup the corresponding
PPN, which is then concatenated with the page
offset to form the physical address.
The PageFault routine starts by selecting
a virtual page to be replaced, writing out
its contents if it's dirty.
The selected page is then marked as not resident.
Finally the desired virtual page is read from
secondary storage and the page map information
updated to reflect that it's now resident
in the newly filled physical page.
We'll use hardware to implement the VtoP functionality
since it's needed for every memory access.
The call to the PageFault procedure is accomplished
via a page fault exception, which directs
the CPU to execute the appropriate handler
software that contains the PageFault procedure.
This is a good strategy to pursue in all our
implementation choices: use hardware for the
operations that need to be fast, but use exceptions
to handle the (hopefully infrequent) exceptional
cases in software.
Since the software is executed by the CPU,
which is itself a piece of hardware, what
we're really doing is making the tradeoff
between using special-purpose hardware (e.g.,
the MMU) or using general-purpose hardware
(e.g., the CPU).
In general, one should be skeptical of proposals
to use special-purpose hardware, reserving
that choice for operations that truly are
commonplace and whose performance is critical
to the overall performance of the system.