Let's wrap up our discussion of system-level
interconnect by considering how best to connect
N components that need to send messages to
one another, e.g., CPUs on a multicore chip.
Today such chips have a handful of cores,
but soon they may have 100s or 1000s of cores.
We'll build our communications network using
point-to-point links.
In our analysis, each point-to-point link
is counted at a cost of 1 hardware unit.
Sending a message across a link requires one
time unit.
And we'll assume that different links can
operate in parallel, so more links will mean
more message traffic.
We'll do an asymptotic analysis of the throughput
(total messages per unit time), latency (worst-case
time to deliver a single message), and hardware
cost.
In other words, we'll make a rough estimate
how these quantities change as N grows.
Note that in general the throughput and hardware
cost are proportional to the number of point-to-point
links.
Our baseline is the backplane bus discussed
earlier, where all the components share a
single communication channel.
With only a single channel, bus throughput
is 1 message per unit time and a message can
travel between any two components in one time
unit.
Since each component has to have an interface
to the shared channel, the total hardware
cost is O(n).
In a ring network each component sends its
messages to a single neighbor and the links
are arranged so that its possible to reach
all components.
There are N links in total, so the throughput
and cost are both O(n).
The worst case latency is also O(n) since
a message might have to travel across N-1
links to reach the neighbor that's immediately
upstream.
Ring topologies are useful when message latency
isn't important or when most messages are
to the component that's immediately downstream,
i.e., the components form a processing pipeline.
The most general network topology is when
every component has a direct link to every
other component.
There are O(N**2) links so the throughput
and cost are both O(N**2).
And the latency is 1 time unit since each
destination is directly accessible.
Although expensive, complete graphs offer
very high throughput with very low latencies.
A variant of the complete graph is the crossbar
switch where a particular row and column can
be connected to form a link between particular
A and B components
with the restriction that each row and each
column can only carry 1 message during each
time unit.
Assume that the first row and first column
connect to the same component, and so on,
i.e., that the example crossbar switch is
being used to connect 4 components.
Then there are O(n) messages delivered each
time unit, with a latency of 1.
There are N**2 switches in the crossbar, so
the cost is O(N**2) even though there are
only O(n) links.
In mesh networks, components are connected
to some fixed number of neighboring components,
in either 2 or 3 dimensions.
Hence the total number of links is proportional
to the number of components, so both throughput
and cost are O(n).
The worst-case latencies for mesh networks
are proportional to length of the sides, so
the latency is O(sqrt n) for 2D meshes and
O(cube root n) for 3D meshes.
The orderly layout, constant per-node hardware
costs, and modest worst-case latency make
2D 4-neighbor meshes a popular choice for
the current generation of experimental multi-core
processors.
Hypercube and tree networks offer logarithmic
latencies, which for large N may be faster
than mesh networks.
The original CM-1 Connection Machine designed
in the 80's used a hypercube network to connect
up to 65,536 very simple processors, each
connected to 16 neighbors.
Later generations incorporated smaller numbers
of more sophisticated processors, still connected
by a hypercube network.
In the early 90's the last generation of Connection
Machines used a tree network, with the clever
innovation that the links towards the root
of the tree had a higher message capacity.
Here's a summary of the theoretical latencies
we calculated for the various topologies.
As a reality check, it's important to realize
that the lower bound on the worst-case distance
between components in our 3-dimensional world
is O(cube root of N).
In the case of a 2D layout, the worst-case
distance is O(sqrt N).
Since we know that the time to transmit a
message is proportional to the distance traveled,
we should modify our latency calculations
to reflect this physical constraint.
Note that the bus and crossbar involve N connections
to a single link, so here the lower-bound
on the latency needs to reflect the capacitive
load added by each connection.
The winner?
Mesh networks avoid the need for longer wires
as the number of connected components grows
and appear to be an attractive alternative
for high-capacity communication networks connecting
1000's of processors.
Summarizing our discussion:
point-to-point links are in common use today
for system-level interconnect, and as a result
our systems are faster, more reliable, more
energy-efficient and smaller than ever before.
Multi-signal parallel buses are still used
for very-high-bandwidth connections to memories,
with a lot of very careful engineering to
avoid the electrical problems observed in
earlier bus implementations.
Wireless connections are in common use to
connect mobile devices to nearby components
and there has been interesting work on how
to allow mobile devices to discover what peripherals
are nearby and enable them to connect automatically.
The upcoming generation of multi-core chips
will have 10's to 100's of processing cores.
There is a lot ongoing research to determine
which communication topology would offer the
best combination of high communication bandwidth
and low latency.
The next ten years will be an interesting
time for on-chip network engineers!