PROFESSOR: Instead of building
all of our logic functions
directly in CMOS,
it is easier for us
to create a higher
level of abstraction
known as Boolean gates,
which represent CMOS gates.
Each gate is assigned a
symbol, which can then
be used in schematic diagrams
that combine multiple logic
gates together.
In order to be
able to understand
what function any combination
of logic gates will produce,
we will begin by reviewing
the basic gates together
with the truth tables
that define their logic.
We begin with an inverter.
An inverter is a gate
that has a single input
and a single output.
The output is simply the
inverse of the input.
When A equals 0, Y equals 1.
And when A equals 1, Y equals 0.
Next, we examine
AND and OR gates.
The AND function expects all
of its inputs to be true,
or 1, in order to produce
a 1 as its output.
So its truth table is for A,
B equals 0, 0, Y equals 0.
For A, B equals
0, 1, Y equals 0.
1, 0, y equals 0.
And for A, B equal
1, 1, Y equals 1.
The OR function just
expects at least one
of its inputs to be true
in order to produce a 1
as its output.
So for A, B equals
0, 0, Y equals 0.
But for the other three
combinations, Y equals 1.
NAND and NOR gates
simply produce
the inverse of AND and OR.
The reason that we like to
work with NAND and NOR gates is
because they are
inverting gates,
and they can be implemented
as a single CMOS gate,
whereas the AND and
OR gates cannot.
Finally, the last basic
gate is an exclusive or.
The exclusive or
produces a 1 output
if exactly one of its two
inputs is a 1 and 0 otherwise.
So for A, B equals
0, 0, Y equals 0.
For A, B equals
0, 1, Y equals 1.
For A, B equal to
1, 0, Y equals 1.
And for A, B equals
to 1, 1, y equals 0.
The output of one Boolean
gate can be used as an input
to another Boolean gate.
So multiple gates can
be used to generate
more complex functions.
For example, here
we have a circuit
that consists of two
inputs and six gates, which
are an inverter, an AND
gate, and OR gate, two NOR
gates, and 1 NAND gate.
In order to figure out what
this combination of gates
produces as its output,
we can work incrementally
through the circuit.
We begin by enumerating all our
choices of inputs for A and B.
We know that the
output of the inverter
is the complement of B. The AND
and OR gates use the A and B
inputs directly.
So since we just reviewed
what AND and OR gates produce,
we can fill in these
columns, as well.
Next, we want to see what
our first NOR gate produces.
Its inputs are A and
the complement of B.
We walk through each of
the input combinations
and determine the corresponding
output for that gate.
For input 0, 1, the output is 0.
For 0, 0, the output is 1.
For inputs 1, 1,
the output is 0.
And for input 1,
0, the output is 0.
In the same manner, we
evaluate the outputs
for our second NOR gate.
Its inputs are the outputs of
the first NOR gate and the AND
gate.
Again, we simply walk through
each combination of inputs
and specify the outputs
produced by the second NOR gate.
When both inputs are
0, the output is 1.
When one input is 0
and the other is a 1,
the output is a 0.
Finally, we take those
outputs, together
with the outputs of the
OR gate, and generate
the final output of the circuit
at the output of the NAND gate.
Here, when both inputs
are 1, we get a 0 output.
Otherwise, the output is a 1.
This NAND column
of our truth table
is the resulting output H.
Now that we have
evaluated what our output
H is equal to for each
combination of A and B,
we can represent the circuit
as a single truth table
whose inputs are A
and B and whose output
is H. At this point, we
can express the function
H as a combination of all the
cases that make H equal to 1.
This occurs if A and
B are both equal to 0,
or if A equals 0 and B
equals 1, or if A and B are
both equal to 1.
This can be expressed as
a Boolean logic expression
as follows.
H equals not A
not B, or not A B,
or A B. This notation is called
the sum of products notation.
Any sum of products can be
converted into a simple gate
representation of the function
using only inverters, AND,
and OR gates by having one large
OR gate that receives as input
one AND gate per product term.
Inverters are used as
needed to complement
the inputs to the AND gates.
One thing that's
interesting to note
about this combination
of gates is
that it can easily be
converted into a circuit that
consists purely of NAND gates.
The way to do this is
to realize that if you
take the output of a
gate and invert it twice,
you've produced the
original output.
This means that we can add
two inverters between each AND
output and OR input.
We can draw these
inverters as bubbles,
which represent
inversion, where we place
one bubble on the
output of the AND gate
and the other bubble at
the input to the OR gate.
We know that an AND gate
followed by an inversion
is simply a NAND gate.
We also know that an inverter
is equivalent to a NAND gate
with both of its
inputs tied together.
In addition, using
De Morgan's law,
we know that not A or not B is
equivalent to not of A and B.
This means that the bubbles
followed by the OR gate
can also be replaced
with a NAND gate,
thus arriving at our
equivalent circuit
representation consisting
purely of NAND gates.
The advantage of using NAND
gates to implement the circuit
is that NAND gates
are inverting logic,
where each gate can be
implemented as a single CMOS
gate.
All functions can be expressed
as a combination of NAND gates.
So a NAND gate is
considered a universal gate.
NOR gates are also
universal and can be
used to express any function.
Furthermore, any
circuit that can
be used to implement
any other function
is also considered universal.
To determine if a
gate G is universal,
one needs to check if one can
convert G into either a NAND
or NOR gate by simply using
one or more copies of G
together with low and
high constant inputs.