If the symbols we are trying to encode occur
with equal probability (or if we have no a
priori reason to believe otherwise), then
we'll use a fixed-length encoding, where all
leaves in the encoding's binary tree are the
same distance from the root.
Fixed-length encodings have the advantage
of supporting random access, where we can
figure out the Nth symbol of the message by
simply skipping over the required number of
bits.
For example, in a message encoded using the
fixed-length code shown here, if we wanted
to determine the third symbol in the encoded
message, we would skip the 4 bits used to
encode the first two symbols and start decoding
with the 5th bit of message.
Mr. Blue is telling us about the entropy for
random variables that have N equally-probable
outcomes.
In this case, each element of the sum in the
entropy formula is simply (1/N)*log2(N), and,
since there are N elements in the sequence,
the resulting entropy is just log2(N).
Let's look at some simple examples.
In binary-coded decimal, each digit of a decimal
number is encoded separately.
Since there are 10 different decimal digits,
we'll need to use a 4-bit code to represent
the 10 possible choices.
The associated entropy is log2(10), which
is 3.322 bits.
We can see that our chosen encoding is inefficient
in the sense that we'd use more than the minimum
number of bits necessary to encode, say, a
number with 1000 decimal digits: our encoding
would use 4000 bits, although the entropy
suggests we *might* be able to find a shorter
encoding, say, 3400 bits, for messages of
length 1000.
Another common encoding is ASCII, the code
used to represent English text in computing
and communication.
ASCII has 94 printing characters, so the associated
entropy is log2(94) or 6.555 bits, so we would
use 7 bits in our fixed-length encoding for
each character.
One of the most important encodings is the
one we use to represent numbers.
Let's start by thinking about a representation
for unsigned integers, numbers starting at
0 and counting up from there.
Drawing on our experience with representing
decimal numbers, i.e., representing numbers
in "base 10" using the 10 decimal digits,
our binary representation of numbers will
use a "base 2" representation using the two
binary digits.
The formula for converting an N-bit binary
representation of a numeric value into the
corresponding integer is shown below – just
multiply each binary digit by its corresponding
weight in the base-2 representation.
For example, here's a 12-bit binary number,
with the weight of each binary digit shown
above.
We can compute its value as 0*2^11 plus 1*2^10
plus 1*2^9, and so on.
Keeping only the non-zero terms and expanding
the powers-of-two gives us the sum 1024 +
512 + 256 + 128 + 64 + 16 which, expressed
in base-10, sums to the number 2000.
With this N-bit representation, the smallest
number that can be represented is 0 (when
all the binary digits are 0) and the largest
number is 2^N – 1 (when all the binary digits
are 1).
Many digital systems are designed to support
operations on binary-encoded numbers of some
fixed size, e.g., choosing a 32-bit or a 64-bit
representation, which means that they would
need multiple operations when dealing with
numbers too large to be represented as a single
32-bit or 64-bit binary string.
Long strings of binary digits are tedious
and error-prone to transcribe, so let's find
a more convenient notation, ideally one where
it will be easy to recover the original bit
string without too many calculations.
A good choice is to use a representation based
on a radix that's some higher power of 2,
so each digit in our representation corresponds
to some short contiguous string of binary
bits.
A popular choice these days is a radix-16
representation, called hexadecimal or "hex"
for short, where each group of 4 binary digits
is represented using a single hex digit.
Since there are 16 possible combinations of
4 binary bits, we'll need 16 hexadecimal "digits":
we'll borrow the ten digits "0" through "9"
from the decimal representation, and then
simply use the first six letters of the alphabet,
"A" through "F", for the remaining digits.
The translation between 4-bit binary and hexadecimal
is shown in the table to the left below.
To convert a binary number to "hex", group
the binary digits into sets of 4, starting
with the least-significant bit (that's the
bit with weight 2^0).
Then use the table to convert each 4-bit pattern
into the corresponding hex digit: "0000" is
the hex digit "0", "1101" is the hex digit
"D", and "0111" is the hex digit "7".
The resulting hex representation is "7D0".
To prevent any confusion, we'll use a special
prefix "0x" to indicate when a number is being
shown in hex, so we'd write "0x7D0" as the
hex representation for the binary number "0111
1101 0000".
This notation convention is used by many programming
languages for entering binary bit strings.