The problem we need to solve is where to store
the values needed by procedure: its arguments,
its return address, its return value.
The procedure may also need storage for its
local variables and space to save the values
of the caller's registers before they get
overwritten by the procedure.
We'd like to avoid any limitations on the
number of arguments, the number of local variables,
etc.
So we'll need a block of storage for each
active procedure call, what we'll call the
"activation record".
As we saw in the factorial example, we can't
statically allocate a single block of storage
for a particular procedure since recursive
calls mean we'll have many active calls to
that procedure at points during the execution.
What we need is a way to dynamically allocate
storage for an activation record when the
procedure is called, which can then be reclaimed
when the procedure returns.
Let's see how activation records come and
go as execution proceeds.
The first activation record is for the call
fact(3).
It's created at the beginning of the procedure
and holds, among other things, the value of
the argument n and the return address where
execution should resume after the fact(3)
computation is complete.
During the execution of fact(3), we need to
make a recursive call to compute fact(2).
So that procedure call also gets an activation
record with the appropriate values for the
argument and return address.
Note that the original activation record is
kept since it contains information needed
to complete the computation of fact(3) after
the call to fact(2) returns.
So now we have two active procedure calls
and hence two activation records.
fact(2) requires computing fact(1), which,
in turn, requires computing fact(0).
At this point there are four active procedure
calls and hence four activation records.
The recursion terminates with fact(0), which
returns the value 1 to its caller.
At this point we've finished execution of
fact(0) and so its activation record is no
longer needed and can be discarded.
fact(1) now finishes its computation returning
1 to its caller.
We no longer need its activation record.
Then fact(2) completes, returning 2 to its
caller and its activation record can be discarded.
And so on…
Note that the activation record of a nested
procedure call is always discarded before
the activation record of the caller.
That makes sense: the execution of the caller
can't complete until the nested procedure
call returns.
What we need is a storage scheme that efficiently
supports the allocation and deallocation of
activation records as shown here.
Early compiler writers recognized that activation
records are allocated and deallocated in last-in
first-out (LIFO) order.
So they invented the "stack", a data structure
that implements a PUSH operation to add a
record to the top of the stack and a POP operation
to remove the top element.
New activation records are PUSHed onto the
stack during procedure calls and the POPed
from the stack when the procedure call returns.
Note that stack operations affect the top
(i.e., most recent) record on the stack.
C procedures only need to access the top activation
record on the stack.
Other programming languages, e.g. Java, support
accesses to other active activation records.
The stack supports both modes of operation.
One final technical note: some programming
languages support closures (e.g., Javascript)
or continuations (e.g., Python's yield statement),
where the activation records need to be preserved
even after the procedure returns.
In these cases, the simple LIFO behavior of
the stack is no longer sufficient and we'll
need another scheme for allocating and deallocating
activation records.
But that's a topic for another course!
Here's how we'll implement the stack on the
Beta:
We'll dedicate one of the Beta registers,
R29, to be the "stack pointer" that will be
used to manage stack operations.
When we PUSH a word onto the stack, we'll
increment the stack pointer.
So the stack grows to successively higher
addresses as words are PUSHed onto the stack.
We'll adopt the convention that SP points
to (i.e., its value is the address of) the
first unused stack location, the location
that will be filled by next PUSH.
So locations with addresses lower than the
value in SP correspond to words that have
been previously allocated.
Words can be PUSHed to or POPed from the stack
at any point in execution, but we'll impose
the rule that code sequences that PUSH words
onto the stack must POP those words at the
end of execution.
So when a code sequence finishes execution,
SP will have the same value as it had before
the sequence started.
This is called the "stack discipline" and
ensures that intervening uses of the stack
don't affect later stack references.
We'll allocate a large region of memory to
hold the stack located so that the stack can
grow without overwriting other program storage.
Most systems require that you specify a maximum
stack size when running a program and will
signal an execution error if the program attempts
to PUSH too many items onto the stack.
For our Beta stack implementation, we'll use
existing instructions to implement stack operations,
so for us the stack is strictly a set of software
conventions.
Other ISAs provide instructions specifically
for stack operations.
There are many other sensible stack conventions,
so you'll need to read up on the conventions
adopted by the particular ISA or programming
language you'll be using.
We've added some convenience macros to UASM
to support stacks.
The PUSH macro expands into two instructions.
The ADDC increments the stack pointer, allocating
a new word at the top of stack, and then initializes
the new top-of-stack from a specified register
value with a ST instruction.
The POP macro LDs the value at the top of
the stack into the specified register, then
uses a SUBC instruction to decrement the stack
pointer, deallocating that word from the stack.
Note that the order of the instructions in
the PUSH and POP macro is very important.
As we'll see in the next lecture, interrupts
can cause the Beta hardware to stop executing
the current program between any two instructions,
so we have to be careful about the order of
operations.
So for PUSH, we first allocate the word on
the stack, then initialize it.
If we did it the other way around and execution
was interrupted between the initialization
and allocation, code run during the interrupt
which uses the stack might unintentionally
overwrite the initialized value.
But, assuming all code follows stack discipline,
allocation followed by initialization is always
safe.
The same reasoning applies to the order of
the POP instructions.
We first access the top-of-stack one last
time to retrieve its value, then we deallocate
that location.
We can use the ALLOCATE macro to reserve a
number of stack locations for later use.
Sort of like PUSH but without the initialization.
DEALLOCATE performs the opposite operation,
removing N words from the stack.
In general, if we see a PUSH or ALLOCATE in
an assembly language program, we should be
able to find the corresponding POP or DEALLOCATE,
which would indicate that stack discipline
is maintained.
We'll use stacks to save values we'll need
later.
For example, if we need to use some registers
for a computation but don't know if the register's
current values are needed later in the program,
we can PUSH their current values onto the
stack and then are free to use the registers
in our code.
After we're done, we can use POP to restore
the saved values.
Note that we POP data off the stack in the
opposite order that the data was PUSHed, i.e.,
we need to follow the last-in first-out discipline
imposed by the stack operations.
Now that we have the stack data structure,
we'll use it to solve our problems with allocating
and deallocating activation records during
procedure calls.