Boolean logic can be used to simplify logic
equations into their simplest form.
This simplest form is known as the function's
minimal sum of products representation.
Having a simplified equation allows us to
implement the function using the fewest number
of gates.
One commonly used method for taking any boolean
expression and converting it to its minimal
sum-of-products equivalent is the use of Karnaugh
maps.
The way Karnaugh maps work is as follows.
You start with the original truth table specification
of a function.
You then express each set of inputs, that
makes the function equal to 1, as a basic
product term.
ORing all of these product terms together
produces a sum of products representation
for the function.
Note that this representation is not yet minimal.
For our example, the sum of products is F
= NOT(A) NOT(B) NOT(C) + NOT(A) B C + A NOT(B)
NOT(C) + A NOT(B) C + A B C.
We then create the Karnaugh map for the function
by making a 2D grid representing all possible
input combinations, and ensuring that from
one column or row to the next in the grid,
only one single input can be changed.
This is known as Gray code.
Once we label the Karnaugh map, we can fill
it with 1's for each combination that produces
a 1 output and 0 for each combination that
produces a 0 output.
Next, we try to merge as many adjacent ones
as possible into groups that are of size that
is a power of 2.
Note that adjacent ones can be merged across
rows, along columns, and across the edges
of the Karnaugh map like a taurus.
Every largest grouping of 1's that is required
in order to cover all of the one's becomes
one term in the minimal sum of products representation
of the function.
To figure out what the term is, look at the
labels of all the columns and rows that are
covered by the grouping of 1's and eliminate
all inputs that appear as both a 1 and 0 input.
Because these inputs are represented in both
their 0 and 1 form, it means that that input
is not affecting the result of that term and
can thus be eliminated.
By doing this for all groupings of 1's and
then ORing the results together, one produces
a minimal sum of products representation for
the function.
Note that having overlapping ones in your
groupings is allowed and desired if it will
result in a simpler product term.
In our example, we circle the bottom two middle
1's which represent the term BC because A
appears in both its low and high form in the
grouping.
The next set of ones are the two in the rightmost
column.
These ones represent the term A NOT(B).
Finally, our last grouping wraps around the
first row to create the term NOT(B) NOT(C).
This is a minimal sum of products representation
of our function.
Note, however, that instead of grouping the
two one's in the rightmost column, we could
have instead grouped the two rightmost ones
in the bottom row.
That would have produced the term AC instead
of A NOT(B).
Either combination of terms is a valid minimal
sum of products representation for this function.