"Optimal" sounds pretty good!
Does that mean we can't do any better?
Well, not by encoding symbols one-at-a-time.
But if we want to encode long sequences of
symbols, we can reduce the expected length
of the encoding by working with, say, pairs
of symbols instead of only single symbols.
The table below shows the probability of pairs
of symbols from our example.
If we use Huffman's Algorithm to build the
optimal variable-length code using these probabilities,
it turns out the expected length when encoding
pairs is 1.646 bits/symbol.
This is a small improvement on the 1.667 bits/symbols
when encoding each symbol individually.
And we'd do even better if we encoded sequences
of length 3, and so on.
Modern file compression algorithms use an
adaptive algorithm to determine on-the-fly
which sequences occur frequently and hence
should have short encodings.
They work quite well when the data has many
repeating sequences, for example, natural
language data where some letter combinations
or even whole words occur again and again.
Compression can achieve dramatic reductions
from the original file size.
If you'd like to learn more, look up "LZW"
on Wikipedia to read the Lempel-Ziv-Welch
data compression algorithm.