Now would be a good time to take a moment
to look at the documentation for the library
of logic gates we'll use for our designs.
Look for "The Standard Cell Library" handout
in the Updates & Handouts tab, which is next
to the Courseware tab.
The information on this slide is taken from
there.
The library has both inverting gates (such
as inverters, NANDs and NORs) and non-inverting
gates (such as buffers, ANDs and ORs).
Why bother to include both types of gates?
Didn't we just learn we can build any circuit
using only NAND or NOR?
Good questions!
We get some insight into the answers if we
look at these three implementations for a
4-input AND function.
The upper circuit is a direct implementation
using the 4-input AND gate available in the
library.
The tPD of the gate is 160 picoseconds and
its size is 20 square microns.
Don't worry too much about the actual numbers,
what matters on this slide is how the numbers
compare between designs.
The middle circuit implements the same function,
this time using a 4-INPUT NAND gate hooked
to an inverter to produce the AND functionality
we want.
The tPD of this circuit is 90 picoseconds,
considerably faster than the single gate above.
The tradeoff is that the size is somewhat
larger.
How can this be?
Especially since we know the AND gate implementation
is the NAND/INVERTER pair shown in the middle
circuit.
The answer is that the creators of the library
decided to make the non-inverting gates small
but slow by using MOSFETs with much smaller
widths than used in the inverting logic gates,
which were designed to be fast.
Why would we ever want to use a slow gate?
Remember that the propagation delay of a circuit
is set by the longest path in terms of delay
from inputs to outputs.
In a complex circuit, there are many input/output
paths, but it's only the components on the
longest path that need to be fast in order
to achieve the best possible overall tPD.
The components on the other, shorter paths,
can potentially be a bit slower.
And the components on short input/output paths
can be very slow indeed.
So for the portions of the circuit that aren't
speed sensitive, it's a good tradeoff to use
slower but smaller gates.
The overall performance isn't affected, but
the total size is improved.
So for faster performance we'll design with
inverting gates, and for smallest size we'll
design with non-inverting gates.
The creators of the gate library designed
the available gates with this tradeoff in
mind.
The 4-input inverting gates are also designed
with this tradeoff in mind.
For the ultimate in performance, we want to
use a tree circuit of 2-input gates, as shown
in the lower circuit.
This implementation shaves 10 picoseconds
off the tPD, while costing us a bit more in
size.
Take a closer look at the lower circuit.
This tree circuit uses two NAND gates whose
outputs are combined with a NOR gate.
Does this really compute the AND of A, B,
C, and D?
Yup, as you can verify by building the truth
table for this combinational system using
the truth tables for NAND and NOR.
This circuit is a good example of the application
of a particular Boolean identity known as
Demorgan's Law.
There are two forms of Demorgan's law, both
of which are shown here.
The top form is the one we're interested in
for analyzing the lower circuit.
It tells us that the NOR of A with B is equivalent
to the AND of (NOT A) with (NOT B).
So the 2-input NOR gate can be thought of
as a 2-input AND gate with inverting inputs.
How does this help?
We can now see that the lower circuit is actually
a tree of AND gates, where the inverting outputs
of the first layer match up with the inverting
inputs of the second layer.
It's a little confusing the first time you
see it, but with practice you'll be comfortable
using Demorgan's law when building trees or
chains of inverting logic.
Using Demorgan's Law we can answer the question
of how to build NANDs and NORs with large
numbers of inputs.
Our gate library includes inverting gates
with up to 4 inputs.
Why stop there?
Well, the pulldown chain of a 4-input NAND
gate has 4 NFETs in series and the resistance
of the conducting channels is starting to
add up.
We could make the NFETs wider to compensate,
but then the gate gets much larger and the
wider NFETs impose a higher capacitive load
on the input signals.
The number of possible tradeoffs between size
and speed grows rapidly with the number of
inputs, so it's usually just best for the
library designer to stop at 4-input gates
and let the circuit designer take it from
there.
Happily, Demorgan's law shows us how build
trees of alternating NANDs and NORs to build
inverting logic with a large number of inputs.
Here we see schematics for an 8-input NAND
and an 8-input NOR gate.
Think of the middle layer of NOR gates in
the left circuit as AND gates with inverting
inputs and then it's easy to see that the
circuit is a tree of ANDs with an inverting
output.
Similarly, think of the middle layer of NAND
gates in the right circuit as OR gates with
inverting inputs and see that we really have
a tree of OR gates with an inverting output.
Now let's see how to build sum-of-products
circuits using inverting logic.
The two circuits shown here implement the
same sum-of-products logic function.
The one on the top uses two layers of NAND
gates, the one on the bottom, two layers of
NOR gates.
Let's visualize Demorgan's Law in action on
the top circuit.
The NAND gate with Y on its output can be
transformed by Demorgan's Law into an OR gate
with inverting inputs.
So we can redraw the circuit on the top left
as the circuit shown on the top right.
Now, notice that the inverting outputs of
the first layer are cancelled by the inverting
inputs of the second layer, a step we can
show visually by removing matching inversions.
And, voila, we see the NAND/NAND circuit in
sum-of-products form: a layer of inverters,
a layer of AND gates, and an OR gate to combine
the product terms.
We can use a similar visualization to transform
the output gate of the bottom circuit, giving
us the circuit on the bottom right.
Match up the bubbles and we see that we have
the same logic function as above.
Looking at the NOR/NOR circuit on the bottom
left, we see it has 4 inverters, whereas the
NAND/NAND circuit only has one.
Why would we ever use the NOR/NOR implementation?
It has to do with the loading on the inputs.
In the top circuit, the input A connects to
a total of four MOSFET switches.
In the bottom circuit, it connects to only
the two MOSFET switches in the inverter.
So, the bottom circuit imposes half the capacitive
load on the A signal.
This might be significant if the signal A
connected to many such circuits.
The bottom line: when you find yourself needing
a fast implementation for the AND/OR circuitry
for a sum-of-products expression, try using
the NAND/NAND implementation.
It'll be noticeably faster than using AND/OR.