In order to better understand the role of
each of the beta control signals, we will
work through an example problem that provides
us with a partially filled control table for
5 different instructions.
Two of these instructions are existing beta
instructions that we must infer from the provided
control signals.
The other three are three new instructions
that we are adding to our beta by modifying
the necessary control signals to produce the
desired behavior of each of the operations.
The first instruction that we want to add
to our beta is an LDX instruction which is
a load that is double indexed.
What this means is that in order to produce
the effective address of the load, instead
of adding the contents of a register to a
constant as is done in the LD instruction,
we add the contents of two different registers.
So the address for this load operation is
the result of adding together the contents
of registers Ra and Rb.
The contents of the memory location pointed
to by this effective address are loaded into
register Rc.
Finally, the PC is incremented by 4 to point
to the next instruction.
The second instruction that we want to add
to our beta is a MVZC instruction which is
a move constant if zero instruction.
The way this instruction works is that if
the contents of register Ra equal zero, then
the sign extended version of the literal constant
will be loaded into register Rc.
This is followed by incrementing the PC to
point to the next instruction.
The third instruction that we want to add
to our beta is a STR instruction which is
a store relative instruction.
For this instruction, the effective address
is computed by sign extending the constant
C, multiplying it by 4 and adding it to PC
+ 4.
The contents of register Rc are then stored
at the memory location pointed to by the effective
address that was just computed.
As a final step, the PC is incremented by
4 to point to the next instruction.
We are given the partially filled control
ROM shown here.
It is our job to fill in all the yellow boxes
labeled with a ?.
Let's begin by looking at the top row of this
table.
The value that stands out as a bit different
in this row is the PCSEL value which is equal
to 2.
For most instructions PCSEL equals 0, for
branch instructions it equals 1, and for JMP
instructions it equals 2.
This means that the instruction described
in this row must be a JMP instruction.
Zooming in on the PCSEL control logic from
the beta diagram, we see that normally PCSEL
= 0 to go to the next instruction.
PCSEL = 1 in order to perform a branch operation,
and PCSEL = 2 in order to perform a jump operation
where the target of the jump is specified
by JT, or the jump target.
This means that the instruction described
in this row must be a JMP instruction.
The behavior of a JMP instruction is shown
here.
The effective address is calculated by taking
the contents of RA and clearing the bottom
2 bits so that the value becomes word aligned.
The address of the next instruction, which
is PC + 4, is stored in register Rc in case
we need to return to the next instruction
in the program.
The PC is then updated with the new effective
address in order to actually continue execution
at the destination of the JMP instruction.
This dataflow diagram highlights the required
dataflow through the beta in order to properly
implement the JMP instruction.
Note that no red lines pass through the ALU
or memory because the ALU and memory are not
used for this instruction.
The control signals that must be set in order
to follow this path in the beta are as follows:
WDSEL, or write data select, must be set to
0 in order to pass the value of PC + 4 through
the WDSEL mux.
WERF, or write enable register file, must
be set to 1 in order to enable writing to
the register file.
WASEL, or write address select, must be set
to 0 in order to write to the Rc register
and not to the XP register.
ASEL, BSEL, and ALUFN, are all don't cares
for the JMP instruction.
In addition MOE, which stands for memory output
enable, is also a don't care because this
instruction does not use the memory data.
The one control signal related to the memory
that we do need to worry about is the MWR,
or memory write read, signal which must be
set to 0 so that no value will be written
to memory.
Going back to our control ROM and filling
in the value of WERF, we see that the control
signals for the JMP instruction correspond
to the dataflow diagram of the beta that we
just looked at.
Moving on to row two of our control ROM, we
see that now we have PCSEL = Z in this row.
This suggests that the instruction corresponding
to this row is some kind of a branch instruction.
Of our two branch instructions, the one that
branches when Z = 1 is BEQ.
This means that this row corresponds to a
BEQ operation.
The rest of the control signals for the BEQ
operation look just like the ones for the
JMP because here too, the ALU and memory are
not used so the only ALU and memory related
signal that must be set is MWR so we don't
write to memory.
Furthermore, like the JMP instruction, the
branch instructions also store the return
address in register Rc, so the behavior of
the control signals related to the register
file are all the same.
We now take a look at the third row of the
control ROM.
In this row, we are actually told that the
corresponding instruction is the newly added
LDX instruction.
So it is our job to determine how to set the
missing control signals in order to get the
desired behavior for this operation.
Recall that the expected behavior of this
instruction is that the contents of register
Ra and Rb will be added together in order
to produce the effective address of the load.
This means that we need to perform an ADD
as our ALUFN.
We also need ASEL and BSEL equal to zero in
order to pass the values of registers Ra and
Rb to the ALU.
The complete dataflow through the register
file, ALU, and memory is shown here.
In order to read register Rb rather than Rc,
RA2SEL must be set to 0.
As we just mentioned, ASEL and BSEL are set
to 0 and ALUFN is set to ADD.
The result of adding registers Ra and Rb is
used as the address of the load.
This is called MA, or memory address in the
beta diagram.
In order to enable reading from memory, we
set MWR to 0 and MOE to 1.
This sets the read/write functionality to
read, and enables an output to be read from
the read port of the memory.
On the beta diagram, the read data is labeled
MRD, or memory read data.
The data that is read from the memory is then
passed along to the register file by setting
WDSEL = 2.
In order to write this result to register
Rc, WERF = 1, and WASEL = 0.
So the completed control ROM for the LDX operation
is shown here.
We now move on to the fourth instruction.
Here we see that the ALUFN just passes operand
B through the register file.
We also see that WERF is dependent on the
value of Z.
This means that the instruction that corresponds
to this row is MVZC which moves a constant
into register Rc if the contents of register
Ra = 0.
The way this instruction works is that BSEL
= 1 in order to pass the constant through
as the B operand, and ALUFN = B to pass that
constant through the ALU.
WDSEL = 1 so that the output of the ALU is
fed back as the write value for the register
file.
Because WDSEL = 1 and not 2, we know that
the data coming out of the memory will be
ignored so MOE can be a don't care.
Of course, MWR still must be set to 0 in order
to ensure that we don't write any random values
into our memory.
RA2SEL is also a don't care because we don't
care whether Register Rb or Register Rc are
passed through as the second read argument
of the register file, RD2.
The reason we don't care is because the BSEL
= 1 will ignore the RD2 value and pass through
the constant that comes directly from the
instruction after sign extending it.
ASEL is also a don't care because the ALU
will ignore the A input when ALUFN = B.
WASEL must be 0 so that the result of the
operation is written into register Rc.
Finally, PCSEL = 0 to load PC + 4 into the
PC register so that the next instruction will
get fetched after this one.
We are now on the last row of our control
ROM.
We know that this row must correspond to our
third added instruction which is STR, or store
relative.
Recall that this instruction writes the contents
of register Rc into memory at the address
that is computed by the effective address
line.
The effective address for this instruction
is PC + 4 + 4 * SEXT(C).
The extra adder, just under the instruction
memory, is used to calculate PC + 4 + 4 * SEXT(C).
This value is then fed to the ALU via the
A operand by setting ASEL = 1.
Setting ALUFN = A passes this value as the
output of the ALU in order to be used as the
memory address.
This is the address that the store will write
to in memory.
The value that will be written to this address
in memory is the contents of register Rc.
Register Rc is fed through the register file
by setting RA2SEL = 1.
This makes RD2 have the contents of register
Rc.
This value then becomes the MWD, or memory
write data which is the data that will be
stored in the memory address that was produced
by the ALU.
In order to enable writing to the memory,
MWR must be set to 1.
Since WERF = 0, nothing can be written to
the register file.
This means that the value of WDSEL and WASEL
are don't cares since the register file won't
be affected regardless of their values.
Finally, the PC is incremented by 4 to fetch
the next instruction.
So our completed Control ROM for the STR operation
is shown here.