Non-volatile memories are used to maintain
system state even when the system is powered
down.
In flash memories, long-term storage is achieved
by storing charge on an well-insulated conductor
called a floating gate, where it will remain
stable for years.
The floating gate is incorporated in a standard
MOSFET, placed between the MOSFET's gate and
the MOSFET's channel.
If there is no charge stored on the floating
gate, the MOSFET can be turned on, i.e., be
made to conduct, by placing a voltage V_1
on the gate terminal, creating an inversion
layer that connects the MOSFET's source and
drain terminals.
If there is a charge stored on the floating
gate, a higher voltage V_2 is required to
turn on the MOSFET.
By setting the gate terminal to a voltage
between V_1 and V_2, we can determine if the
floating gate is charged by testing to see
if the MOSFET is conducting.
In fact, if we can measure the current flowing
through the MOSFET, we can determine how much
charge is stored on the floating gate, making
it possible to store multiple bits of information
in one flash cell by varying the amount of
charge on its floating gate.
Flash cells can be connected in parallel or
series to form circuits resembling CMOS NOR
or NAND gates, allowing for a variety of access
architectures suitable for either random or
sequential access.
Flash memories are very dense, approaching
the areal density of DRAMs, particularly when
each cell holds multiple bits of information.
Read access times for NOR flash memories are
similar to that of DRAMs, several tens of
nanoseconds.
Read times for NAND flash memories are much
longer, on the order of 10 microseconds.
Write times for all types of flash memories
are quite long since high voltages have to
be used to force electrons to cross the insulating
barrier surrounding the floating gate.
Flash memories can only be written some number
of times before the insulating layer is damaged
to the point that the floating gate will no
longer reliably store charge.
Currently the number of guaranteed writes
varies between 100,000 and
To work around this limitation, flash chips
contain clever address mapping algorithms
so that writes to the same address actually
are mapped to different flash cells on each
successive write.
The bottom line is that flash memories are
a higher-performance but higher-cost replacement
for the hard-disk drive, the long-time technology
of choice for non-volatile storage.
A hard-disk drive (HDD) contains one or more
rotating platters coated with a magnetic material.
The platters rotate at speeds ranging from
5400 to 15000 RPM.
A read/write head positioned above the surface
of a platter can detect or change the orientation
of the magnetization of the magnetic material
below.
The read/write head is mounted an actuator
that allows it to be positioned over different
circular tracks.
To read a particular sector of data, the head
must be positioned radially over the correct
track, then wait for the platter to rotate
until it's over the desired sector.
The average total time required to correctly
position the head is on the order of 10 milliseconds,
so hard disk access times are quite long.
However, once the read/write head is in the
correct position, data can be transferred
at the respectable rate of 100 megabytes/second.
If the head has to be repositioned between
each access, the effective transfer rate drops
1000-fold, limited by the time it takes to
reposition the head.
Hard disk drives provide cost-effective non-volatile
storage for terabytes of data, albeit at the
cost of slow access times.
This completes our whirlwind tour of memory
technologies.
If you'd like to learn a bit more, Wikipedia
has useful articles on each type of device.
SRAM sizes and access times have kept pace
with the improvements in the size and speed
of integrated circuits.
Interestingly, although capacities and transfer
rates for DRAMs and HDDs have improved, their
initial access times have not improved nearly
as rapidly.
Thankfully over the past decade flash memories
have helped to fill the performance gap between
processor speeds and HDDs.
But the gap between processor cycle times
and DRAM access times has continued to widen,
increasing the challenge of designing low-latency
high-capacity memory systems.
The capacity of the available memory technologies
varies over 10 orders of magnitude, and the
variation in latencies varies over 8 orders
of magnitude.
This creates a considerable challenge in figuring
out how to navigate the speed vs size tradeoffs.
Each transition in memory hierarchy shows
the same fundamental design choice: we can
pick smaller-and-faster or larger-and-slower.
This is a bit awkward actually - can we figure
how to get the best of both worlds?
We want our system to behave as if it had
a large, fast, and cheap main memory.
Clearly we can't achieve this goal using any
single memory technology.
Here's an idea: can we use a hierarchical
system of memories with different tradeoffs
to achieve close to the same results as a
large, fast, cheap memory?
Could we arrange for memory locations we're
using often to be stored, say, in SRAM and
have those accesses be low latency?
Could the rest of the data could be stored
in the larger and slower memory components,
moving the between the levels when necessary?
Let's follow this train of thought and see
where it leads us.
There are two approaches we might take.
The first is to expose the hierarchy, providing
some amount of each type of storage and let
the programmer decide how best to allocate
the various memory resources for each particular
computation.
The programmer would write code that moved
data into fast storage when appropriate, then
back to the larger and slower memories when
low-latency access was no longer required.
There would only be a small amount of the
fastest memory, so data would be constantly
in motion as the focus of the computation
changed.
This approach has had notable advocates.
Perhaps the most influential was Seymour Cray,
the "Steve Jobs" of supercomputers.
Cray was the architect of the world's fastest
computers in each of three decades, inventing
many of the technologies that form the foundation
of high-performance computing.
His insight to managing the memory hierarchy
was to organize data as vectors and move vectors
in and out of fast memory under program control.
This was actually a good data abstraction
for certain types of scientific computing
and his vector machines had the top computing
benchmarks for many years.
The second alternative is to hide the hierarchy
and simply tell the programmer they have a
large, uniform address space to use as they
wish.
The memory system would, behind the scenes,
move data between the various levels of the
memory hierarchy, depending on the usage patterns
it detected.
This would require circuitry to examine each
memory access issued by the CPU to determine
where in the hierarchy to find the requested
location.
And then, if a particular region of addresses
was frequently accessed - say, when fetching
instructions in a loop -
the memory system would arrange for those
accesses to be mapped to the fastest memory
component and automatically move the loop
instructions there.
All of this machinery would be transparent
to the programmer: the program would simply
fetch instructions and access data and the
memory system would handle the rest.
Could the memory system automatically arrange
for the right data to be in the right place
at the right time?
Cray was deeply skeptical of this approach.
He famously quipped "that you can't fake what
you haven't got".
Wouldn't the programmer, with her knowledge
of how data was going to be used by a particular
program, be able to do a better job by explicitly
managing the memory hierarchy?
It turns out that when running general-purpose
programs, it is possible to build an automatically
managed, low-latency, high-capacity hierarchical
memory system that appears as one large, uniform
memory.
What's the insight that makes this possible?
That's the topic of the next section.