The nice feature of two's complement representation
is that it allows you to do both addition
and subtraction as addition problems, by simply
turning the subtraction problem A-B into an
addition problem of A + (-B).
Since we now know how to easily negate values
in two's complement, this is pretty straight
forward.
For example, let's perform 15 - 18 using 6-bit
two's complement representation.
15-18 = 15 + (-18)
15 = 001111
18 = 010010
To convert 18 to -18, we flip all the bits
and add one.
This results in 101110 which is = -18.
We can now take our two's complement representation
of our two numbers and add them together.
Whenever we add 1 + 1 in binary that produces
a 0 plus a carry of 1.
So our final sum is 111101.
To see what this number is equal to, we again
flip the bits and add one.
Flipping the bits, we get 000010, and adding
one to that we get 000011 which equals 3.
Which means that 111101 = -3 which is the
result we expected to get when performing
15-18.
Let's try another example:
27 - 6 = 27 + (-6)
27 is equal to 16 + 8 + 2 + 1 which is equal
to 24 + 23 + 21
+ 20.
So in two's complement representation this
number is 011011.
6 is equal to 4 + 2 which is equal to 22
+ 21, so its 6-bit binary representation
is 000110.
To find the representation of negative six,
we flip all the bits and add one resulting
in 111010.
When we add these two numbers together, remembering
that in binary 1 + 1 produces a 0 plus a carry
of 1, we find that our result ends up having
7 bits.
This most significant bit is dropped because
we are working with 6-bit representation in
this case.
So our final result is 010101 which is equal
to 24 + 22 + 20
which equal 16 + 4 + 1 or 21.
If you try adding two numbers whose result
is beyond the range of numbers that can be
represented using your N-bit representation,
then that means that overflow occurred.
Overflow can be detected by looking at the
sign of the two numbers being added and the
sign of the resulting number.
If you try adding two positive numbers (where
the most significant bit is 0) and your result
ends up being negative (your most significant
bit is a 1), then overflow occurred.
Similarly if you try adding two negative numbers
whose most significant bit is one, and you
end up with a result that is positive (where
the most significant bit is 0) then once again
overflow occurred.
Overflow cannot occur when you add a positive
and negative number that are within range.
Let's take a look at an example of this.
Suppose we try adding 31 + 12 using 6-bit
two's complement.
This results in 101011 which has its most
significant bit equal to 1 even though we
were adding two positive numbers.
This means that overflow occurred.
Overflow occurred because the result of adding
these two numbers is 43 which is larger than
2 to the 5th minus 1, or 31, which is the largest
positive number that can be represented using
6-bits two's complement.