Surprise!
We've just been given a robotic ant that has
an FSM for its brain.
The inputs to the FSM come from the ant's
two antennae, labeled L and R.
An antenna input is 1 if the antenna is touching
something, otherwise its 0.
The outputs of the FSM control the ant's motion.
We can make it step forward by setting the
F output to 1, and turn left or right by asserting
the TL or TR outputs respectively.
If the ant tries to both turn and step forward,
the turn happens first.
Note that the ant can turn when its antenna
are touching something, but it can't move
forward.
We've been challenged to design an ant brain
that will let it find its way out of a simple
maze like the one shown here.
We remember reading that if the maze doesn't
have any unconnected walls (i.e.,no islands),
we can escape using the "right hand rule"
where we put our right hand on the wall and
walk so that our hand stays on the wall.
Let's try to implement this strategy.
We'll assume that initially our ant is lost
in space.
The only sensible strategy to walk forward
until we find a maze wall.
So our initial state, labeled LOST, asserts
the F output, causing the ant to move forward
until at least one of the antennae touches
something, i.e., at least one of the L or
R inputs is a 1.
So now the ant finds itself in one of these
three situations.
To implement the "right hand rule", the ant
should turn left (counterclockwise) until
it's antennae have just cleared the wall.
To do this, we'll add a rotate-counterclockwise
state, which asserts the turn-left output
until both L and R are 0.
Now the ant is standing with a wall to its
right and we can start the process of following
the wall with its right antenna.
So we have the ant step forward and right,
assuming that it will immediately touch the
wall again.
The WALL1 state asserts both the turn-right
and forward outputs, then checks the right
antenna to see what to do next.
If the right antenna does touch, as expected,
the ant turns left to free the antenna and
then steps forward.
The WALL2 state asserts both the turn-left
and forward outputs, then checks the antennae.
If the right antenna is still touching, it
needs to continue turning.
If the left antenna touches, it's run into
a corner and needs to reorient itself so the
new wall is on its right, the situation we
dealt with the rotate-counterclockwise state.
Finally, if both antennae are free, the ant
should be in the state of the previous slide:
standing parallel to the wall, so we return
the WALL1 state.
Our expectation is that the FSM will alternate
between the WALL1 and WALL2 states as the
ant moves along the wall.
If it reaches an inside corner, it rotates
to put the new wall on its right and keeps
going.
What happens when it reaches an outside corner?
When the ant is in the WALL1 state, it moves
forward and turns right, then checks its right
antenna, expecting the find the wall its traveling
along.
But if its an outside corner, there's no wall
to touch!
The correct strategy in this case is to keep
turning right and stepping forward until the
right antenna touches the wall that's around
the corner.
The CORNER state implements this strategy,
transitioning to the WALL2 state when the
ant reaches the wall again.
Hey, this might even work!
Let's try it out…
Meet the Roboant simulator.
On the left we see a text representation of
the transition table for the FSM brain.
Each action line specifies an input pattern,
which, if it matches, will set the next state
and output signals as specified.
This particular version of Roboant allows
the ant to drop or pickup breadcrumbs, and
to sense breadcrumbs it comes across - these
inputs and outputs aren't needed for this
demo.
The input pattern specifies a value for the
current state and antenna inputs.
The simulator highlights the row in the table
that matches the current inputs.
As you can see, initially the ant is the LOST
state with neither antennae touching.
On the right is a map showing our green ant
standing in a maze with blue walls.
We can select several different mazes to try.
To see the ant in action, let's click the
STEP button several times.
After a few steps, the ant hits the wall,
then rotates counterclockwise to free its
antenna.
Now it starts following the wall until it
reaches a corner, at which point it keeps
turning right and stepping until it's once
again in contact with the wall.
Now we'll let it run and watch as the FSM
patiently pursues the programmed strategy,
responding to inputs and generating the appropriate
output responses.
With more sensors and actuators, you can see
that fairly sophisticated behaviors and responses
would be possible.
In essence this is exactly what modern robots
do - they too have FSM brains full of pre-programmed
behaviors that let them perform their assigned
tasks.
Neat!