SARAH HANSEN: So how did
you become interested
in computation structures?
CHRISTOPHER TERMAN:
Well, in the early '70s
I was a college student trying
to earn my way through college.
And so I was the computer
operator on the third shift
for the campus computer.
That was in the era in which
you could only afford one.
And since watching the
blinking lights was boring,
I pulled out the schematics
for the computer I
was running for the university.
And I started trying to figure
out how the computer worked.
Ever since then, it's been
sort of a lifelong interest
in figuring out,
how do they actually
put together these components
to make a machine that
can do computation?
SARAH HANSEN: And
that interest is
coupled with your interest
in teaching and learning,
and especially online education.
Could you talk a
little bit about where
that interest comes from?
CHRISTOPHER TERMAN: Well,
I was always fascinated
and very motivated by the great
teachers I could listen to.
And so everybody picks
a model when they're
a teenager or a young
adult. They say,
I want to be like so-and-so.
Well, the so-and-sos
I liked to pick
were the excellent
teachers I had.
So I said, I'm going to try
to be the best teacher I can.
There's something very
satisfying about teaching
students and having them
nod and suddenly get it.
So it's been sort of a very
fulfilling experience to teach.
And so that's sort of a
virtuous cycle, right?
You get good vibes
from teaching.
And then you do it
better next year.
And you get better vibes.
And so for 40 years,
that's been a great--
it's been great.
SARAH HANSEN: What kind
of background experiences
do the students bring related
to computation structures?
CHRISTOPHER TERMAN:
It's all over the map.
So some of them will come
having programmed computers
for a long time, and maybe
even know a little bit
about how the computers are
structured on the insides.
Other people have
not done beans.
They're just-- I wanted
to take a course.
I've used computers,
sort of browsers,
laptops, email, sort of thing.
But they have no idea about
the OS or the actual hardware
inside.
And so they come with interest,
but no background at all.
SARAH HANSEN: So how do
you structure a course
to meet the needs of people with
diverse backgrounds like that?
CHRISTOPHER TERMAN: Right.
So to handle really
diverse backgrounds,
you have to have a huge
range of materials.
So you need something
that somebody who just--
I need to start
at the beginning.
You need a beginning
for them to start at.
And for somebody who's
sort of past the first half
of your material, you
need a second half which
will engage their interests.
So I create a huge--
I think of it as a buffet.
There's lots of dishes.
And you can start at the
beginning of the buffet
and sort of pick
it up from scratch.
Or you can say, I'll skip
the first couple courses,
and I'm ready to dive
in sort of in the middle
of the conversation somewhere.
So I think the real key
is having a huge selection
of materials to draw from.
And that's, I think, one
of the hallmarks of 6.004
has been that we have
every possible way
of learning the material.
So not only for
different backgrounds,
but for different
learning styles.
So some students want
to talk or listen.
Some students want to read.
Some students just
want to work on P-sets
and do just-in-time learning,
where they sort of say,
here's what I need to know.
Now I'll go look
at the material,
just find the worked
example, and if I
don't understand
the worked example,
I'll go actually read the text.
So they actually only get to
the beginning of, if you will,
the introductory or the
explanatory material only,
and as a last resort
if they somehow
didn't pick it up from before.
SARAH HANSEN:
That's interesting.
CHRISTOPHER TERMAN: So many
different learning styles,
many different backgrounds.
SARAH HANSEN: How has the MITx
Residential platform enabled
you to provide this buffet?
CHRISTOPHER TERMAN:
Well, one, it's
a one-stop shop for all the
different sorts of materials.
And the other is there's sort
of an emerging best practice
about how to explain material
to people for the first time.
So you want to do short bites;
sound bites, video bites.
You know, those short
segments of learning
where you introduce a single
skill or a single concept.
And then you take a moment
to actually give them
some check yourself questions.
So the idea is in theory
you just listened to this
or watched it.
I'm going to ask you some
simple questions, not puzzlers.
They're just if you
understood what I just
told you on the video,
then you can answer them.
And so that gives
those students a chance
to start the process
of retrieval learning,
where you keep coming
back again and again.
And I'll ask you a similar sort
of question two segments later.
And pretty soon,
you're pulling it out
of your short-term, and then
medium-term, and long-term
memories.
So the MITx platform
works really
well at letting you construct
those sort of learning
sequences.
And I think the
students appreciate it.
Everything is more
and more bite-sized.
We both know, as
you can imagine,
pushing play on a 50-minute
video and along about minute--
well, I'm going to say 37,
but along about minute six,
you're going to be,
all right, maybe I
should check my email while
I'm listening to this.
SARAH HANSEN: Right.
CHRISTOPHER TERMAN: It's
keeping things short and sweet.
So you have a huge--
because now you have a
bunch of short bites.
Now, the MITx platform
lets you organize
those with questions that
let you sort of continue
to test your learning.
So it's actually worked out to
be a very nice way of making
a fairly organized tour
through the material
that the students can start,
and stop, and come back to.
Plus it's asynchronous.
In other words, they get to
choose their time and place.
And us teachers always
have a fantasy, well,
they didn't come to
lecture, so I'm sure at 3:00
in the morning when
they're wide awake,
they're actually watching it.
SARAH HANSEN: Of course.
CHRISTOPHER TERMAN:
If you actually
look at the statistics
for the viewing,
there's a lot of viewing
that happens in quiz weeks.
So a lot of people may
be using it as sort of a,
OK, I want the intense,
immersive introduction
to the material.
SARAH HANSEN: Right.
This must be just such
an exciting time for you
as someone who's really
interested in the scholarship
of teaching and
learning, and then
the emergence of
these digital tools
to enable that learning
through best practices.
I can feel your enthusiasm for
kind of the era that we're in.
CHRISTOPHER TERMAN: Yeah.
Well, so much of how us
people-- or those of us who
teach at the university level,
we get handed a piece of chalk
and be told to teach,
unlike the teachers
for your kids in
elementary school
who've actually gone through
a program that teaches them
how to teach.
We're just said, here teach.
And so it's all anecdotal.
It's all trying to remember
how people taught you.
Finally, we have the
online courses providing
a real educational laboratory.
We're able to try out
different techniques.
We're able to make fairly
accurate assessments
of how well did that
just work, whether it
was an exercise, or a video
segment, or a design problem.
And so we can actually do
A/B tests in the same cadre.
So it's pretty
neat having a lab.
I mean, as a scientist and
engineer, you can say, look,
I know about the hypothesis.
Test it through a
bunch of experiments.
We can really do the experiments
with the MITx platform.
And so that's been great.
SARAH HANSEN: Yeah,
it's really exciting.
CHRISTOPHER TERMAN: It is.
SARAH HANSEN: Let's talk about
learning in the classroom
and teaching large
lecture classes.
What strategies do you have
for keeping students engaged?
CHRISTOPHER TERMAN:
Well, that's interesting.
Because we have so many
different materials,
really the only students
who come to lecture
are the ones for whom
lecture is how they learn.
And I was such a student.
SARAH HANSEN: I see.
CHRISTOPHER TERMAN:
So the people
who are there are
not a draft army.
They're all volunteers.
SARAH HANSEN: Self-selected.
CHRISTOPHER TERMAN: So they're
prepared to be somewhat engaged
by a vocal presentation.
SARAH HANSEN: I see.
CHRISTOPHER TERMAN: So I have a
well-developed set of materials
that I present in
class that have
sort of been debugged for having
not too much or too little.
A progression that
most people can follow.
And then happily, when
you teach for a while,
you start to get more relaxed.
And so it's a very relaxed
sort of experience.
I tell jokes.
I tell stories from my career.
And it's interesting to me how
when the students are making
comments at the end of the
semester on the evaluations,
many of them say, I
really liked the stories.
SARAH HANSEN: Interesting.
CHRISTOPHER TERMAN:
So after boring you
with technical details,
it's fun to say,
and then when I
tried to use that,
this following thing happened.
And all of a sudden, they're
sort of perking up, saying, oh.
SARAH HANSEN: And I think it
helps them remember the related
content, too.
CHRISTOPHER TERMAN: It does.
It does.
When you think about what
you remember from lectures,
it's almost never
a technical nugget.
It's a joke they told, or
an accident that happened,
or a mistake that was made.
SARAH HANSEN: Right.
CHRISTOPHER TERMAN:
And so it's--
there's this concept
called fluency,
which is basically how
smoothly things are going,
and everybody's nodding.
So your mind is starting to
drift, because it's all--
so it's actually good to try
to put a little disfluency
into your lecture, to
actually have a-- you stop,
and you tell a joke.
SARAH HANSEN: Right.
CHRISTOPHER TERMAN:
Or you make a mistake,
or you drop the
chalk, and say, darn,
and you look at the floor.
SARAH HANSEN: Right.
CHRISTOPHER TERMAN:
And here's what
I like to do is you walk
out from behind the lecture
table or lectern, and you
approach the audience.
And you can see them sort of
going, wait, he's escaped.
So just anything that sort of
switches up the sort of I'm
just going along
with the flow here.
So making little flows that
have things that change
make a lot of difference in
keeping people sort of engaged.
SARAH HANSEN:
That's a great tip.
Let's talk for a second
about the teaching team.
I understand there
are a fair number
of people involved in developing
and teaching this course.
Could you talk about that?
CHRISTOPHER TERMAN: Well,
we have a little cadre
of people who are instructors.
I've been sort of part of
that cadre every semester
for a very long time.
But we have other people who
come in from the outside.
In recent years, the department
has added lecturer resources.
So there's another lecturer
associated with it.
And then faculty come in.
And they provide a little
depth to the gene pool.
SARAH HANSEN: Sure.
CHRISTOPHER TERMAN: But
then we have graduate TAs
who teach recitations.
And we have student
undergraduate TAs, and then
lab assistants.
So sort of we have
this whole hierarchy.
They've all taken the course.
Almost, they've all loved it.
So I mean, it's sort of the
material that people say,
oh, this is really pretty neat.
I can't wait to tell the next
person about how this works.
SARAH HANSEN: Right.
CHRISTOPHER TERMAN: And so
as they sit there and work
with the students,
sort of like me,
there's an enthusiasm
that sort of bubbles out.
SARAH HANSEN: It's contagious.
CHRISTOPHER TERMAN: Yeah.
And the students actually--
I sort of listed
things sort of--
well, I was going
to say top down.
I'm not sure lecturers
are at the top
or instructors are at the top.
But the students actually
prefer the other thing,
which is actually asking an
LA is not very intimidating.
The students, maybe they
just took it last semester.
And so they have it
fresh in their minds
what it is they needed to
do in order to get whatever
it is they're trying to get.
And then you sort of
work the chain up,
work up the hierarchy to get
an answer of people below.
And that way you're
only asking questions
of the more
intimidating people when
you're pretty sure that no
one else has the answer.
So it's really-- by the time
the questions sort of get to me,
mostly no one is worried
that they're a dumb question.
Now, I don't really
believe in dumb questions.
I think all questions
are sort of interesting.
But I think the students
are, look, I asked 10 people.
None of us knew, so
now we can ask you.
And I'm pretty confident that
it wasn't an obvious thing
that if I only read the
assignment I would have known.
So that sort of range of sort
of experience level and age,
at the high end of
the experience level,
you can get an answer
to any question.
At the beginning end of
the experience level,
you're talking to somebody who--
SARAH HANSEN: Just
had that experience
CHRISTOPHER TERMAN: Just months
ago did what you're doing.
And so we can be--
I can ask you, and we
won't be embarrassed.
SARAH HANSEN: Right, right.
What's the role
of the online fora
in the course for
helping students feel
comfortable asking questions?
And how do you monitor it?
How do you run it productively?
This is something that educators
sometimes struggle with.
CHRISTOPHER TERMAN:
Well, I mean, to me,
it's a wonderful asset.
For the first time I'm able
to make a thoughtful answer
to a question and
have 180 people look
at the answer instead of one.
And then the next person who
has the same question, you say,
well, I just spent 10 minutes.
And with a large class,
you can't spend 10 minutes
for each of 300 people.
So it's a great place
to ask questions.
I try to always give a
thoughtful and respectful
answer to each question.
So even if the question
is sort of like,
well, if you had done the
reading, you would known,
I say, well, if you look
back at the material,
you'll see it explains
the following.
Try to make it not--
a little hint that maybe a
little bit more preparation.
But many of the questions are,
look, I read the material.
I'm still not getting it.
I need an example.
And so the students,
I try to make students
feel very comfortable asking.
It's never-- there's nothing.
No cost.
They can ask
anonymously, so that
removes some of the barrier.
SARAH HANSEN: OK.
CHRISTOPHER TERMAN: And
then I think-- let's see.
In the fall of 2017, we had
about 2,500 contributions
to the forum.
SARAH HANSEN: Wow.
OK.
CHRISTOPHER TERMAN: The
average response time
is about 20 minutes.
And so you say, wait, but
students are asking questions
at 3:00 AM.
How does that work?
And it turns out
that we have TAs.
We particularly have
some really good--
SARAH HANSEN: Nocturnal TAs.
CHRISTOPHER TERMAN:
Yes, exactly.
At 3:00 AM they're just
hitting their stride.
A lot of us who are
involved in the course
sort of have-- we
put the notification
of postings on real time.
And so we get an
email right away.
And so often we can
just type in an answer.
And it's--
SARAH HANSEN: OK.
CHRISTOPHER TERMAN:
And I'm really--
I think the fast response time
really reduces the frustration
level of the students.
SARAH HANSEN: Ah.
CHRISTOPHER TERMAN:
There's nothing
like being stuck on something.
SARAH HANSEN: Right.
CHRISTOPHER TERMAN: And say,
I wish I could ask somebody.
Well, for the first time,
it's 3:12 in the morning.
And you can say, wait, I can
ask, and I can get an answer.
And the students really,
really appreciate that.
So the forum has
really, I think,
changed students'
level of frustration
when they get stuck.
Being stuck is just a 10-minute
process, not a two-day process.
SARAH HANSEN: Right.
CHRISTOPHER TERMAN: My
god, the next office hours
are after the weekend.
What do I do?
And of course, a lot of
students are doing work outside
of sort of 9:00 to 5:00 hours.
So it's a way for the staff to
be a 24/7 staff instead of just
a 9:00 to 5:00, five
days a week staff.
The staff like-- and then the
students work like that, too.
Most of the people who
are helping on the forum
are keeping the same schedule
as the users of the forum.
So it's a good match.
SARAH HANSEN: OK.
Let's talk for a
minute about the lab
experiences in the course.
So students get
hands-on experience
doing digital design.
CHRISTOPHER TERMAN: Yes.
SARAH HANSEN: Could
you talk about a few
of those experiences?
And also, does that take place
here where we are right now?
CHRISTOPHER TERMAN: Well,
you can do it anywhere.
It's browser-based.
So there's no
software to download.
It's just on the web.
You go.
SARAH HANSEN: I see.
CHRISTOPHER TERMAN: And
so one of the things
I enjoy doing is to build
browser-based computer-aided
design tools.
It turns out that they
actually work really well.
The modern browser
environments are
quite capable as a
programming environment.
You have to learn a few tricks,
but once you do, it works well.
So they're reasonably
high-performing tools.
They can sit down and do.
Much of the design work we do is
sort of design-driven learning,
where we're actually trying
to get them to build something
that we've described.
SARAH HANSEN: I see.
CHRISTOPHER TERMAN: And
we may have even told them
in quite some detail
how it fits together,
but there's something about
the old muscle memory bit
about if you actually
build it yourself, drag
the components on
and wire them up,
you'll remember it much better.
Or you'll ask yourself, wait,
does this go here or here?
And then you say--
then you look back,
and you're starting
to say, I'm looking
at this diagram,
the instructions,
for the first time with enough
care to appreciate that,
oh, I have to put it this
way in order for it to work.
And so we're sort of--
hand and eye are engaged.
It's not just a
listening experience.
We are able to-- if
you assemble something,
we build tests to see if
it functions correctly.
And so you can tell right away
whether you've screwed it up.
It's not like, well, I turn
it in, and a week later--
long past when I've
ceased to care--
I get back a red X. And
I say, OK, well, dang.
So here they have to get it
right in order to complete it,
but we tell them right
away that it's not right.
And they keep working on it.
Or they post on Piazza.
My circuit doesn't work.
The staff can pull it up
remotely from the server,
and say, oh, here's where--
here's your mistake.
So the idea is that the students
are actually being engineers.
This may be one of the first
actual build-it experiences
they have.
Again, these are
sophomores, right?
So it's a little bit
of fun to say, well,
this is sort of neat.
I've actually put together
the circuit and debugged it.
So I had to say,
well, what was wrong?
I got a wrong thing.
What did I do wrong?
And then fix it.
So that's a very
valuable experience.
So it's one thing.
It's like the late
night TV salesman.
When you watch them, use it.
It's so easy.
SARAH HANSEN: Right.
CHRISTOPHER TERMAN: But
you get the widget home.
And it doesn't work.
And so that's-- they've
seen it in lectures.
They've seen it on the videos.
They've seen it the
worked examples.
And it's all extremely obvious
that this is straightforward
until you do it yourself.
And then you fill
in all the pieces,
that you were just being,
oh, how hard could that be?
Oh, now I know.
SARAH HANSEN: Right.
CHRISTOPHER TERMAN: So they
work hard at trying to fix that.
And I think the whole idea
of these virtual lab benches
is great.
As I said, the
execution environment
and the graphics environment
on the browser is first rate.
It's very easy to build
sophisticated tools that
use reasonably complex
calculations in the background
and have a really
great user interface.
And the browser is portable.
So 20 years ago I
gave you software
to download on your
computer to do this stuff.
The landmine that was.
Everybody's environment
was a little different.
Oh, you don't have the latest
version of that library?
Well, you can't run this.
But if you update your
library, you can't run that.
It was really a nightmare.
So packaging things--
packaging up these lab
experiences in a way
that they can be used
by people around the world.
So here I was.
I was riding on the
Hong Kong subway.
And some young adult
comes up to me and says,
I took your MITx course.
SARAH HANSEN: Really?
CHRISTOPHER TERMAN: And I really
loved doing the circuit stuff.
And I didn't have to
download anything.
And I'm sort of going, wow.
I mean, this is--
SARAH HANSEN: It's incredible.
CHRISTOPHER TERMAN: It is.
It's interesting to
be stopped by people.
SARAH HANSEN: Right.
CHRISTOPHER TERMAN:
And they start
talking about how this was
more than just a listening
experience.
So these virtual labs actually
go from being something that--
I mean, it takes courses
from being a listening
experience with maybe some
pencil P-sets to your hands
are active.
So hands-on, brain on, right?
And when people's brains
turn on, it's amazing what--
they remember it.
SARAH HANSEN: Right.
So what kind of
challenges do students
encounter when they're trying
their hand at being engineers
for the first time?
Is there anything that tends
to pop up again and again?
CHRISTOPHER TERMAN: So
I think a lot of this
is sort of competence.
So people sometimes-- the
students come to me, and say,
I want to make this work.
And I say, OK, let me
look at your design.
Let's fix it.
And I go through.
And I try to keep my
hands in my pockets
and let them do the fixing.
But I say, have you
thought about this?
If this works and that doesn't,
what does that tell you?
So a lot of students
aren't very good at taking
the information they
do know and using
it to deduce the
next thing to try
or the next thing to
test and to narrow down
where the problem is.
So there's a real--
there's a learning--
something you have to learn how
to do is to be organized about
how taking something
that isn't working--
or complicated things, so
parts of it are working,
but something isn't.
And trying to work
back from both
ends to somewhere in the
middle that doesn't work.
And so that's a skill that you
have to practice for a while.
And we try to help
with that skill.
I have a lot of
confidence that will work.
Most students are pretty
convinced that either
the simulator is
broken or is hopeless.
And so they're
somewhat surprised
to realize that there
is a systematic way
to make something that works.
And once they are convinced
that that's actually true,
they are getting more confident
that, oh, it doesn't work now,
but I'll just work on it for 10
minutes, and I'm sure it will.
As opposed to just saying,
oh, the only thing I can do
is to raise my hand and
say, could you help me?
Because it isn't working.
So we try to get
the students out
of, look, your job is to
actually make it work,
not to merely ask us to come
over and watch us make it work.
SARAH HANSEN: Right.
CHRISTOPHER TERMAN: And so
students make that transition
through the course.
SARAH HANSEN: So it seems--
CHRISTOPHER TERMAN: The
course of the course.
SARAH HANSEN: Right.
So it seems like a
learning goal in the course
is not only learning
the architecture
of digital systems,
but also developing
professional competencies
in the sense of attitudes
that engineers embrace.
CHRISTOPHER TERMAN: Right.
There's a bunch of processes
that you have to go through.
SARAH HANSEN: Processes.
CHRISTOPHER TERMAN: And the same
thing is true of all learning.
Learning how to
learn is something
that sophomores are still doing.
And so this is
probably the first time
that they've been sort of
thrown into the deep end.
We try to have lots of
lifeguards standing by.
But we're prepared
to do more than just
check off on our
clipboard, sink or swim.
I mean, we're ready to dive
in, and say, OK, try this.
Try that.
It's actually pretty helpful
to have an experience like this
after your freshman year, which
has a lot of training wheels,
but before your
upper level classes
where help is a little thin.
SARAH HANSEN: Right.
CHRISTOPHER TERMAN: One of the
great things about 004 is that
half the people on your
hall have taken this course.
And so even though we
have our core staff,
you can go down your
hall, and as I say,
every other person will
say, oh, I took the course.
So there's actually
an enormous body
of knowledge about the
material and things like that.
So not many courses
have that opportunity,
but we take great
advantage of it.
So there's a lot of sort
of hallway learning,
peer learning that
happens outside
of the sort of
structured learning
that we do in the class.
SARAH HANSEN:
That's fascinating.
It kind of speaks
to the importance
of having common
learning experiences
at the undergraduate
level just to facilitate
that sort of, like you
said, hallway learning.
It's really interesting.
CHRISTOPHER TERMAN: Well,
plus students often--
during the day, it's hectic.
SARAH HANSEN: Yes.
CHRISTOPHER TERMAN:
They're distracted.
They come to lecture.
They have lots of
things on their minds.
So mostly it's being in
the quiet of their room
that they probably
intellectually really
grapple with the material.
So first of all, giving them
things to grapple with is good,
but then making sure they're
supported, either through peers
or through the Piazza forum.
When they're outside of the sort
of structured help we provide.
SARAH HANSEN: Right.
CHRISTOPHER TERMAN:
It's really, I
think, changed how the
students consume the course.
And so the lecture
attendance is modest.
But a lot of people do very
well on learning the material
on the assessments.
SARAH HANSEN: Right.
I mean, I think
that speaks to what
you talked about earlier in
that you offer a buffet of ways
to learn.
And so people who
come to the lectures
are the people who learn
best through that format.
CHRISTOPHER TERMAN: Right.
And some people I never see
except occasionally they'll
come when I have lab hours.
They'll come by, because they
just want to chit chat, right?
SARAH HANSEN: Right.
CHRISTOPHER TERMAN: We have--
one of the activities you
do after you do the design,
we have a check-off.
So you have to come and
sort of explain your design.
Partly that's just to make
sure that maybe you actually
did the design instead of
your friend down the hall.
SARAH HANSEN: I see.
CHRISTOPHER TERMAN: And
so at the very least
we want them to
understand the design
that they claim they have done.
SARAH HANSEN: Right.
CHRISTOPHER TERMAN:
But for people
who have worked hard
on it, it's an opp--
they love to come
by and show it off.
And so they're proud
of their baby, right?
I mean, particularly
towards the end
of the course when we have
a fairly complex design
project, which is actually very
hard to get very high marks on.
I mean, you have to be
really good to get it.
And so it's an amazing number
of people who tackle that.
And they come in.
And they say, OK,
I'm stuck here.
Give me some ideas
what to try next.
And if you dare try to
say, well, just do this.
I don't want the answer.
I want you to--
I'm having fun here.
So don't take away the fun part.
I want to puzzle it out myself.
I just need some
hints as to where
my puzzler should be focusing.
SARAH HANSEN: The
fun is in the puzzle.
CHRISTOPHER TERMAN: It is.
It is, and the doing of it.
SARAH HANSEN: And
the doing of it.
CHRISTOPHER TERMAN: And
I think that's great,
because when
students first come,
they tend to be
focusing on the answers.
Here you gave me a bunch of--
a worksheet full of questions.
So I looked at the answers.
I think I'm good to go.
I say, no, the worksheets aren't
because we want you to know
the answers to those questions.
The worksheets are
to help you diagnose
whether you understand things.
So the best thing that can
happen with the worksheet
is I don't know how
to do this problem.
And so I should go
figure out how to do it.
So if you're doing this
self-paced mastery learning
shtick, which is sort of
how we try to help students
master the material at their
own pace, whenever they want to.
So we have to provide a
lot of self-assessments.
They have to use them
as assessments, though.
SARAH HANSEN: Right.
CHRISTOPHER TERMAN:
They don't use them
as assessments if
they're just saying,
oh, the answer's three
to this question,
and I hope they ask
this one on the quiz.
They're not getting it.
SARAH HANSEN: Right.
CHRISTOPHER TERMAN:
Getting students
to stop focusing on
the answers and really
focus on, how do I tackle
this sort of problem?
SARAH HANSEN: Right.
CHRISTOPHER TERMAN: Of all
the things I know how to do,
I first have to select the
appropriate concept or skill,
and then I have to
know how to apply it.
It's sort of neat to watch them
make the transition from coming
in as sort of answer focused to
leaving sort of like, OK, you
can ask me anything,
because I actually
know how to do
things from scratch,
not because I just
could pick something.
I can not only recognize the
right answer when I see it.
I can actually
make right answers.
That's a very--
people feel empowered
when they can do that.
SARAH HANSEN: Let's talk
a bit about the future.
It seems like the courses
is finely tuned already.
But do you have
ideas for how you
might tweak it in the future?
CHRISTOPHER TERMAN: Well,
I'm retiring in two weeks.
SARAH HANSEN: Oh, so not you.
CHRISTOPHER TERMAN: So
it's being turned over
to a new team.
Some of the people who were
part of the teaching cadre
earlier are taking it over.
They, of course, have
their own strong opinions
about better ways
of doing things.
So I think that the basic
structure of the course
will be the same, the basic list
of topics that will be taught.
But they have a different sort
of design experience in mind.
So they'll find their own way.
It's interesting to
me because I think
until you've taught
a 300-person course,
you may not appreciate how
things which work really
well with two students
in your office
or 10 students in a
recitation doesn't really
work for 300 students.
You suddenly say, well,
they'll ask a question
if they have one.
So I don't need to
be too specific.
It's sort of interesting to
say, whoa, 300 questions.
That's a lot of questions.
And three of them
from every student.
So I have 1,000
questions this week.
And so you start learning
how carefully the materials
have to be prepared.
In one of the
questions you sent me,
you talked about
engineering the materials.
And a big class has a real
issue with engineering materials
that will help get
students to do the things
you want them to do, but
you can't leave them adrift,
because you only
have so much capacity
to pull them all back to shore.
And so you really have
to put most of what
they need into the materials.
SARAH HANSEN: Right.
Can you say more about
engineering the materials
to keep everyone afloat?
CHRISTOPHER TERMAN: Well, so
it's an iterative process.
I mean, people say, oh,
004, it runs like clockwork.
This is the best organized
course I've ever had.
And I say, well, 20 years ago
you wouldn't have said that.
We've had our share of
unfortunate assignments,
or undoable assignments,
or assignments
that were just too hard for
some students, or too easy
for everybody.
And so yes, we do that.
We try to get student feedback.
The forum is actually
great for that.
You get instant feedback on--
this sucked.
And you're going, OK, OK.
And so if you're
good, you make notes.
SARAH HANSEN: OK.
CHRISTOPHER TERMAN: I think
I've taught this course--
I don't know--
30 semesters.
SARAH HANSEN: Wow.
CHRISTOPHER TERMAN: So that
gives you a lot of opportunity
to think--
reflect at the end of
each semester about what
went right, what went wrong.
With a good staff, they're
usually on top of it.
Oh, we've got to change this,
or I spent too much time
helping students with this.
And even in real-time
we'll add a paragraph
to the assignment saying, oh,
a little bit more explanation,
or a hint.
SARAH HANSEN: Right.
CHRISTOPHER TERMAN: So a
willingness to sort of--
and think of building
the materials
as a continuous process.
And after a while, most of
the potholes are filled in,
and the drive is pretty smooth.
SARAH HANSEN: Right.
CHRISTOPHER TERMAN:
And sometimes
the unexpected problem
is actually a doorway
actually into a whole new thing.
We have some students that
say, I thought about this,
and I tried doing it this way.
And I'm going, whoa, what
a great insight that is.
And so we want all the students
to have that opportunity.
So now we're going
to figure out how
to build that into
the design problem
so that everybody has an
opportunity to go aha.
And it was really
neat that the students
were able to come up
with that themselves.
But that gives you a viewpoint.
It gives you an opportunity
to understand how students
are seeing what you're asking.
They misunderstood, so they
answered a different question.
And it turns out that
different question was at least
as interesting, or maybe even
better than the one you asked.
And so then you start one
of these virtual cycles.
Then slowly you
build up stuff where
you end up with questions
that are really--
they don't look like
there's much to them,
but there's been
a lot of evolution
behind asking it just this way.
SARAH HANSEN: Interesting.
CHRISTOPHER TERMAN:
And just this order.
So it's been fun to go
through that experience,
and often surprising.
And we go, oh, I
thought it was so clear.