The Beta is an example of
a reduced-instruction-set
computer (RISC) architecture.
“Reduced” refers to the
fact that in the Beta ISA,
most instructions only
access the internal registers
for their operands
and destination.
Memory values are
loaded and stored
using separate memory-access
instructions, which
implement only a simple
address calculation.
These reductions
lead to smaller,
higher-performance hardware
implementations and simpler
compilers on the software side.
The ARM and MIPS ISAs are other
examples of RISC architectures.
Intel’s x86 ISA is more complex.
There is a limited amount of
storage inside of the CPU —
using the language
of sequential logic,
we’ll refer to this
as the CPU state.
There’s a 32-bit program counter
(PC for short) that holds
the address of the current
instruction in main memory.
And there are
thirty-two registers,
numbered 0 through 31.
Each register holds
a 32-bit value.
We’ll use use 5-bit fields
in the instruction to specify
the number of the register to be
used an operand or destination.
As shorthand, we’ll refer to a
register using the prefix “R”
followed by its number, e.g.,
“R0” refers to the register
selected by the
5-bit field 0b00000.
Register 31 (R31) is special
— its value always reads as 0
and writes to R31 have
no affect on its value.
The number of bits
in each register
and hence the number of bits
supported by ALU operations
is a fundamental
parameter of the ISA.
The Beta is a
32-bit architecture.
Many modern computers
are 64-bit architectures,
meaning they have
64-bit registers
and a 64-bit datapath.
Main memory is an
array of 32-bit words.
Each word contains
four 8-bit bytes.
The bytes are
numbered 0 through 3,
with byte 0 corresponding
to the low-order 7 bits
of the 32-bit value, and so on.
The Beta ISA only
supports word accesses,
either loading or storing
full 32-bit words.
Most “real” computers also
support accesses to bytes
and half-words.
Even though the Beta only
accesses full words, following
a convention used by many
ISAs it uses byte addresses.
Since there are 4
bytes in each word,
consecutive words in memory
have addresses that differ by 4.
So the first word in
memory has address 0,
the second word
address 4, and so on.
You can see the addresses to
left of each memory location
in the diagram shown here.
Note that we’ll usually use
hexadecimal notation when
specifying addresses and other
binary values — the “0x” prefix
indicates when a
number is in hex.
When drawing a memory diagram,
we’ll follow the convention
that addresses increase as
you read from top to bottom.
The Beta ISA supports
32-bit byte addressing,
so an address fits exactly into
one 32-bit register or memory
location.
The maximum memory size is 2^32
bytes or 2^30 words — that’s 4
gigabytes (4 GB) or one
billion words of main memory.
Some Beta implementations
might actually
have a smaller
main memory, i.e.,
one with fewer than
1 billion locations.
Why have separate
registers and main memory?
Well, modern programs and
datasets are very large,
so we’ll want to have a large
main memory to hold everything.
But large memories are slow
and usually only support access
to one location at a time, so
they don’t make good storage
for use in each instruction
which needs to access several
operands and store a result.
If we used only one
large storage array,
then an instruction would need
to have three 32-bit addresses
to specify the two source
operands and destination — each
instruction encoding
would be huge!
And the required memory
accesses would have to be
one-after-the-other, really
slowing down instruction
execution.
On the other hand, if we use
registers to hold the operands
and serve as the
destination, we can
design the register
hardware for parallel access
and make it very fast.
To keep the speed up we won’t
be able to have very many
registers — a classic
size-vs-speed performance
tradeoff we see in digital
systems all the time.
In the end, the tradeoff
leading to the best performance
is to have a small number
of very fast registers used
by most instructions and a
large but slow main memory.
So that’s what
the BETA ISA does.
In general, all program data
will reside in main memory.
Each variable used by the
program “lives” in a specific
main memory location and so
has a specific memory address.
For example, in
the diagram below,
the value of variable “x”
is stored in memory location
0x1008, and the value of “y”
0x100C, and so on.
To perform a computation,
e.g., to compute x*37 and store
the result in y, we would have
to first load the value of x
into a register, say, R0.
Then we would have the datapath
multiply the value in R0
by 37, storing the
result back into R0.
Here we’ve assumed that
the constant 37 is somehow
available to the datapath
and doesn’t itself need to be
loaded from memory.
Finally, we would
write the updated value
in R0 back into memory
at the location for y.
Whew!
A lot of steps…
Of course, we
could avoid all the
loading and storing if we chose
to keep the values for x and y
in registers.
Since there are
only 32 registers,
we can’t do this for
all of our variables,
but maybe we could arrange to
load x and y into registers,
do all the required computations
involving x and y by referring
to those registers, and
then, when we’re done,
store changes to x and y back
into memory for later use.
Optimizing performance by
keeping often-used values
in registers is a favorite trick
of programmers and compiler
writers.
So the basic program
template is some loads
to bring values into
the registers, followed
by computation, followed
by any necessary stores.
ISAs that use this template
are usually referred
to as “load-store
architectures”.