So, how can the memory system
arrange for the right data
to be in the right
place at the right time?
Our goal is to have the
frequently-used data
in some fast SRAM.
That means the
memory system will
have to be able to predict
which memory locations will
be accessed.
And to keep the overhead
of moving data into and out
of SRAM manageable, we’d like
to amortize the cost of the move
over many accesses.
In other words we
want any block of data
we move into SRAM to
be accessed many times.
When not in SRAM, data would
live in the larger, slower DRAM
that serves as main memory.
If the system is
working as planned,
DRAM accesses would
happen infrequently, e.g.,
only when it’s time to
bring another block of data
into SRAM.
If we look at how
programs access memory,
it turns out we *can* make
accurate predictions about
which memory locations
will be accessed.
The guiding principle is
“locality of reference” which
tells us that if there’s an
access to address X at time t,
it’s very probable that the
program will access a nearby
location in the near future.
To understand why programs
exhibit locality of reference,
let’s look at how a running
program accesses memory.
Instruction fetches
are quite predictable.
Execution usually
proceeds sequentially
since most of the time
the next instruction is
fetched from the
location after that
of the current instruction.
Code that loops will
repeatedly fetch
the same sequence
of instructions, as
shown here on the
left of the time line.
There will of course be branches
and subroutine calls that
interrupt sequential execution,
but then we’re back to fetching
instructions from
consecutive locations.
Some programming
constructs, e.g.,
method dispatch in
object-oriented languages,
can produce scattered references
to very short code sequences
(as shown on the right
of the time line)
but order is quickly restored.
This agrees with our intuition
about program execution.
For example, once we execute
the first instruction
of a procedure, we’ll almost
certainly execute the remaining
instructions in the procedure.
So if we arranged for all the
code of a procedure to moved
to SRAM when the procedure’s
first instruction was fetched,
we’d expect that many subsequent
instruction fetches could be
satisfied by the SRAM.
And although fetching the first
word of a block from DRAM has
relatively long latency, the
DRAM’s fast column accesses
will quickly stream the
remaining words from sequential
addresses.
This will amortize the
cost of the initial access
over the whole
sequence of transfers.
The story is
similar for accesses
by a procedure to its
arguments and local variables
in the current stack frame.
Again there will be many
accesses to a small region
of memory during the span
of time we’re executing
the procedure’s code.
Data accesses generated by
LD and ST instructions also
exhibit locality.
The program may be accessing
the components of an object
or struct.
Or it may be stepping through
the elements of an array.
Sometimes information
is moved from one array
or data object to another,
as shown by the data
accesses on the right
of the timeline.
Using simulations we
can estimate the number
of different locations
that will be accessed
over a particular span of time.
What we discover when we do
this is the notion of a “working
set” of locations that
are accessed repeatedly.
If we plot the
size of the working
set as a function of the
size of the time interval,
we see that the size of
the working set levels off.
In other words once the time
interval reaches a certain size
the number of
locations accessed is
approximately the
same independent
of when in time the
interval occurs.
As we see in our
plot to the left,
the actual addresses
accessed will change,
but the number of *different*
addresses during the time
interval will, on the average,
remain relatively constant
and, surprisingly,
not all that large!
This means that if we
can arrange for our SRAM
to be large enough to hold the
working set of the program,
most accesses will be able
to be satisfied by the SRAM.
We’ll occasionally have to move
new data into the SRAM and old
data back to DRAM, but the
DRAM access will occur less
frequently than SRAM accesses.
We’ll work out the
mathematics in a slide or two,
but you can see that thanks
to locality of reference we’re
on track to build a memory
out of a combination of SRAM
and DRAM that performs like
an SRAM but has the capacity
of the DRAM.
The SRAM component of our
hierarchical memory system is
called a “cache”.
It provides low-latency access
to recently-accessed blocks
of data.
If the requested
data is in the cache,
we have a “cache hit” and the
data is supplied by the SRAM.
If the requested data
is not in the cache,
we have a “cache miss” and
a block of data containing
the requested location will
have to be moved from DRAM
into the cache.
The locality principle
tells us that we
should expect cache
hits to occur much more
frequently than cache misses.
Modern computer systems
often use multiple levels
of SRAM caches.
The levels closest to the CPU
are smaller but very fast,
while the levels further
away from the CPU
are larger and hence slower.
A miss at one level of the
cache generates an access
to the next level, and so on
until a DRAM access is needed
to satisfy the initial request.
Caching is used in
many applications
to speed up accesses to
frequently-accessed data.
For example, your
browser maintains
a cache of
frequently-accessed web pages
and uses its local
copy of the web page
if it determines the
data is still valid,
avoiding the delay
of transferring
the data over the Internet.
Here’s an example memory
hierarchy that might be found
on a modern computer.
There are three levels
on-chip SRAM caches,
followed by DRAM main memory
and a flash-memory cache
for the hard disk drive.
The compiler is
responsible for deciding
which data values are
kept in the CPU registers
and which values require
the use of LDs and STs.
The 3-level cache
and accesses to DRAM
are managed by circuity
in the memory system.
After that the access
times are long enough
(many hundreds of
instruction times)
that the job of managing
the movement of data
between the lower
levels of the hierarchy
is turned over to software.
Today we’re discussing how
the on-chip caches work.
In Part 3 of the course,
we’ll discuss how the software
manages main memory and
non-volatile storage devices.
Whether managed by
hardware or software,
each layer of the
memory system is
designed to provide
lower-latency access
to frequently-accessed locations
in the next, slower layer.
But, as we’ll see, the
implementation strategies will
be quite different in the
slower layers of the hierarchy.