Let's look at a concrete example.
This graph shows the voltage transfer characteristic
for a particular device and we're wondering
if we can use this device as a combinational
inverter.
In other words, can we pick values for the
voltage thresholds V_OL, V_IL, V_IH and V_OH
so that the shown VTC meets the constraints
imposed on a combinational device?
An inverter outputs a digital 1 when its input
is a digital 0 and vice versa.
In fact this device does produce a high output
voltage when its input voltage is low, so
there's a chance that this will work out.
The lowest output voltage produced by the
device is 0.5V, so if the device is to produce
a legal digital output of 0, we have to choose
V_OL to be at least 0.5V.
We want the inverter to produce a valid digital
0 whenever its input is valid digital 1.
Looking at the VTC, we see that if the input
is higher than 3V, the output will be less
than or equal to V_OL, so let's set V_IH to
3V.
We could set it to a higher value than 3V,
but we'll make it as low as possible to leave
room for a generous high noise margin.
That takes care of two of the four signal
thresholds, V_OL and V_IH.
The other two thresholds are related to these
two by the noise margin N as shown by these
two equations.
Can we find a value for N such that V_OUT
>= V_OH when V_IN <= V_IL?
If we chose N = 0.5V, then the formulas tell
us that V_IL = 1V and V_OH = 3.5V.
Plotting these thresholds on the graph and
adding the forbidden regions, we see that
happily the VTC is, in fact, legal!
So we can use this device as a combinational
inverter if we use the signaling specification
with V_OL = 0.5V, V_IL = 1V, V_IH = 3V and
V_OH = 3.5V.
We're good to go!