Here's a failed attempt at pipelining a circuit.
For what value of K is the circuit a K-pipeline?
Well, let's count the number of registers
along each path from system inputs to system
outputs.
The top path through the A and C components
has 2 registers.
As does the bottom path through the B and
C components.
But the middle path through all three components
has only 1 register.
Oops, this not a well-formed K-pipeline.
Why do we care?
We care because this pipelined circuit does
not compute the same answer as the original
unpipelined circuit.
The problem is that successive generations
of inputs get mixed together during processing.
For example, during cycle i+1, the B module
is computing with the current value of the
X input but the previous value of the Y input.
This can't happen with a well-formed K-pipeline.
So we need to develop a technique for pipelining
a circuit that guarantees the result will
be well-formed.
Here's our strategy that will ensure if we
add a pipeline register along one path from
system inputs to system outputs, we will add
pipeline registers along every path.
Step 1 is to draw a contour line that crosses
every output in the circuit and mark its endpoints
as the terminal points for all the other contours
we'll add.
During Step 2 continue to draw contour lines
between the two terminal points across the
signal connections between modules.
Make sure that every signal connection crosses
the new contour line in the same direction.
This means that system inputs will be one
side of the contour and system outputs will
be on the other side.
These contours demarcate pipeline stages.
Place a pipeline register wherever a signal
connection intersects the pipelining contours.
Here we've marked the location of pipeline
registers with large black dots.
By drawing the contours from terminal point
to terminal point we guarantee that we cross
every input-output path, thus ensuring our
pipeline will be well-formed.
Now we can compute the system's clock period
by looking for the pipeline stage with the
longest register-to-register or input-to-register
propagation delay.
With these contours and assuming ideal zero-delay
pipeline registers, the system clock must
have a period of 8 ns to accommodate the operation
of the C module.
This gives a system throughput of 1 output
every 8 ns.
Since we drew 3 contours, this is a 3-pipeline
and the system latency is 3 times 8 ns or
24 ns total.
Our usual goal in pipelining a circuit is
to achieve maximum throughput using the fewest
possible registers.
So our strategy is to find the slowest system
component (in our example, the C component)
and place pipeline registers on its inputs
and outputs.
So we drew contours that pass on either side
of the C module.
This sets the clock period at 8 ns, so we
position the contours so that longest path
between any two pipeline registers is at most
8.
There are often several choices for how to
draw a contour while maintaining the same
throughput and latency.
For example, we could have included the E
module in the same pipeline stage as the F
module.
Okay, let's review our pipelining strategy.
First we draw a contour across all the outputs.
This creates a 1-pipeline, which, as you can
see, will always have the same throughput
and latency as the original combinational
circuit.
Then we draw our next contour, trying to isolate
the slowest component in the system.
This creates a 2-pipeline with a clock period
of 2 and hence a throughput of 1/2, or double
that of the 1-pipeline.
We can add additional contours, but note that
the 2-pipeline had the smallest possible clock
period, so after that additional contours
add stages and hence increase the system's
latency without increasing its throughput.
Not illegal, just not a worthwhile investment
in hardware.
Note that the signal connection between the
A and C module now has two back-to-back pipelining
registers.
Nothing wrong with that; it often happens
when we pipeline a circuit where the input-output
paths are of different lengths.
So our pipelining strategy will be to pipeline
implementations with increased throughput,
usually at the cost of increased latency.
Sometimes we get lucky and the delays of each
pipeline stage are perfectly balanced, in
which case the latency will not increase.
Note that a pipelined circuit will NEVER have
a smaller latency than the unpipelined circuit.
Notice that once we've isolated the slowest
component, we can't increase the throughput
any further.
How do we continue to improve the performance
of circuits in light of these performance
bottlenecks?
One solution is to use pipelined components
if they're available!
Suppose we're able to replace the original
A component with a 2-stage pipelined version
A-prime.
We can redraw our pipelining contours, making
sure we account for the internal pipeline
registers in the A-prime component.
This means that 2 of our contours have to
pass through the A-prime component, guaranteeing
that we'll add pipeline registers elsewhere
in the system that will account for the two-cycle
delay introduced by A-prime.
Now the maximum propagation delay in any stage
is 1 ns, doubling the throughput from 1/2
to 1/1.
This is a 4-pipeline so the latency will be
4 ns.
This is great!
But what can we do if our bottleneck component
doesn't have a pipelined substitute.
We'll tackle that question in the next section.