Here's a final logic implementation strategy
using read-only memories.
This strategy is useful when you need to generate
many different outputs from the same set of
inputs, a situation we'll see a lot when we
get to finite state machines later on in the
course.
Where MUXes are good for implementing truth
tables with one output column, read-only memories
are good for implementing truth tables with
many output columns.
One of the key components in a read-only memory
is the decoder which has K select inputs and
2^K data outputs.
Only one of the data outputs will be 1 (or
HIGH) at any given time, which one is determined
by the value on the select inputs.
The Jth output will be 1 when the select lines
are set to the binary representation of J.
Here's a read-only memory implementation for
the 2-output truth table shown on the left.
This particular 2-output device is a full
adder, which is used as a building block in
addition circuits.
The three inputs to the function (A, B, and
CI) are connected to the select lines of a
3-to-8 decoder.
The 8 outputs of the decoder run horizontally
in the schematic diagram and each is labeled
with the input values for which that output
will be HIGH.
So when the inputs are 000, the top decoder
output will be HIGH and all the other decoder
outputs LOW.
When the inputs are 001 - i.e., when A and
B are 0 and CI is 1 - the second decoder output
will be HIGH.
And so on.
The decoder outputs control a matrix of NFET
pulldown switches.
The matrix has one vertical column for each
output of the truth table.
Each switch connects a particular vertical
column to ground, forcing it to a LOW value
when the switch is on.
The column circuitry is designed so that if
no pulldown switches force its value to 0,
its value will be a 1.
The value on each of the vertical columns
is inverted to produce the final output values.
So how do we use all this circuitry to implement
the function described by the truth table?
For any particular combination of input values,
exactly one of the decoder outputs will be
HIGH, all the others will be low.
Think of the decoder outputs as indicating
which row of the truth table has been selected
by the input values.
All of the pulldown switches controlled by
the HIGH decoder output will be turned ON,
forcing the vertical column to which they
connect LOW.
For example, if the inputs are 001, the decoder
output labeled 001 will be HIGH.
This will turn on the circled pulldown switch,
forcing the S vertical column LOW.
The COUT vertical column is not pulled down,
so it will be HIGH.
After the output inverters, S will be 1 and
COUT will be 0, the desired output values.
By changing the locations of the pulldown
switches, this read-only memory can be programmed
to implement any 3-input, 2-output function.
For read-only memories with many inputs, the
decoders have many outputs and the vertical
columns in the switch matrix can become quite
long and slow.
We can reconfigure the circuit slightly so
that some of the inputs control the decoder
and the other inputs are used to select among
multiple shorter and faster vertical columns.
This combination of smaller decoders and output
MUXes is quite common in these sorts of memory
circuits.
Read-only memories, ROMs for short, are an
implementation strategy that ignores the structure
of the particular boolean expression to be
implemented.
The ROM's size and overall layout are determined
only by the number of inputs and outputs.
Typically the switch matrix is fully populated,
with all possible switch locations filled
with an NFET pulldown.
A separate physical or electrical programming
operation determines which switches are actually
controlled by the decoder lines.
The other switches are configured to be in
the permanently off state.
If the ROM has N inputs and M outputs, then
the switch matrix will have 2^N rows and M
output columns, corresponding exactly to the
size of the truth table.
As the inputs to the ROM change, various decoder
outputs will turn off and on, but at slightly
different times.
As the decoder lines cycle, the output values
may change several times until the final configuration
of the pulldown switches is stable.
So ROMs are not lenient and the outputs may
show the glitchy behavior discussed earlier.
Whew!
This has been a whirlwind tour of various
circuits we can use to implement logic functions.
The sum-of-products approach lends itself
nicely to implementation with inverting logic.
Each circuit is custom-designed to implement
a particular function and as such can be made
both fast and small.
The design and manufacturing expense of creating
such circuits is worthwhile when you need
high-end performance or are producing millions
of devices.
MUX and ROM circuit implementations are mostly
independent of the specific function to be
implemented.
That's determined by a separate programming
step, which may be completed after the manufacture
of the devices.
They are particularly suited for prototyping,
low-volume production, or devices where the
functionality may need to be updated after
the device is out in the field.