If the necessary synchronization requires
acquiring more than one lock, there are some
special considerations that need to be taken
into account.
For example, the code below implements the
transfer of funds from one bank account to
another.
The code assumes there is a separate semaphore
lock for each account and since it needs to
adjust the balance of two accounts, it acquires
the lock for each account.
Consider what happens if two customers try
simultaneous transfers between their two accounts.
The top customer will try to acquire the locks
for accounts 6005 and 6004.
The bottom customer tries to acquire the same
locks, but in the opposite order.
Once a customer has acquired both locks, the
transfer code will complete, releasing the
locks.
But what happens if the top customer acquires
his first lock (for account 6005) and the
bottom customer simultaneously acquires his
first lock (for account 6004).
So far, so good, but now each customer will
be not be successful in acquiring their second
lock, since those locks are already held by
the other customer!
This situation is called a "deadlock" or "deadly
embrace" because there is no way execution
for either process will resume.
Both will wait indefinitely to acquire a lock
that will never be available.
Obviously, synchronization involving multiple
resources requires a bit more thought.
The problem of deadlock is elegantly illustrated
by the Dining Philosophers problem.
Here there are, say, 5 philosophers waiting
to eat.
Each requires two chopsticks in order to proceed,
and there are 5 chopsticks on the table.
The philosophers follow a simple algorithm.
First they pick up the chopstick on their
left, then the chopstick on their right.
When they have both chopsticks they eat until
they're done, at which point they return both
chopsticks to the table, perhaps enabling
one of their neighbors to pick them up and
begin eating.
Again, we see the basic setup of needing two
(or more) resources before the task can complete.
Hopefully you can see the problem that may
arise
If all philosophers pick up the chopstick
on their left, then all the chopsticks have
been acquired, and none of the philosophers
will be able to acquire their second chopstick
and eat.
Another deadlock!
Here are the conditions required for a deadlock:
1.
Mutual exclusion, where a particular resource
can only be acquired by one process at a time.
2.
Hold-and-wait, where a process holds allocated
resources while waiting to acquire the next
resource.
3.
No preemption, where a resource cannot be
removed from the process which acquired it.
Resources are only released after the process
has completed its transaction.
4.
Circular wait, where resources needed by one
process are held by another, and vice versa.
How can we solve the problem of deadlocks
when acquiring multiple resources?
Either we avoid the problem to begin with,
or we detect that deadlock has occurred and
implement a recovery strategy.
Both techniques are used in practice.
In the Dining Philosophers problem, deadlock
can be avoided with a small modification to
the algorithm.
We start by assigning a unique number to each
chopstick to establish a global ordering of
all the resources,
then rewrite the code to acquire resources
using the global ordering to determine which
resource to acquire first, which second, and
so on.
With the chopsticks numbered, the philosophers
pick up the lowest-numbered chopstick from
either their left or right.
Then they pick up the other, higher-numbered
chopstick, eat, and then return the chopsticks
to the table.
How does this avoid deadlock?
Deadlock happens when all the chopsticks have
been picked up but no philosopher can eat.
If all the chopsticks have been been picked
up, that means some philosopher has picked
up the highest-numbered chopstick and so must
have earlier picked up the lower-numbered
chopstick on his other side.
So that philosopher can eat then return both
chopsticks to the table, breaking the hold-and-wait
cycle.
So if all the processes in the system can
agree upon a global ordering for the resources
they require, then acquire them in order,
there will be no possibility of a deadlock
caused by a hold-and-wait cycle.
A global ordering is easy to arrange in our
banking code for the transfer transaction.
We'll modify the code to first acquire the
lock for the lower-numbered account, then
acquire the lock for the higher-numbered account.
Now, both customers will first try to acquire
the lock for the 6004 account.
The customer that succeeds then can acquire
the lock for the 6005 account and complete
the transaction.
The key to deadlock avoidance was that customers
contented for the lock for the *first* resource
they both needed.
Acquiring that lock ensured they would be
able to acquire the remainder of the shared
resources without fear that they would already
be allocated to another process in a way that
could cause a hold-and-wait cycle.
Establishing and using a global order for
shared resources is possible when we can modify
all processes to cooperate.
Avoiding deadlock without changing the processes
is a harder problem.
For example, at the operating system level,
it would be possible to modify the WAIT SVC
to detect circular wait and terminate one
of the WAITing processes, releasing its resources
and breaking the deadlock.
The other strategy we mentioned was detection
and recovery.
Database systems detect when there's been
an external access to the shared data used
by a particular transaction, which causes
the database to abort the transaction.
When issuing a transaction to a database,
the programmer specifies what should happen
if the transaction is aborted, e.g., she can
specify that the transaction be retried.
The database remembers all the changes to
shared data that happen during a transaction
and only changes the master copy of the shared
data when it is sure that the transaction
will not be aborted,
at which point the changes are committed to
the database.
In summary, we saw that organizing an application
as communicating processes is often a convenient
way to go.
We used semaphores to synchronize the execution
of the different processes, providing guarantees
that certain precedence constraints would
be met, even between statements in different
processes.
We also introduced the notion of critical
code sections and mutual exclusion constraints
that guaranteed that a code sequence would
be executed without interruption by another
process.
We saw that semaphores could also be used
to implement those mutual exclusion constraints.
Finally we discussed the problem of deadlock
that can occur when multiple processes must
acquire multiple shared resources,
and we proposed several solutions based on
a global ordering of resources or the ability
to restart a transaction.
Synchronization primitives play a key role
in the world of "big data" where there are
vast amounts of shared data, or when trying
to coordinate the execution of thousands of
processes in the cloud.
Understanding synchronization issues and their
solutions is a key skill when writing most
modern applications.