We’ll get a good understanding
of how the register operates
as we follow the signals
through the circuit.
The overall operation of
the register is simple:
At the rising 0-to-1
transition of the clock input,
the register samples
the value of the D input
and stores that value until
the next rising clock edge.
The Q output is simply the
value stored in the register.
Let’s see how the register
implements this functionality.
The clock signal is connected
to the gate inputs of the master
and slave latches.
Since all the action
happens when the clock makes
a transition, it’s those
events we’ll focus on.
The clock transition
from LOW to HIGH
is called the rising
edge of the clock.
And its transition from HIGH to
LOW is called the falling edge.
Let’s start by looking the
operation of the master latch
and its output signal, which
is labeled STAR in the diagram.
On the rising edge of
the clock, the master
latch goes from open to closed,
sampling the value on its input
and entering memory mode.
The sampled value thus becomes
the output of the latch
as long as the
latch stays closed.
You can see that the STAR
signal remains stable whenever
the clock signal is high.
On the falling edge of the
clock the master latch opens
and its output will
then reflect any changes
in the D input, delayed
by the tPD of the latch.
Now let’s figure out
what the slave is doing.
It’s output signal, which
also serves as the output of D
register, is shown as
the bottom waveform.
On the rising edge of the
clock the slave latch opens
and its output will follow
the value of the STAR signal.
Remember though that the
STAR signal is stable
while the clock is HIGH since
the master latch is closed,
so the Q signal is also stable
after an initial transition
if value saved in the
slave latch is changing.
At the falling
clock edge [CLICK],,
the slave goes from
open to closed,
sampling the value on its
input and entering memory mode.
The sampled value then becomes
the output of the slave
latch as long as the
latch stays closed.
You can see that that the Q
output remains stable whenever
the clock signal is LOW.
Now let’s just look at the Q
signal by itself for a moment.
It only changes
when the slave latch
opens at the rising
edge of the clock.
The rest of the time either the
input to slave latch is stable
or the slave latch is closed.
The change in the Q output is
triggered by the rising edge
of the clock, hence the name
“positive-edge-triggered D
register”.
The convention for
labeling the clock input
in the schematic icon for
an edge-triggered device
is to use a little triangle.
You can see that here in the
schematic symbol for the D
register.
There is one tricky
problem we have
to solve when designing the
circuitry for the register.
On the falling clock edge,
the slave latch transitions
from open to closed and so
its input (the STAR signal)
must meet the setup and
hold times of the slave
latch in order to ensure
correct operation.
The complication is
that the master latch
opens at the same time, so the
STAR signal may change shortly
after the clock edge.
The contamination delay
of the master latch
tells us how long
the old value will
be stable after the
falling clock edge.
And the hold time
on the slave latch
tells us how long it
has to remain stable
after the falling clock edge.
So to ensure correct
operation of the slave latch,
the contamination delay
of the master latch
has to be greater than or equal
to the hold time of the slave
latch.
Doing the necessary
analysis can be a bit tricky
since we have to consider
manufacturing variations as
well as environmental factors
such as temperature and power
supply voltage.
If necessary, extra
gate delays (e.g.,
pairs of inverters) can be added
between the master and slave
latches to increase
the contamination delay
on the slave’s input relative
to the falling clock edge.
Note that we can only
solve slave latch hold
time issues by changing
the design of the circuit.
Here’s a summary of the
timing specifications for a D
register.
Changes in the Q signal
are triggered by a rising
edge on the clock input.
The propagation delay
t_PD of the register
is an upper bound on the time
it takes for the Q output
to become valid and stable
after the rising clock edge.
The contamination
delay of the register
is a lower bound on the
time the previous value of Q
remains valid after
the rising clock edge.
Note that both t_CD and t_PD are
measured relative to the rising
edge of the clock.
Registers are designed to
be lenient in the sense
that if the previous value
of Q and the new value of Q
are the same, the
stability of the Q signal
is guaranteed during
the rising clock edge.
In other words, the t_CD
and t_PD specifications
only apply when the Q
output actually changes.
In order to ensure correct
operation of the master latch,
the register’s D input must
meet the setup and hold time
constraints for
the master latch.
So the following
two specifications
are determined by the
timing of the master latch.
t_SETUP is the amount
of time that the D input
must be valid and stable
before the rising clock
edge and t_HOLD is
the amount of time
that D must be valid and
stable after the rising clock.
This region of stability
surrounding the clock edge
ensures that we’re obeying
the dynamic discipline
for the master latch.
So when you use a D register
component from a manufacturer’s
gate library,
you’ll need to look up these
four timing specifications
in the register’s data sheet
in order to analyze the timing
of your overall circuit.
We’ll see how this analysis
is done in the next section.