We will now review a problem on
error correction and detection
in order to better
understand how the selected
encoding of a message can
help both detect and correct
transmission errors.
In this problem messages consist
of 9 data bits and 7 parity
bits.
Each Dij represents
a data bit which
belongs to row i and column j.
The Pij bits are used to
make the parity of each row
and column be odd.
The Pxx box, which is in
the bottom right corner,
is used to make the parity
of the entire message odd.
In other words, it makes the
total number of ones be odd.
The first question we
want to ask ourselves
is what is the minimum Hamming
Distance between valid code
words using this encoding?
In order to figure
that out, we need
to think about how many
bits of the encoding
are changed if I want to
change one of the data bits.
The easiest way to see
this is through an example.
Suppose that I want to
change D01 from a 0 to a 1.
The first thing changing
is my data bit itself.
Then P0x would get flipped
because I just added another 1
to my row which means that
I need to flip the parity
bit in order for the total
number of 1's in my row
to remain odd.
The next change is
that Px1 needs to get
flipped in order to maintain
an odd parity in my column.
So far, 3 entries
have changed which
implies that the parity of
the entire message flipped.
In order to keep the parity
of the entire message odd,
Pxx needs to be flipped
as well so that there
are a total of 4
entries being flipped
which will cause the odd
parity of the entire message
to remain unchanged.
This means that our
minimum hamming distance
for this encoding equals 4
because any time we flip a data
bit, a total of 4
entries need to change
to maintain our encoding.
We know that to
detect an E-bit error,
the hamming distance (HD)
has to be greater than E,
or in other words,
the HD >= E + 1.
So to detect a 1-bit
error, one needs a HD >= 2.
We also know that to correct
an E-bit error, the HD > 2E,
or the HD >= 2E + 1.
So to correct a 1-bit error,
one needs to have a HD >= 3.
For this encoding, since our
hamming distance equals 4,
that means we should
be able to both detect
and correct 1-bit errors.
Taking a look at
this message, if we
check the parity of each row,
column, and full message,
we see that in all
cases our parity is odd.
Since odd parity
indicates a valid message,
there are no errors
in this message.
Looking at this message
we see that all the row
parities are odd, but the
parity of column 1 is even.
This means that there
is an error in column 1.
However, since
there were no errors
in the parity of the rows, this
means that the bit in error
is the parity bit itself.
If we flip Px1 from
a 0 to a 1 we now
have a valid message again.
Looking at the parity of each
row and column in this message,
we see that row 0
has an even parity,
and column 0 has an even parity.
This means that the data bit
at row 0, column 0 is wrong.
If we flip this bit, we now see
that all of our row and column
parities are correct, and
our total message parity
is correct as well,
so we have restored
our message by identifying
the bit in error.
In this example, all of the row
parities and column parities
are odd.
However, the parity of the
entire message is even.
This means that the bit
in error in this message
is the Pxx bit itself.
Flipping that bottom right
bit results in a valid message
once again.
Now let's go back to our
original valid message
and see if we can
correct 2-bit errors.
Suppose we flip D11 to 0 and D22
to 1 to create a 2-bit error.
Now when we look at
the parity of each row,
we find that both row 1
and 2 have a parity error.
Similarly, columns 1 and
2 have a parity error.
The total message
parity remains correct.
Given this information, we
know that an error occurred
in the transmission
of this message,
but we cannot identify exactly
which bits are in error
because there is more than one
possible way to alter two bits
and arrive at a valid message.
This demonstrates that we
can detect a 2-bit error,
but we can't correct
a 2-bit error.
Going back to our original
claims about hamming distances,
this is in line with
our expectations.
If E=2, meaning that we want
to detect a 2-bit error,
then the HD >= E+1
which equals 3.
To correct a 2-bit error, the
HD >= 2E+1 which equals 5.
Since our hamming distance
in this problem is 4,
we can only detect 2-bit
errors, but not correct them.