For some applications, data naturally comes
in vector or matrix form.
For example, a vector of digitized samples
representing an audio waveform over time,
or a matrix of pixel colors in a 2D image
from a camera.
When processing that data, it's common to
perform the same sequence of operations on
each data element.
The example code shown here is computing a
vector sum, where each component of one vector
is added to the corresponding component of
another vector.
By replicating the datapath portion of our
CPU, we can design special-purpose vector
processors capable of performing the same
operation on many data elements in parallel.
Here we see that the register file and ALU
have been replicated and the control signals
from decoding the current instruction are
shared by all the datapaths.
Data is fetched from memory in big blocks
(very much like fetching a cache line) and
the specified register in each datapath is
loaded with one of the words from the block.
Similarly each datapath can contribute a word
to be stored as a contiguous block in main
memory.
In such machines, the width of the data buses
to and from main memory is many words wide,
so a single memory access provides data for
all the datapaths in parallel.
Executing a single instruction on a machine
with N datapaths is equivalent to executing
N instructions on a conventional machine with
a single datapath.
The result achieves a lot of parallelism without
the complexities of out-of-order superscalar
execution.
Suppose we had a vector processor with 16
datapaths.
Let's compare its performance on a vector-sum
operation to that of a conventional pipelined
Beta processor.
Here's the Beta code, carefully organized
to avoid any data hazards during execution.
There are 9 instructions in the loop, taking
10 cycles to execute if we count the NOP introduced
into the pipeline when the BNE at the end
of the loop is taken.
It takes 160 cycles to sum all 16 elements
assuming no additional cycles are required
due to cache misses.
And here's the corresponding code for a vector
processor where we've assumed constant-sized
16-element vectors.
Note that "V" registers refer to a particular
location in the register file associated with
each datapath, while the "R" registers are
the conventional Beta registers used for address
computations, etc.
It would only take 4 cycles for the vector
processor to complete the desired operations,
a speed-up of 40.
This example shows the best-possible speed-up.
The key to a good speed-up is our ability
to "vectorize" the code and take advantage
of all the datapaths operating in parallel.
This isn't possible for every application,
but for tasks like audio or video encoding
and decoding, and all sorts of digital signal
processing, vectorization is very doable.
Memory operations enjoy a similar performance
improvement since the access overhead is amortized
over large blocks of data.
You might wonder if it's possible to efficiently
perform data-dependent operations on a vector
processor.
Data-dependent operations appear as conditional
statements on conventional machines, where
the body of the statement is executed if the
condition is true.
If testing and branching is under the control
of the single-instruction execution engine,
how can we take advantage of the parallel
datapaths?
The trick is provide each datapath with a
local predicate flag.
Use a vectorized compare instruction (CMPLT.V)
to perform the a[i] < b[i] comparisons in
parallel and remember the result locally in
each datapath's predicate flag.
Then extend the vector ISA to include "predicated
instructions" which check the local predicate
to see if they should execute or do nothing.
In this example, ADDC.V.iftrue only performs
the ADDC on the local data if the local predicate
flag is true.
Instruction predication is also used in many
non-vector architectures to avoid the execution-time
penalties associated with mis-predicted conditional
branches.
They are particularly useful for simple arithmetic
and boolean operations (i.e., very short instruction
sequences) that should be executed only if
a condition is met.
The x86 ISA includes a conditional move instruction,
and in the 32-bit ARM ISA almost all instructions
can be conditionally executed.
The power of vector processors comes from
having 1 instruction initiate N parallel operations
on N pairs of operands.
Most modern CPUs incorporate vector extensions
that operate in parallel on 8-, 16-, 32- or
64-bit operands organized as blocks of 128-,
256-, or 512-bit data.
Often all that's needed is some simple additional
logic on an ALU designed to process full-width
operands.
The parallelism is baked into the vector program,
not discovered on-the-fly by the instruction
dispatch and execution machinery.
Writing the specialized vector programs is
a worthwhile investment for certain library
functions which see a lot use in processing
today's information streams with their heavy
use of images, and A/V material.
Perhaps the best example of architectures
with many datapaths operating in parallel
are the graphics processing units (GPUs) found
in almost all computer graphics systems.
GPU datapaths are typically specialized for
32- and 64-bit floating point operations found
in the algorithms needed to display in real-time
a 3D scene represented as billions of triangular
patches as a 2D image on the computer screen.
Coordinate transformation, pixel shading and
antialiasing, texture mapping, etc., are examples
of "embarrassingly parallel" computations
where the parallelism comes from having to
perform the same computation independently
on millions of different data objects.
Similar problems can be found in the fields
of bioinformatics, big data processing, neural
net emulation used in deep machine learning,
and so on.
Increasingly, GPUs are used in many interesting
scientific and engineering calculations and
not just as graphics engines.
Data-level parallelism provides significant
performance improvements in a variety of useful
situations.
So current and future ISAs will almost certainly
include support for vector operations.