We're on the home stretch now.
For all the instructions up until now, the
next instruction has come from the location
following the current instruction - hence
the "PC+4" logic.
Branches and JMPs change that by altering
the value in the PC.
The JMP instruction simply takes the value
in the RA register and makes it the next PC
value.
The PCSEL MUX in the upper left-hand corner
lets the control logic select the source of
the next PC value.
When PCSEL is 0, the incremented PC value
is chosen.
When PCSEL is 2, the value of the RA register
We'll see how the other inputs to the PCSEL
MUX are used in just a moment.
The JMP and branch instructions also cause
the address of the following instruction,
i.e., the PC+4 value, to be written to the
RC register.
When WDSEL is 0, the "0" input of the WDSEL
MUX is used to select the PC+4 value as the
write-back data.
Here's how the data flow works.
The output of the PC+4 adder is is routed
to the register file and WERF is set to 1
to enable that value to be written at the
end of the cycle.
Meanwhile, the value of RA register coming
out of the register file is connected to the
"2" input of the PCSEL MUX.
So setting PCSEL to 2 will select the value
in the RA register as the next value for the
PC.
The rest of the control signals are "don't
cares", except, of course for the memory write
enable (MWR), which can never be "don't care"
lest we cause an accidental write to some
memory location.
The branch instruction requires an additional
adder to compute the target address by adding
the scaled offset from the instruction's literal
field to the current PC+4 value.
Remember that we scale the offset by a factor
of 4 to convert it from the word offset stored
in the literal to the byte offset required
for the PC.
The output of the offset adder becomes the
"1" input to the PCSEL MUX, where, if the
branch is taken, it will become the next value
of the PC.
Note that multiplying by 4 is easily accomplished
by shifting the literal two bits to the left,
which inserts two 0-bits at the low-order
end of the value.
And, like before, the sign-extension just
requires replicating bit ID[15], in this case
fourteen times.
So implementing this complicated-looking expression
requires care in wiring up the input to the
offset adder, but no additional logic!
We do need some logic to determine if we should
branch or not.
The 32-bit NOR gate connected to the first
read port of the register file tests the value
of the RA register.
The NOR's output Z will be 1 if all the bits
of the RA register value are 0, and 0 otherwise.
The Z value can be used by the control logic
to determine the correct value for PCSEL.
If Z indicates the branch is taken, PCSEL
will be 1 and the output of the offset adder
becomes the next value of the PC.
If the branch is not taken, PCSEL will be
0 and execution will continue with the next
instruction at PC+4.
As in the JMP instruction, the PC+4 value
is routed to the register file to be written
into the RC register at end of the cycle.
Meanwhile, the value of Z is computed from
the value of the RA register while the branch
offset adder computes the address of the branch
target.
The output of the offset adder is routed to
the PCSEL MUX where the value of the 3-bit
PCSEL control signal, computed by the control
logic based on Z, determines whether the next
PC value is the branch target or the PC+4
value.
The remaining control signals are unused and
set to their default "don't care" values.
We have one last instruction to introduce:
the LDR or load-relative instruction.
LDR behaves like a normal LD instruction except
that the memory address is taken from the
branch offset adder.
Why would it be useful to load a value from
a location near the LDR instruction?
Normally such addresses would refer to the
neighboring instructions, so why would we
want to load the binary encoding of an instruction
into a register to be used as data?
The use case for LDR is accessing large constants
that have to be stored in main memory because
they are too large to fit into the 16-bit
literal field of an instruction.
In the example shown here, the compiled code
needs to load the constant 123456.
So it uses an LDR instruction that refers
to a nearby location C1: that has been initialized
with the required value.
Since this read-only constant is part of the
program, it makes sense to store it with the
instructions for the program, usually just
after the code for a procedure.
Note that we have to be careful to place the
storage location so that it won't be executed
as an instruction!
To route the output of the offset adder to
the main memory address port, we'll add ASEL
MUX so we can select either the RA register
value (when ASEL=0) or the output of the offset
adder (when ASEL=1) as the first ALU operand.
For LDR, ASEL will be 1, and we'll then ask
the ALU compute the Boolean operation "A",
i.e., the boolean function whose output is
just the value of the first operand.
This value then appears on the ALU output,
which is connected to the main memory address
port and the remainder of the execution proceeds
just like it did for LD.
This seems a bit complicated!
Mr. Blue has a good question:
why not just put the ASEL MUX on the wire
leading to the main memory address port and
bypass the ALU altogether?
The answer has to do with the amount of time
needed to compute the memory address.
If we moved the ASEL MUX here, the data flow
for LD and ST addresses would then pass through
two MUXes, the BSEL MUX and the ASEL MUX,
slowing down the arrival of the address by
a small amount.
This may not seem like a big deal, but the
additional time would have to be added the
clock period, thus slowing down every instruction
by a little bit.
When executing billions of instructions, a
little extra time on each instruction really
impacts the overall performance of the processor.
By placing the ASEL MUX where we did, its
propagation delay overlaps that of the BSEL
MUX, so the increased functionality it provides
comes with no cost in performance.
Here's the data flow for the LDR instruction.
The output of the offset adder is routed through
the ASEL MUX to the ALU.
The ALU performs the Boolean computation "A"
and the result becomes the address for main
memory.
The returning data is routed through the WDSEL
MUX so it can be written into the RC register
at the end of the cycle.
The remaining control values are given their
usual default values.