So far we've talked about assembling instructions.
What about data?
How do we allocate and initialize data storage
and how do we get those values into registers
so that they can be used as operands?
Here we see a program that allocates and initializes
two memory locations using the LONG macro.
We've used labels to remember the addresses
of these locations for later reference.
When the program is assembled the values of
the label N and factN are 0 and 4 respectively,
the addresses of the memory locations holding
the two data values.
To access the first data value, the program
uses a LD instruction, in this case one of
convenience macros that supplies R31 as the
default value of the Ra field.
The assembler replaces the reference to the
label N with its value 0 from the symbol table.
When the LD is executed, it computes the memory
address by adding the constant (0) to the
value of the Ra register (which is R31 and
hence the value is 0)
to get the address (0) of the memory location
from which to fetch the value to be placed
in R1.
The constants needed as values for data words
and instruction fields can be written as expressions.
These expressions are evaluated by the assembler
as it assembles the program and the resulting
value is used as needed.
Note that the expressions are evaluated at
the time the assembler runs.
By the time the program runs on the Beta,
the resulting value is used.
The assembler does NOT generate ADD and MUL
instructions to compute the value during program
execution.
If a value is needed for an instruction field
or initial data value, the assembler has to
be able to perform the arithmetic itself.
If you need the program to compute a value
during execution, you have to write the necessary
instructions as part of your program.
One last UASM feature: there's a special symbol
".", called "dot", whose value is the address
of the next main memory location to be filled
by the assembler when it generates binary
data.
Initially "." is 0 and it's incremented each
time a new byte value is generated.
We can set the value of "." to tell the assembler
where in memory we wish to place a value.
In this example, the constant 0xDEADBEEF is
placed into location 0x100 of main memory.
And we can use "." in expressions to compute
the values for other symbols, as shown here
when defining the value for the symbol "k".
In fact, the label definition "k:" is exactly
equivalent to the UASM statement "k = ."
We can even increment the value of "." to
skip over locations, e.g., if we wanted to
leave space for an un initialized array.
And that's assembly language!
We use assembly language as a convenient notation
for generating the binary encoding for instructions
and data.
We let the assembler build the bit-level representations
we need and to keep track of the addresses
where these values are stored in main memory.
UASM itself provides support for values, symbols,
labels and macros.
Values can be written as constants or expressions
involving constants.
We use symbols to give meaningful names to
values so that our programs will be more readable
and more easily modified.
Similarly, we use labels to give meaningful
names to addresses in main memory and then
use the labels in referring to data locations
in LD or ST instructions, or to instruction
locations in branch instructions.
Macros hide the details of how instructions
are assembled from their component fields.
And we can use "." to control where the assembler
places values in main memory.
The assembler is itself a program that runs
on our computer.
That raises an interesting "chicken and egg
problem":
how did the first assembler program get assembled
into binary so it could run on a computer?
Well, it was hand-assembled into binary.
I suspect it processed a very simple language
indeed, with the bells and whistles of symbols,
labels, macros, expression evaluation, etc.
added only after basic instructions could
be assembled by the program.
And I'm sure they were very careful not loose
the binary so they wouldn't have to do the
hand-assembly a second time!