Our first task is to work on the datapath
logic needed to execute ALU instructions with
two register operands.
Each instruction requires the same processing
steps:
Fetch, where the 32-bit encoded instruction
is read from main memory from the location
specified by the program counter (PC).
Decode, where the opcode field (instruction
bits [31:26]) is used to determine the values
for the datapath control signals.
Read, where the contents of the registers
specified by the RA and RB fields (instruction
bits [20:16] and [15:11]) are read from the
register file.
Execute, where the requested operation is
performed on the two operand values.
We'll also need to compute the next value
for the PC.
And Write-back, where the result of the operation
is written to the register file in the register
specified by the RC field (instruction bits
[25:21]).
The system's clock signal is connected to
the register file and the PC register.
At the rising edge of the clock, the new values
computed during the Execute phase are written
to these registers.
The rising clock edge thus marks the end of
execution for the current instruction and
the beginning of execution for the next instruction.
The period of the clock, i.e., the time between
rising clock edges, needs to be long enough
to accommodate the cumulative propagation
delay of the logic that implements the 5 steps
described here.
Since one instruction is executed each clock
cycle, the frequency of the clock tells us
the rate at which instructions are executed.
If the clock period was 10ns, the clock frequency
would be 100 MHz and our Beta would be executing
instructions at 100 MIPS!
Here's a sketch showing the hardware needed
for the Fetch and Decode steps.
The current value of the PC register is routed
to main memory as the address of the instruction
to be fetched.
For ALU instructions, the address of the next
instruction is simply the address of the current
instruction plus 4.
There's an adder dedicated to performing the
"PC+4" computation and that value is routed
back to be used as the next value of the PC.
We've also included a MUX used to select the
initial value for the PC when the RESET signal
is 1.
After the memory propagation delay, the instruction
bits (ID[31:0]) are available and the processing
steps can begin.
Some of the instruction fields can be used
directly as-is.
To determine the values for other control
signals, we'll need some logic that computes
their values from the bits of the opcode field.
Now let's fill in the datapath logic needed
to execute ALU instructions with two register
operands.
The instruction bits for the 5-bit RA, RB
and RC fields can be connected directly to
the appropriate address inputs of the register
file.
The RA and RB fields supply the addresses
for the two read ports and the RC field supplies
the address for the write port.
The outputs of the read data ports are routed
to the inputs of the ALU to serve as the two
operands.
The ALUFN control signals tell the ALU what
operation to perform.
These control signals are determined by the
control logic from the 6-bit opcode field.
For specificity, let's assume that the control
logic is implemented using a read-only memory
(ROM), where the opcode bits are used as the
ROM's address and the ROM's outputs are the
control signals.
Since there are 6 opcode bits, we'll need
2^6 = 64 locations in the ROM.
We'll program the contents of the ROM to supply
the correct control signal values for each
of the 64 possible opcodes.
The output of the ALU is routed back to the
write data port of the register file, to be
written into the RC register at the end of
the cycle.
We'll need another control signal, WERF ("write-enable
register file"), that should have the value
1 when we want to write into the RC register.
Let me introduce you to Werf, the 6.004 mascot,
who, of course, is named after her favorite
control signal, which she's constantly mentioning.
Let's follow the flow of data as we execute
the ALU instruction.
After the instruction has been fetched, supplying
the RA and RB instruction fields, the RA and
RB register values appear on the read data
ports of the register file.
The control logic has decoded the opcode bits
and supplied the appropriate ALU function
code.
You can find a listing of the possible function
codes in the upper right-hand corner of the
Beta Diagram handout.
The result of the ALU's computation is sent
back to the register file to be written into
the RC register.
Of course, we'll need to set WERF to 1 to
enable the write.
5.oo Here we see one of the major advantages
of a reduced-instruction set computer architecture:
the datapath logic required for execution
is very straightforward!
The other form of ALU instructions uses a
constant as the second ALU operand.
The 32-bit operand is formed by sign-extending
the 16-bit two's complement constant stored
in the literal field (bits [15:0]) of the
instruction.
In order to select the sign-extended constant
as the second operand, we added a MUX to the
datapath.
When its BSEL control signal is 0, the output
of the register file is selected as the operand.
When BSEL is 1, the sign-extended constant
is selected as the operand.
The rest of the datapath logic is the same
as before.
Note that no logic gates are needed to perform
sign-extension - it's all done with wiring!
To sign-extend a two's complement number,
we just need to replicate the high-order,
or sign, bit as many times as necessary.
You might find it useful to review the discussion
of two's complement in Lecture 1 of Part 1
of the course.
So to form a 32-bit operand from a 16-bit
constant, we just replicate it's high-order
bit (ID[15]) sixteen times as we make the
connection to the BSEL MUX.
During execution of ALU-with-constant instructions,
the flow of data is much as it was before.
The one difference is that the control logic
sets the BSEL control signal to 1, selecting
the sign-extended constant as the second ALU
operand.
As before, the control logic generates the
appropriate ALU function code and the output
of the ALU is routed to the register file
to be written back to the RC register.
Amazingly, this datapath is sufficient to
execute most of the instructions in the Beta
ISA!
We just have the memory and branch instruction
left to implement.
That's our next task.